[MUSIC] Welcome to Section 4 of the
course.
This is going to be the last section
where ML is our primary programming
language, so I thought a short
introduction just to remind us where we
are and where we're going would be
helpful.
So we've done most of what we need to do
with ML.
We've studied pattern matching, Haro
functions, closures.
All the main, big topics.
But there's 4 things that I put off, just
because we didn't need them for the
homework, but I think complete our proper
introduction to this first half of the
course.
So in this section, which may end up
being a little bit shorter than the
others, we're going to study type
inference, how ML has has been able to
figure out, what types all our functions
and bindings should have.
mutual recursion.
I just never showed you how to have
multiple recursive functions all call
each other.
The big topic I'm most excited about is
the module system.
How we're going to be able to write
modules that can hide things,
keep things private from other parts of
the program and ML has a very elegant
module system for that purpose.
We will do just the basics of it.
And then a discussion, it's more
conceptual, about when two functions in a
language like ML are equivalent and you
can replace one with another.
Now this section is not going to have a
homework assignment associated with it.
we have time in the course for I believe
7 homework assignments and we will have 8
or possibly 9 sections.
And that will give us more time to study
for the mid-term which sort of fits
nicely at the end of this section.
So the midterm will have short answer
questions covering all of the first 4
sections, including some questions on
this material, as well as the earlier
sections.
And then after that we'll move onto more
concepts, and we'll switch our
programming language to Racket cause
it'll be better suited for the concepts
we want to cover with that.