As we begin our study of type inference I
want to start by making sure whereas
clear as we can be about what type
inference is and what problem its trying
to solve.
So, when you have type-checking at
compile time, which is called static
type-checking, it lets us reject programs
before we ever run them.
And we do this to prevent the possibility
of some errors.
So statistically typed programming
languages are languages that have this
feature.
So you might have some function that does
not type check because potentially it
might say try to call a number, treat a
number as.
The function.We don't actually have to
execute the function to get that error,
we get that error before we ever run a
program.Conversely dynamically type
languages do little or perhaps none of
that's what of checking so, you have to
actually not just call the function but
actually get the particular problematic
expression.
To evaluate with variables bound to the
right things before you see the potential
error.
Now the relative advantages of static and
dynamic type-checking is a major concept
in the course and we're going to study it
but I want to do that after we've used
the dynamically typed programming
language for a while.
And Racket is one so we'll be in good
shape Right there.
At this point we've only seen ML and ML
like Java, C, Scala etc.
is statically typed.
It has this property that certain things
don't type check even before we run them.
And what all of these statically typed
languages have in common is every
variable we introduce is given a type.
Every binding has some type.
And for the scope that it's usable, it
maintains that type and can only hold
values of that type.
So we keep our strings, and our booles,
and our functions and out tuples
separate.
Now the reason why I'm emphasizing this
is that, even though ML is statically
typed, it is implicitly typed.
Ever since the beginning of section 2 or
so, we have not been writing down the
types of any of our variables.
We never did for valve bindings, and only
at the beginning of the course when you
were using hash 1 and hash 2, did we for
arguments to a function.
So just because ml is implicitly typed,
it can sometimes be confusing to remember
that it is statically typed.
In this first function here f, the 2
variables f and x both have a type.
F has type n 0 int, x has type int and
they're just as statically typed as if
this were Java or C, where we have to
write down the types of all of our
variables when we introduce them.
That is why when we have a function like
g we under put the type error, the reason
for the type error here is that one of
the type checking rules in and all is
that the then branch and the else branch
of the conditional have to have the same
type.
So that, that can be the type of the
entire if expression and in this case
therefore the return type of g and so
when these don't match like a bull here
and a int here we get a type error.This
is exactly the sort of thing in a
dynamically typed language I would expect
to be allowed and depending on the
argument to g you either get back a bull.
Or an int, okay, so in that sense of
static type checking ML is more like Java
or C and less like JavaScript or Python.
So what then is the type inference
problem? The type inference problem is
take a program, like we saw in the
previous slide, and try to give every
variable and binding and expression in
that program a type.
Such that, if you wrote down all those
types, type checking would succeed.
So we need to infer all the types such
that the program would type check.
If we cannot do so, if it is impossible
to give such types, like in that second
example where true and x * 2 simply do
not have the same type, then it's the
role of type inference to fail, and
presumably give some sort of error
message.
So, in principle, you could set it up
exactly like this.
You could have a type inference procedure
that wrote down the types for everything,
and then have a type checker, that
checked those types.
In practice, and in implementation of a
language like SML, we often don't
separate things out so cleanly.
We just have the type inferencer and type
checker be the same.
Staying, and either your program
type-checks, or it does not.
The last thing I want to emphasize,
before the next segment, when we get into
type inference for ML, this segment was
really about type inference in general,
and what it is.
As the type inference can be easy, or
difficult, or impossible, it depends, on
the type system, that That you're trying
to infer types four.
So as 2 extreme view points if if every
program type checks, that's very easy to
infer.
Just say yes, if no program type checks
that's also easy to infer, just say no.
So type inference doesn't get easier or
harder necessarily by having a type
system that accepts more programs or
excepts fewer programs.
It's not so simply to figure that out.
This is part of the difficulty of
language design if you want type
inference.
But the reason why we're going to study
ML type inference is that it is a bit
subtle, but it's also extremely elegant,
and it may at this point in the course
seem magical.
We've seen these polymorphic types sort
of inferred for us, but through a series
of examples I want to convince you that
it's actually a fairly elegant and
straightforward procedure.