[MUSIC] It's now time to take our module
example from the previous segment and
figure our a good signature to give it.
And I think this will be much more
interesting than you might imagine.
So from what we know so far, what would
be natural is defined as signature like
you see on the slide that hides the two
helper functions that we don't want the
outside world to know about.
So we make no mention of GCD and reduce,
but the outside world does need to know
there's a type rational that can be
wholes or fracs, that there's an
exception bad frac, there's a make frac
that takes a numerator and a denominator
and returns a rational.
Add takes 2 rationals, returns a rational
and to string takes a rational and
returns a string.
And this signature is something we can
give to our structure.
It will type check and then the outside
world will not be able to use GCD or
reduced directly.
So, that's okay.
It's not a bad start.
But it turns out we made a crucial error.
And that is, that by revealing the data
type definition, this first line here
where we told the outside world how
rational was implemented clients can
violate all of our invariants and they'll
be able to use the library in the way
that will not lead to the results and the
behavior that we want.
Now we could include a comment, or we
could ask clients to please, please
promise not to build their own rationals.
To always call make frac, because make
frac checks for certain things, and
insta, institutes our invariants when we
get started.
But I don't know about you, I have
certainly found that when I put things in
comments and documentation, my library
clients don't always follow those rules.
And it would be much better if my
language had a way to enforce those
rules.
And it does, and I'll show that to you in
just a second.
But first, let me emphasize what goes
wrong here under this first signature
rational A.
The key problem is that clients will be
able to call the frac constructor
directly.
They could make a frac out of an 1 and 0
or a 3 and -2, or 9 and 6 and these are
all forms of values that the functions in
my library assume do not exist and once
they do exist, all sorts of things could
end up going wrong.
So let me show some slightly different
examples I've already included everything
here exactly as you've seen it, so I have
this structure rational 1 that has the
signature you see right here,
okay? And now let me just write some
things that work and some things that
don't work.
So suppose I wanted to add 2 rationals
and suppose first I do this correctly and
I call make frac.
So 1,0 and make_frac of say two-thirds,
okay? If I do this, I get the exception
bad frac which is the correct behavior.
But if my client does not follow the
rules and makes a frac directly then it
goes in an infinite loop it turns out and
we could try to figure out why I think
it's related to GCD.
But we don't want to figure this out, we
want to keep clients from doing something
like this.
Like this, alright.
here's something else they might do if I
just had negative denominator I think I
end up overflowing.
Again because the arithmetic just assumed
in the module there wouldn't be a
negative denominator and if there is
certain things are not behaving correctly
and as a final even simpler example.
Remember, one of the things we promised
clients is that we would always print
everything in reduced form.
But if they just called to string with a
frac directly, we're just going to get
nine slash six.
Because you may recall that our to string
code which you see here assumes its
argument was already reduced.
And this is again something our client is
able to violate,
okay? So this is what we want to try to
prevent, and here's the intuition.
The intuition is that an ADT should hide
the concrete representation of a type.
That way clients will never be able to
make anything of the type without going
through our functions like make frac.
That way we can get those invariants
installed and then out functions can keep
them, so here's how you might think to do
this.
Let's just take the signature we had
before and take out the data type
definition don't tell clients that it can
be built from a whole constructor or a
frac constructor.
So this does not work here,
and the reason is the type checker sees
these types rational and says I've never
heard of such a thing,
right?
It'll just give an error and says, you,
you can't, you can't just make up type
names like that.
I need to know there's a type rational
otherwise I, I think you just, you know,
had a typo.
Alright,
so that's good the type checker is
helping us.
Somehow what we want to do is tell the
type checker, that for this signature,
yes, rational is a type.
But no, I don't want clients to know
anything more about it.
And that is an absolutely crucial idea,
which is known as an abstract type.
You can know the type is exists, but you
cant know it's definition.
So this is how we do this in ML, this is
a feature provided by ML, which is in
signatures you can just write type and
the name of a type.
And if you have no equals and no more
information, it means what I just said.
The type exists, but the outside world
can't know what it is.
So here is a signature I like very much.
I'll call it rational B,
and it tells clients what they can know
about rational.
It says you can know there's a type
rational.
You can know there's an exception
BadFrac.
You can know that make_frac returns a
rational given 2 int's.
Add can take 2 rationals and return a
rational to string can take a rational
and return a string.
And if we gave Rational1 this signature,
we will still be able to try all the
examples that use make_frac correctly,
but the outside world no longer knows
there is a frac constructor.
Capital FRAC, and so it won't be able to
create any of those vowels that violate
our invariance.
So this is a really big deal, there is
nothing a client can do not to violate
our invariance.
We could take the structure we studied
carefully in the previous segment and
this signature and convince ourselves
that all of our properties will always
hold, here is the intuition of the
argument.
How we will make it rational?
The first rational acclaim ever makes has
to be made make_frac, because this is all
they have to create rationals, you can't
call add until you have a rational.
You can't call to string until you have a
rational.
So, you're going to have to start with
make_frac.
We could study the code for make_frac and
convince ourselves that it gets all the
invariants and properties correctly, no
zero denominator, no negative denominator
fraction in reduced form.
After that, the only thing you can do
with rationals is add them together and
convert them to strings and we would
similarly convince ourselves that those
functions were implemented correctly.
Now to the outside world it can do what
it wants with the rational values it can
put them in lists, it can pass them to
functions it can put them in tuples, but
the only operations it can perform that
access the pieces Are those provided in
our library.
Now, the reason why our structure
actually has this signature, is because
it does define everything.
Defines make_frac added to string and can
have these types and it does define a
type rational.
It does it with a data type binding, that
is a perfect good way to define a type.
The outside world just doesn't know you
did it with a data type binding, and it
certainly doesn't know that details of
data type binding. And this is how you
use signatures of abstract types to
properly enforce obstructions and
implement abstract data types.
So, what we have now are two powerful
ways to use a signature to hide things
from clients.
The first one is to deny bindings exist.
That if you leave val-bindings,
fun-bindings, constructors and so on out
of your signature, they simply don't
exist to clients.
But, the second more sophisticated and
more exciting way to hide things, is to
take a type definition.
Tell the outside world that yes you have
defined this type, but I'm not going to
tell you how I did it, and that's
important, so that we can say that make
frac.
Returns a rational and takes 2 rationals
and returns a rational without revealing
what the rational actually is.
We'll see some other things that
signatures can hide in, in, one of the
later segments on modules but these are
the 2 things I hope you'll always
remember.
Now before we finish up this segment, I
want to show you a third signature that's
also in the code file that's posted with
these materials and this is just a little
bit cute.
So it turns out that if you look at the
data type binding for this module which I
have right here, It was a problem for our
invariance, to export the frac
constructor, and I showed you a bunch of
examples of that.
But it turns out, it would be fine, to
export the whole constructor.
That our library doesn't mind, any int,
past the whole.
So you cant get in trouble that, that's,
has to do with our particular properties
in invariance, but it turns out you can
convince yourself it would be okay, if
clients used whole directly, okay? So we
actually can export it and we can do it
with this signature.
It turns out we could go ahead and tell
clients that there is a function whole
with a capital W of type int arrow
rational.
And if you take this structure as we've
already defined it and type check it
against this signature, ML allows it.
And that's kind of surprising perhaps,
but the reason why is when it sees this
data type binding, it remembers all the
way back from when we first learned data
types.
That this defines a number of things.
It defines a type rational yes, but also
a function whole of type int or a
rational, Frac of int*int, a rational, as
well as Whole and Frac being allowed to
be used in patterns.
Signatures let us hide some things and
reveal some things.
And in this particular example, ML will
allow us to expose that there is a
function Whole of type int rational.
There is a type rational, but still hide
all the other things that data type
binding gave us.
This is a bit of a peculuraity to ML, I
don't think this is the most important
feature in a language, but I do find it
cute and I find it, that it emphasizes
that signatures get to expose some things
and hide other things.
And there's just a particular way we
could let clients do a little bit more.
They can call Whole directly rather than
having to call make_frac with a second
argument of int.