At this point in our study of modular
systems, I just want to give a more
precise definition of what is called
signature matching.
So we have a structure, we have a
signature, we want to know if the
structure can have that signature.
This is what the type checker has to
check,
and that's the process of signature
matching.
So as usual, we had our informal notion
of well, the structure has to have
everything the signature says it has,
but we can give it a more precise and
elegant definition of exactly what the
rules are.
So, I have the basic idea here on the
slide.
If you have some structure Foo and you
want to know if it has signature BAR, you
go through everything in BAR and make
sure that Foo provides it in an
appropriate way.
So let's go through the various
possibilities.
If in the signature BAR there's a full
type definition, not just an abstract
type, but maybe say a data type binding
or a type synonym,
well then the module better provide that
data type binding.
It better have all of those constructors.
On the other hand, if the signature bar
just has an abstract type, like we built
up to in the previous segment, something
like type rational,
then all we have to check is that indeed
the structure Foo defines such a type.
It could define it with a type synonym,
it could define it with a data type
binding.
We've seen a data type binding.
I'll show you a type synonym in a couple
segments.
Now if bar has a val-binding, then the
structure better provide that
val-binding.
It could do it with a val-binding.
It could do it with a function binding.
That doesn't matter.
It does have to provide it, and it has to
have something of the appropriate type.
Now, this is the interesting part, okay.
So the type that, that binding has inside
the module does not have to be the same
as the type it has outside the module. It
has to be related.
Now inside the module it could have a
more general type.
Back in section 2, we actually studied
the idea of one type being more general
than another.
For example, inside the module, it could
have type alpha arrow alpha, quote a
arrow quote a, and in the signature, we
could say it has type, string arrow
string.
Since string arrow string is less general
than alpha arrow alpha, that would be
okay.
I'll show you an example soon where
that's actually useful.
Also, the type in the module doesn't deal
with abstract types,
okay.
So inside the module, maybe we know what
a rational is, or what some type synonym
is,
but out in the signature it might just be
abstract.
And I'll show you an example of that as
well in a future segment.
So really what you have to do is take the
type the signature claims, take the type
that it has in the module based on type
checking and type inference, and see if
the relation between those 2 types are
okay.
It does not have to be exactly the same
type.
It just has to be something that is that
it makes sense as a way to expose that at
a possibly more restrictive type.
Tell clients less about how the function
can be used, but everything you tell
clients has to be true enough that
clients can use it that way.
And then as the final details here if an
exception is declared in the signature
bar then Foo needs to declare that
exception.
That makes sense.
And these are really the rules.
Now the thing that's not in any of these
bullet points, is that the structure foo
can have bindings that aren't mentioned
in bar at all.
And we know that's true, and that's
actually implied by these bullets.
All you do is you take everything that's
in bar and you make sure foo defines it
appropriately.
Whatever else Foo happens to define is
just fine, and that's our more precise
definintion of signature matching and now
we can go on to see some additional
structures that match signatures in some
interesting ways.