Let's finish our study of module systems in this segment by just avoiding
one common misunderstanding about multiple structures with the same signature.
We've seen you can have multiple structures with the same signature,
that signature can have an abstract type.
But each implementation of the signature,
introduces a new type which is different from the other structure's types.
So let me show you what's going on here in the REPL.
I've already loaded a file that defines all three signatures.
So here's signature A, then signature B,
then signature C. And it defines
all three structures which I've already shown you and I made
each of them specifically say that they provide signature rational C. So,
they all provide the same signature.
Now, of course, I can do something like
Rational1.toString(Rational1.make_frac(9,-6))
and I should
get back negative three over two.
Okay. And I could use the other structures as well like here's maybe rational
three which we know implements the fractions in a different way,
but they're equivalent structures,
I always get the same result.
What you cannot do is mix and match your modules.
This is simply not going to type check.
You cannot take the result of
rational ones make_frac and pass it to rational threes toString.
After all, that better not type check.
They're not even implemented the same way.
This would be passing an int*int where we expect a data type.
But even if they were implemented the same way like with
rational two and rational one it still doesn't type check.
That is also a good thing.
If we allowed this,
we would be breaking our abstractions.
I believe something like this,
especially if I flipped it around and did it the other way,
would not do what we want.
Because we know that Rational2.make_frac doesn't reduce
the fraction and we know Rational1.toString doesn't reduce the fraction.
So if we allowed this it would print
out negative 9 slash 6 which is not what is supposed to happen.
And the reason why this doesn't type check is entirely straightforward.
If I look at Rational1.toString it has type Rational1.Rational arrow
string whereas Rational2.toString has type Rational2.Rational arrow string.
They're not the same type.
They are two abstract types.
We do not know if they are the same or different.
They may be different.
They are not allowed to be confused with each other and
that's essential for enforcing our abstractions.
Two modules can have
the same signature but they still define different types.
As a result if you try to mix and match things don't type check,
and that's good because each library expects the values it's passed to
be from itself not from
some other library that can be enforcing different properties or different invariants.
This is a crucial feature for your type system.
And in fact it's essential both for ML's type system to not allow
confusing instance strings as well as for making sure that
abstractions are actually enforced and your libraries behave properly.