[MUSIC] The last major topic we will
consider in this section is a deeper and
more precise understanding of when 2
functions are the same, or I'll call them
equivalent.
So this is important to look at
carefully.
I'm not going to show you any new coding
idioms or clever new things or language
constructs.
But it's such a fundamental idea in
software engineering that I think it's
worth focusing on.
we're going to see that you can replace
one function with another if you're very
careful and you know what it means for
two things to be equivalent.
And we'll see that things are more likely
to be equivalent when you are using more
abstraction, and when you have fewer side
effects.
If you can assume that other computations
don't do things like mutate references or
print things out, then additional things
are equivalent.
So let me motivate why we're looking at
this.
I believe that developers, people
programming, think about equivalence all
the time.
When you are maintaining code and you say
oh, I have a nicer style way, I have a
nicer way to express this, what you're
really saying is to express the same
thing, or to express an equivalent thing,
no one would be able to tell that I did
this code clean up.
You are also thinking about this all the
time when you're looking at backward
compatibility.
Can I add new features without changing
how this software behaves for any of the
old features?
It still behaves equivalently for all old
possibilities.
Code optimization whether manual when
you're writing the code or if you're
implementing a language,
is all about equivalence.
Can I speed up this code without changing
how it behaves on any inputs? And finally
when we were studying our module system,
we did this a bit as well.
Can an external client tell if I replace
this implementation with another
implementation? Now, what we're going to
look at here is not necessarily related
to modules or abstract types.
Instead what we'll do is say, here are
two functions,
are they equivalent for all possible
calls to them? So, maybe I'm implementing
a library.
I don't know all the clients in my
library.
I might be putting this code up on the
Internet for people to use.
I want to be able to think about, could I
replace this function with this other
function, without any possible call to
these functions, ever being able to tell?
That's what equivalence is all about.
Now we need to define, what it means for
2 functions to behave the same way.
And I will say, that they have the same
observable behavior, if, given equivalent
arguments, they meet all of these bullet
points, you see here on the slide.
Clearly they need to always return the
same answer.
If 1 takes 3 and returns 7 and the other
takes 3 and returns 8, this is no good.
Right? But that's not enough.
They also have to have the same non
termination behavior if one of them
doesn't terminate on 9 The other needs to
not terminate on nine.
And similarly they need to terminate on
all the same arguments.
They have to have any effects that they
have on mutable references that other
parts of the program can see, be the
same.
If one of them updates a reference to a
different value than the other does,
then after the call completes, some other
code in the program might be able to tell
that you replaced the first function with
the sec, second function.
They have to have the same input/output
behavior.
We can't have one printing something and
the other not printing the same thing.
And then they have to raise the same
exceptions.
We can't have one of them choose to raise
an exception in a situation where the
other one doesn't.
And I may have even forgotten things
here, but I think this is a pretty good
list.
Alright? Now notice, it's going to be
easier for 2 functions to be equivalent
if users of these functions cannot use
them with as many arguments.
For example, if you have a nice strong
type system, that will ensure that say
these functions only take string star
string as our units.
And we don't have to think about, well
what would happen if someone passed an
int instead,
because no such calls will ever type
check.
We will also see that it's much easier
for two functions to be equivalent if our
language is a functional language where
there are fewer ways to make
side-effects.
And, sometimes people even assume that
you won't make side-effects, even if the
language allows them.
I'll show you an example of that in just
a second.
Kay?'
So, let's finish up this segment with a
few examples and then we'll move on to
some more universal notions of function
equivalents.
So on the top here I have 2 functions, f,
that are equivalent.
The function on the left takes in an
argument, returns x + x.
The one on the right takes in an argument
and returns y * x.
This is defined in an environment where y
is 2.
Both of these functions always double
their argument, they have no other side
effects,
they always terminate, they are
equivalent in every way.
No ML program using the function on the
left would ever be able to tell if you
swapped it out for the function on the
right.
And vice versa, so that's a good example.
Here's an example where you might be
surprised that the two functions are not
equivalent if we are not careful about
our assumptions.
So the function on the left, g, takes in
a function f in argument x and returns f
applied to x plus f applied to x.
The one on the right multiplies f applied
to x by y and y is bound to 2.
So these will always return the same
answer assuming f is a function that
always returns the same thing when given
the same argument, but, the code on the
left calls f twice, and the code on the
right calls f once.
And that is a problem if f could have
side effects.
Suppose it increments a reference every
time.
Well then the code on the left will set
that reference to 2 more than it used to
have.
The code on the right 1 more.
An even simpler example is if f always
prints something out.
Like this function here, if you pass this
for f, it prints out "hi", and then
returns it's argument.
The code on the left will print "hi"
twice, the code on the right will print
"hi" once.
So, when you are in a functional
programming language, we typically have
functions that don't do this sort of
thing.
And if you assume these things don't
happen, then the functions are
equivalent.
Some languages, like haskell is a good
example force a notion of pure functional
programming.
Most functions in the language, those
that you can pass to other functions like
this, cannot do things like print out.
And as a result, the corresponding code
in a language like haskell is equivalent
on the left and the right.
So this is sort of yet another advantage
of avoiding side effects in your code.
Let's do one more example.
Here are, is a slight, it's, it's a few
more lines of code but it's actually very
simple what's going on.
The function f here on the left, assumes
we have in our environment some functions
g and h.
it calls g with x, calls h with x and
returns a pair of the results.
The code on the right is the exact same,
except it just calls h and g in the
opposite order.
So unlike in the previous example,
there's no number of calls problem here.
Both of these call g once and call h
once.
So are they equivalent? Again if g and h
are pure functions that don't have side
effects, they just compute something and
return a result, then yes, they're
equivalent.
But if g and h can have side effects,
then no, not necessarily.
Suppose g prints something and h prints
something.
Well then the code on the left will print
those outputs in one order,
the code on the right will print them in
the opposite order.
Here's another example.
Suppose g sets some mutable reference,
and h reads that same mutable reference.
Then the code on left h is going to see
the new value after whatever g wrote to
it.
And in the code on the right, h is going
to see the value before g does it's
write.
Because h executes, before g executes.
So once you have mutation, side effects,
printing, we suddenly have to worry about
the order we do things,
and different orders, lead to functions
that are not equivalent.
But if we stick to a functional style,
where don't write functions with side
efefects,
then we do not have to worry about order,
and we can execute these functions in
either order.
With one final caveat.
That if g of x, and h of x both raise
exceptions, and raise different
exceptions.
Then the order could matter again.
And, the code on the left would raise one
exception, and the code on the right
would raise another exception.