[SOUND] In this segment, I'm going to
share with you some well-known
equivalences between functions.
Things that programming languages people
have studied very carefully and
understand well when two functions are
equivalent and what you have to be
careful of to make sure you're following
all the assumptions carefully.
So we'll just go through a few of these
examples.
The first one is actually by definition.
We've seen a bunch of examples of
syntactic sugar, and if something is
syntactic sugar, it's always equivalent
with the thing that is syntactic sugar
for.
That's really kind of the definition of
syntactic sugar.
So for example we saw that E1 and also E2
is sugar for if E1 then E2 else false.
So if you saw a function like you have
here on the left, takes an x and computes
x and g of x for some g that's presumably
in the environment,
you could always replace that with if x
then g of x else false,
which is not good style but a language
implementation might do that, so that it
only has to implement if then else and
not have to also implement and also by
duplicating a bunch of codes.
And you know you can go the other way if
you see something like on the right, it
would be a good style to replace it with
the thing on the left.
The thing to be careful about here is
evaluation order and also is only sugar
if you evaluate the arguments x first
then g of x only if x is false.
So, the code on the left is not
equivalent with this version you see
here, because the version on the right
always calls g or the version on the left
only calls g if x is false.
So that's our first example,
it is really by definition.
Here is another example.
This is the first of three that are sort
of a well understood by programming
language people, and we work hard when
designing our languages to make sure that
they hold by treating variables properly,
and so on.
And that is that you should be able to
rename the variables in your function
without causing problems.
So, I have code on the left here, takes
in x, returns x+y+x,
so 2x+14,
right?
The code on the right is exactly like the
code on the left, except it called the
function parameter z instead of calling
it x,
so it's z+y+z.
And we really want these to be
equivalent, because we shouldn't have a
language where the callee can have its
parameter name changed,
like you're cleaning up somebody's code
and you say, oh, that's not a very good
variable name, here is a better one, and
have suddenly callers be able to tell
that you've made that change.
So you really want in your language that
this equivalence holds.
That said, sometimes people get a little
sloppy, and think that this means you can
rename parameters to anything and have it
always work.
Here are two subtle mistakes where you
actually cannot do this.
First, suppose we took the code on the
left,
it's the same that we had up above, and
instead of replacing x with z, we
replaced x with y.
Well, if you just do that naively you end
up with f taking in y returning y+y+y.
That's not the same function.
The function f on the right multiplies
its argument by three,
the function on the left returns twice
its argument plus 14.
The mistake here is if you rename your
parameter to something that you were
already using in the function body to
refer to some outer thing, you're
introducing shadowing that was not there
before and your function is not
equivalent.
There is a related subtlety that comes up
where maybe y is not something already in
the environment, but instead, it's a
locally defined variable.
So here, the function on the left defines
a local variable y for three, returns
x+y.
So we know that this function just
returns its argument plus three.
The code on the right always returns six,
that's not the same thing.
Even though, again, all I did was replace
every x with y.
Now, this x I had here and x+y, is now
referring to the shadowing of y, the
three instead of the parameter.
So you have to be careful with this stuff
and not reuse variables you are already
using for some other purpose.
Let's do another one.
It turns out that you should always be
able to choose whether or not to use a
helper function without callers being
able to tell.
So here, I have some code on the left
that just, I think returns three times
its argument plus 14.
The code on the right also always returns
three times its argument plus 14, but it
does it by using this helper function f.
Alright? So the code on the right calls f
as a helper function the code on the left
does not use f. It shouldn't matter if I
move out some of the function body and
end to a properly used helper function.
So, that is all fine,
you just have to be careful that when you
do this, all the variables still refer to
what they did before.
So, in this slightly different example,
the code on the left is actually
returning three times its argument plus
seven, because of this shadowed y.
And the code on the right is using a
helper function f, and this helper
function f is the exact same code, as it
was up above, but now it doesn't mean the
same thing,
because f's is y and g's y are not the
same y,
right? And so, if I replace what was
z+y+z with (f z), I end up using 14 where
I should use seven.
And you can check this by typing into the
REPL that the function g on the left and
the function g on the right are, are
simply not the same.
The last one I want to talk about, we
actually have talked about plenty of
times, and this is unnecessary function
wrapping.
So on the left here, function g takes in
a y and returns f with y.
And as I've emphasized a few times now, a
simpler way to define g is to just say
val g=f, alright? They're both functions
that take in one argument and return
whatever the body of f returns, in this
case doubling the argument.
The [INAUDIBLE] the subtlety is you have
to be a little careful.
It's fine here where the function
recalling is just the variable, but if
instead we have an expression that we
evaluate to get a function, then whether
we're using function wrapping or not can,
can affect how many times we execute
things.
And if you have side effects like
printing or mutable references, that can
make a difference.
So let me show you two things that are
not equivalent.
On the left here, alright, I have f which
just doubles its argument,
h a zero argument function takes any unit
that when you call it, prints out hi and
then returns the function f.
So this function g of y, every time you
call g,
it calls h which prints hi, then takes
the result, and calls y with it.
So, function g, every time you call it,
prints hi and then doubles its argument.
The code on the right defines g the other
way by just saying val g equals h appied
to unit.
What that will do is we will one time
call h, which will print hi,
then return f, and so val g is bound to
f,
g and f are the same function.
So the code on the right will print hi
once before you ever call g and will
never print hi again.
Let me say that again.
The code on the right will print hi once
and never call and never print again.
They're both double argument.
The code on the left does not print at
all until you call g, but then prints
every time you call g.
So if h might have side effects like
this, it makes a difference,
they're not the same.
Okay.
One more that I just kind of like because
it helps explain let expressions and
functions.
We've also mentioned this once before,
but it's good to repeat it now that we're
talking about equivalents.
I claim that the code on the left and the
code on the right will always do the same
thing.
Here is why.
The code on the left evaluates as
follows.
Evaluate e1 to a value, extend the
environment so that x maps to that value,
evaluate e2, and that's your answer.
What about the code on the right?
Well, this is already a value on the
left.
So evaluate e1 to a value,
then, evaluate e2 in the environment
where x is bound the result of e1,
and that's our entire answer.
The left and the right do the exact same
sequence of steps.
They both evaluate e1, then evaluate e2
in the same extended environment, and
then return the result of e2.
So there's no way they can't be
equivalent.
And you really can think of these as
being the same expression as if one were
syntactic sugar for the other.
Now, in ML, there's a type system
difference, which is that the code on the
left can give x a polymorphic type.
The code on the right will never give x a
polymorphic type.
So there are programs, where the version
on the left type checks, and the version
on the right doesn't, but that's a detail
of ML's type system.
For any expressions that do both type
check, they are equivalent and will
always produce the same result.
So overall, I've now shown you, I think,
five examples of general situations where
two things are equivalent and some of the
subtleties where you have to think about,
shadowing, or side effects, and similar
ideas.
And, if you understand these subtle
distinctions, then you should understand
the role of variables and the meaning of
functions at a very fundamental level.
These things are not ML specific.
These are things that should be true
whenever you're programming with
variables and functions.