[MUSIC]
I want to finish our discussion of
function equivalence by dealing with
the fact that we have not been
talking about performance.
That we've ignored any
notion of how slow or
fast something is when saying
the two functions are equivalent.
This is just the definition from
a programming language perspective, and
that definition by ignoring performance
is both a feature and a limitation.
And I want to talk about the pluses and
minuses of ignoring performance
when talking about equivalence.
So, just to be clear,
this can make a big difference.
If you remember back to when we
studied the necessary efficiencies of
let expressions, I showed you an example
of computing the max of a list.
It was before pattern matching, so
it didn't look quite like this, but
the idea is the same.
It turns out the code on the left
is sometimes very, very slow.
Exponentially slow in
the length of certain lists.
So for a list of length 50, it could
literally take centuries to complete,
whereas the code on
the right is always fast.
It takes time proportional
to the length of the list.
But our definition of equivalence
said same side effects,
same termination behavior,
same result for any argument.
And technically, the code on the left,
if you're willing to wait a few centuries,
will terminate.
So by our definition,
these are equivalent to each other.
Now I acknowledge that in the real world,
these are not equivalent.
One of them is useful in many
situations where the other is not, but
our definition says that
they are equivalent.
So why is that a good thing,
and why is that a limitation?
Well, the way I like to think of
it is that in computer science,
there are many definitions of equivalence.
And in particular,
there are three that I use all the time.
And it's okay to have three definitions,
as long as I'm using them all
appropriately and when I need
to think at sort of that level.
So the first one is the programming
languages equivalence that we've
been studying here.
It says that given the same inputs,
you have the same outputs and
the same effects.
This is a feature, because what it would
do is let us take the bad version of max
on the previous slide.
Replace it with the good one, and
say it's okay I didn't break any clients,
because I did an equivalent thing,
and now, it performs better.
And performance is not part of the
definition of two things being the same.
Of course, it's a bad thing because it
would let you take the good one and
replace it with the bad one.
So as long as you use the definition
appropriately to justify good things and
not bad things,
it seems perfectly reasonable.
Now if you take a course
in data structures or
algorithms, you study
a different kind of equivalence.
This is asymptotic equivalence.
This is where you look at an algorithm,
and you decide its running time or
its running space or some other
property as it relates to its inputs.
And you're willing to
ignore small inputs and
just say as the inputs grow very large,
how does the running time react
proportionally to those
change in the inputs?
So this is good for studying algorithms.
It's good for understanding why one
version of max is better than another.
It's a very powerful definition
of equivalence or one thing being
better than another than being tied,
which is how equivalence comes in.
And it's very effective and you should be
familiar with that definition as well for
studying algorithms.
It's still limiting
because it says that if
one version of the program is
always four times faster or
nine times faster than the other one,
those programs are the same.
And the same way we might prefer
the nine times faster one, but
this definition says they're the same.
It's limiting the same way the programming
language definition is limiting,
just to a lesser extent, okay?
So there's a third definition
that sort of says wait,
practical considerations matter too.
We should account for those things.
And maybe when I'm performance-tuning
a system or I care about how it reacts to
representative workloads in the real
world, I should take care to make sure
that I don't swap out an implementation
that behaves fundamentally differently.
That maybe being 10% off is okay,
it's a little faster for some,
it's a little slower for others.
But I expect the system to behave mostly
the same, and because I'm dealing with
a live system or something like that, I
should only make sort of code changes that
are not going to have large effects
on performance, one way or the other.
The limitation of this more fine
grain notion of equivalence
is that it tends to focus
on inputs you've studied.
It doesn't study the general algorithm,
maybe even for
inputs you haven't seen, and it doesn't
study the general notion of equivalence,
maybe for clients of your code
library that you've never seen.
So for example, maybe if you focus on
systems equivalence for lists that only
have length up to 20, then maybe those
two versions of max look the same.
And it's a limitation of your thinking
that you don't realize that they actually
behave very differently for
inputs you haven't seen yet.
Okay, so I love all of these definitions.
My claim, which you've probably already
seen here at the bottom of the slide,
is that software developers and
computer scientists probably use all
of these definitions almost every day.
That when you're thinking about a problem
that you are working on, you're dealing
with abstractions, and those abstractions
allow different implementations.
And that's what programming
language equivalence is all about.
You're thinking about algorithms and
it's something general and
efficient in all cases, and that's
what the middle definition is about.
And then you're thinking about how your
software will perform in practice,
and are there inputs where you
need to tune it and improve it.
And that's more of a systems perspective.
None of these are better than the other.
They are all mental tools,
intellectual tools that we need
in order to reason about our
sophisticated software in today's world.