[MUSIC] So, let's now begin studying how
ML does type inference, how it figures
out the types for all our bindings.
And the way we're going to do this in the
next few segments is via examples.
So, given the general algorithm
implementing this and actually showing
how it does everything in the whole ML
language,
it's a slightly more advanced topic.
It would just take more time in the class
than I wish to spend on it especially if
you start supporting things like
functions defined in other functions.
But I think these series of examples
which we will do manually will be enough
for you to do type inference in your
head,
to look at a piece of ML code and in most
cases, be able to figure out that type or
understand what the ML type checker is
telling you and at least appreciate that
there is complete step-by-step procedure
that a computer could implement, that
infers types for code in ML.
So, here are the key steps we're going to
see for every example we do. This is how
Ml type infrence works.
First, it determines types of bindings in
order. So, unless you have mutual
recursion, in which case, it needs to
look at all of the things that call each
other at the same time as we'll see in a
later segment,
you look at the first binding and further
type for it, then the next binding and
further type for that, and so on.
And this is why you have to put helper
functions before the functions that use
them. Otherwise, you just get a type
error because things simple aren't in the
environment yet.
That's the semantics of ML.
But we do use those earlier bindings.
We already know their types before we
move on the the next one,
and we can use that.
Then for each binding,
say, a val binding, or file, fun binding,
we have to figure out the type of that
binding.
What we do is we analyze the definition
for all necessary facts.
These are essentially things that are
going to constrain the type in some way.
So, for example, if you see the
expression x > or = 0 inside a function
that takes a parameter x,
then x must have type int.
We simply look at the, function body in
order to figure out the type of the
function overall.
We gather all these facts, we figure out
what those constraints imply and
sometimes, they imply things that can't
possibly all be true.
That's exactly when you get a type error.
If we try to have in our function body x
> or = 0, and x concatenated with the
string high, then x has to be an int and
a string, and that's impossible and so
you get an error message.
Now, after we've figured out everything
the constraints imply and it's, if it's
not a contradiction, so the function or
variable will type-check.
Sometimes, we still have too few
constraints.
Things that can still be anything, it
doesn't matter what type they have.
And that's exactly when we get to infer a
polymorphic function, something with a a'
or a b' in it.
For example, if you have some function
argument that the function body never
uses, then it can clearly be anything, it
doesn't have to be the same as any other
type and we can introduce a fresh type
variable for that argument.
And then, there is this last step, which
is we have to enforce the value
restriction and we're going to ignore
that until one segment later in the
section that's focused just on the value
restriction.
Alright.
So, here's an example.
In future segments, we're going to do our
examples much more step-by-step very much
like the actual algorithm does it.
But do get a sense of how these
constraints work, let's just keep it
high-level and do this like more how
humans would do it.
So, we have two bindings, which we're
going to do in order.
First, val x = 42.
That's easy.
You see 42, it has type int so x must
have type int.
Now, we have this function f, so we know
it's going to have some function type.
We have to figure out the types of the
arguments and the return type.
So, we just look at the function body.
We see if y, then something,
well, y must have type bool.
We see z + x, z must have type int,
because x is an int and the only thing
you can add to an int is an int.
So great, y is a bool, z is an int.
There's a bunch of other things we have
to check.
We have to check that this x really does
have an appropriate argument for plus, it
does.
We have to check that this 0 has the same
type as the type of the expression in the
then branch,
it does. So, we're checking all this as
we're doing inference and now, we're
basically done.
The entire body here can have type int,
so the return type of f will be int. And
then, we notice that w over here never
got constrained.
w can be anything.
There are no facts that constrain, well,
it has to be in any way, so we know that
f must return an int, and we know it must
take a bool,
an int, and anything you want.
So, as that sort of last step, we turn
that anything you want into a type
variable and we give f this type, bool *
int * alpha arrow int.
And if we go over here and try it out,
we'll see that that's exactly what the
type checker says as well,
okay? So, one more point I want to make,
which is that a central feature of ML
type inference is that it does generate
these polymorphic expressions things with
type variables whenever it can.
This is great for code reuse and for
understanding functions.
It actually tells us in that example that
you know, you're never using the argument
w which is why I was able to give it this
more general type.
But I want to emphasize because it is
often confused, that type inference and
polymorphism with type variables are
entirely different concepts, you could
have a language that has type inference
and doesn't have type variable.
It would make it harder to infer a type
for that previous example but they really
are separate concepts. And conversely,
you can have languages with type
variables that do not have type
inference, that require programmers to
write down all the types. And Java, in
most situations, is a pretty good example
of that.
If you want a polymorphic function in
Java, you still have to write down all
the types of all the arguments of the
method that happens to be polymorphic.