In this segment we're going to
work through a couple examples
completely to show type inference.
Before we get to the examples,
let's make sure we remember
the key steps here, right?
The idea is to just collect
all the facts we need.
All the facts that have to be true for
something to type-check, and
use those to constrain
the type of the function.
So we're going to do two examples.
Neither of these examples will
involve polymorphism, and
then I'll change one of the examples so,
in fact, it doesn't type check at all, and
we'll see how type inference
can figure that out as well.
So, for the rest of the segment,we'll just
do this over here in the Emacs buffer, and
here's our first example.
It's a fairly silly code that
just takes in a pair of ints and
adds them with absolute value and
what not.
Of course, type inference doesn't
really reason about what the code does,
it just collects facts for type checking.
So it sees a function binding f, and
the first thing it realizes is for
some types, t1 and t2,
f has to have type t1 arrow t2.
Why?
Well, it must be a function, and
we know all functions take one argument.
So, that just has to be.
And in fact, if we look at the pattern,
which is just a variable here for
that argument, x has to have type T1.
There's no other way this function
binding is going to type check.
So now we can go on to the function body
to start gathering additional constraints,
and we first see this binding here,
and we say, okay,
I have two other variables I'm going
to have to figure out types for.
So y is going to have to
have some type t3 and
z is going to have to have some type t4.
And now we can start looking at all the
expressions and patterns in our program
to come up with additional constraints
among these types, t1, t2, and t3 and t4.
So the first thing we see from the pattern
match is that T1 has to be T3 star T4.
There's no other way for
this pattern where we match X
against Y comma Z to type check.
So, else pattern match
does not type check.
We can write down these reasons as we go
just to keep track of what we're doing.
Okay, so the next thing we could
look at is this function call here.
Now, remember, we've already type
checked all earlier bindings,
including things that are built into
the environment, and so we already
know that abs has type int arorw int,
and so for abs of Y to type check,
Y is going to have to have type int,
which means T3 has to equal int.
T3 being the type of y, T3 equals int..
All right, and that's everything
we get from this construct here.
Fortunately, getting int back
because plus will require that,
and that means that this expression
over here will have to be an int, and
since that's z,
we know that T4 has the equal int.
Ha!
This is because we added z to an int,
okay?
So given those three constraints, T1,
our argument type to our function is int
star int, and
we've already inferred the argument type.
Now, in terms of the result type,
we have that abs of y plus z has type int,
so the let expression has type int, so
the body of our function has type int,
and we know that T2 has to be
the type of the body of the function,
so T2 has to equal int and
once we've constrained T1 and T2,
that's the type of F, which is what
we were supposed to be inferring,
and we have our result.
So we just gathered facts and
continued to propagate those constraints
until we had the type we needed for F.
So now let's go on and
do a more interesting function.
A function that's actually useful for
something, and
that's summing all the elements in a list.
So, it's going to start
the same way sum is a function,
so it has to have type T1 arrow T2.
The argument has to be that T1.
Okay?
And now, we're just going to look at
these three lines, which actually have
quite a bit of information about
what T1 and T2 need to be.
So first, because we pattern match a T1,
we know that these other variables x
in that pattern has to have type T3,
and xs' has to have type T3 list.
And the reason why, sorry,
excuse me, is that if we have this
pattern here it can only match lists.
We know the second thing
has to be some list, and
the first thing has to be
an element of the list.
So that have to be related like this,
and in fact T1,
because we are pattern matching
against x's, has to equal T3 list.
There's no other way for
just the patterns,
just the things on the left of
the arrow to type check, okay?
So now we can look at this first branch
here, and we can say, oh, in fact,
since zero has type int, and that has
to be the type of the case expression,
and the case expression is the function
body, we can know already that
the return type has to be int,
because zero might be returned.
Okay, so we know our result type.
Now we just have to look
at this other branch and
figure out what's going on there.
So we know that T3 has to equal int, why?
Because x has type T3,
and we add x to something.
Okay, so we see that just from here,
I'm ignoring here by the way
the plus works on type real as well,
that's an issue I'm going to ignore
in this segment, but that's okay.
So we have quite a bit here,
we just have to deal with the sum of xs'.
And in fact, everything we already
know is enough to type check this.
So we know T3 is int, we know xs'' is
a T3 list, so this has to be an int list.
And int list is T3 list, which is T1.
That is the argument of sums, so
this recursive call already type-checks.
This recursive call has to give back a T2.
We know T2 is int, and that's good
because that's the argument to plus.
So it turns out we don't
get any new facts here.
We already had all the facts we needed.
And it turns out that just
from T1 equaling T3 list and
T3 equaling int,
we know T3 equals int list.
And from that and T2 equals int,
we know that F has typed int list
arrow int, just like we need and
just like we want sum to have.
So that's our second example.
Now what I'm going to do
is break this example, so
that nothing I did here is wrong.
This is correct.
Now let's go and change our code and see
what type inference would do in that case.
So I'm going to make a mistake here.
A mistake that will not type check.
If I make this mistake,
it will type check.
It will just be an infinite loop.
I'm more interested in this mistake,
where I try to recursively call
sum with the head of the list.
This is in fact,
now not going to type check.
So let's see why.
Everything starts how it did before.
Sum still has to be a T1 arrow T2.
xs still has to be that argument type.
x and xs' still have to have
the form T3 and T3 list for
some type T3, because they
are part of a list pattern, okay.
We still have that T1 has to equal
T3 list, and that's because of
xs being pattern matched
against x colon colon xs'.
We still have the T2 as equal int, because
of the zero here that's returning it.
We still have to have the T3 as int,
because we're adding it right here.
And now we're in a very
interesting situation.
So let me delete this, and
just focus in on this sum of X.
So we know from T1 equals T3 list, and T3
equals int, that T1 has to equal int list.
All right?
We also know that T3 equals int.
And that is the type of x.
So now I have to try to call
something that needs an int list,
with something of type int.
And that cannot type check.
There is no way to set up additional
constraints if that's going to work out.
So, I'm going to expect an error message
from the type checker, something along
the lines of I think x has type int and
I think some needs an int list.
Now, that's how we did
type inference here, and
that's the sort of error message we
would get if we went in this order.
But the type inferencer sometimes
has a bit of a mind of its own,
if you will, in the sense that it can
gather constraints in any order it likes
that will not affect its final result,
which is a deep property that's very cool.
But it will report an error as soon as it
gets to a situation where it
reaches the sort of contradiction.
The sort of thing where it says
int has to the equal int list, and
I know that's impossible.
So in fact when I try this out, I think
we'll see a different error message
in a different place in the code,
and that's okay.
I mean, you might not like it, but in some
sense, there are too many facts here for
them all to be true, and
the type error message is just going
to tell you about one of them.
So, if it goes in a slightly different
order, I think it actually complains
about case objects and
rules don't agree, it says that the,
I think what it's saying is that it
thought this was going to be a list, and
something else was an int,
honestly, I'm not really sure.
I can try to fix that by putting in
type annotations or what not, but
it's actually complaining up
here that it figured out that
xs is going to have to have type int,
because of how we called it down here.
But now you're matching
it against an int list.
So all it really did, if I had to guess,
was it worked on these facts
before the pattern matching facts, so
you got a different error message.
But it always detects,
because this is how type inference works,
that there's no way for the entire thing
to type check, and so it gives you one
error message about where it ran out of
room to try to figure out a good answer.
Okay, so that's our examples of
working through type inference.
We'll see more examples next, where we're
going to end up with polymorphic types for
the results of our function.