[MUSIC]
In this segment, we'll continue
with our type inference examples.
But the examples here are all going to
produce functions with polymorphic types.
So the key ideas, we'll start the same,
we're still going to collect all
the facts we need for type-checking.
We're still going to use these facts,
to constrain the type of the function.
The only difference is,
we'll end up with so few constraints,
that some of the arguments of our
result can still be any type.
And we'll use that information to
then figure out a polymorphic type.
Where some of the arguments and
results might need to be the same
type as some others, or not.
And then we'll have inferred
polymorphic functions.
So even though this is conceptually
perhaps more difficult,
it's actually easier ,because we have
fewer constraints to deal with, all right.
So let's just go over here, and let's
start with an example that's a lot like
the sum of the elements in the int list
that we saw in the previous segment.
This is just computing
the length of a list, but
we sort of know what
the answer's going to be.
We know that length on a list can work for
any type of list, so
we'll be building up to
showing a list -> int.
So we start, as we always do, by saying
that length better have T1 -> T2,
because it's a function, and its
argument better have the argument type.
Everything continues as we
did in the previous segment.
We notice that since we're
pattern-matching with x, and xs'.
There's going to have to be some
type T3 such that x has type T3, and
xs' is type T3 list,
just from that pattern.
Since we are pattern-matching against xs,
that means that T1, the type of xs,
has to equal T3 list.
We know from trying to return 0 as
a possible result of our function,
that T2 has to equal int.
And let's see, that's about it.
1 is type int, so
we can have that be an argument to plus.
length is our recursive call,
so we better call it with a T1.
While xs' has type T3 list, and
we already know that T1 = T3 list.
So we have no more constraints,
everything type-checks with
what I've already written down.
Therefore, putting all
those constraints together,
I end up with T3 list -> int,
and there's nothing more to say.
There's no constraint on what T3, the type
of the list elements of xs, need to be.
After all,
we never used any of the elements.
The contents of them, here, we could have
written a underscore there, instead of x.
So when we have a type like this, and
it cannot be further constrained?
What we do is we take all these T's that
are in there, there's one in this case,
and we replace them consistently
with type variables.
So in this example, we take that T3,
we replace it with the first letter of
the alphabet, 'a, -> int, and
that is the type we would give.
We would say for all types 'a, or alpha,
we can take in a list of 'a's and
return an int.
And that's how you type-check
the length function.
The 'a simply falls out, from having no
reason to prefer any particular type for
the list elements, okay?
So now,
let's do a more sophisticated example.
It's a less interesting function,
in terms of actually wanting to use it for
something.
But it's this function, f, that takes
in three arguments, x, y, and z,
and either returns (x, y, z) or (y, x, z).
Now you can look at this function and
say, well, if true,
it's always going to return this one.
But the type-checker follows
the type-checking rules.
And the type-checking rules for
a conditional is,
that we don't know which
branch might be returned.
So, let's just go through this and pretend
we're the computer, doing type inference.
So, f, I'm going to go ahead and
say it takes a T1 * T2 * T3 -> T4.
I could write out more steps, and
say well, it takes one argument, and
then that one argument is a pattern.
But if you just look at this, it's going
to have to take in some triple and
return some fourth type, T4.
And certainly, x1 has type T1,
y has type T2, and z has type T3, okay?
So at this point, we don't need to type
check this is true, that is type bool,
just like if/then/else needs.
And we just noticed that we're
either going to return this, or
we're going to return this.
So T4 either has to
have type T1 * T2 * T3,
or T4 has to have T2 * T1 * T3.
And in fact, those both have to be true,
because the type-checker doesn’t
know which of these might happen.
So the result type has to be the type
has to be the type of (x, y, z) and
the type of (y, x, z), so
both these constraints have to be true.
And the only way those can both
be true is if T1 = T2, right?
There's no other way for T4 for
to equal both of those things.
So that's enough, then we'll have
the same thing in both cases.
So if we put it all together,
the type of f is
T1 * T1 * T3, aecause I know T1 equals T2.
And I want to write down the type for f,
that incorporates all
the constraints I have.
-> not T4, but what T4 has to equal after
all my constraints, so T1 * T1 * T3.
And what this type says, is that x and
y have to have the same type,
z can have a possibly different type.
So there are no other constraints, there's
no reason to prefer anything in particular
for T1 and T3, and T1 and
T3 do not have to be the same type.
So at this point, we replace these
capital T's with 'a and 'b, consistently.
So we can pick any letters
of the alphabet, but
every T1 has to be 'a, and
every single T3 has to be 'b.
And so we end up with this type,
which is actually correct.
You can call this with any types
of arguments you want, but x and
y have to have the same type.
z can have the same type, or
it can have a different type.
It's exactly the sort of polymorphic type
we've seen before, now we just know how to
infer it, and how type inference works for
this sort of thing.
Okay, so that's our second example,
we saw two typed variables here.
Let's do a final example that's
actually going to have three,
and is actually one of
our favorite functions.
So here is function composition.
We've written this before, is takes
in two function arguments, f, g, and
returns a function that takes in an x and
returns f (g x).
And type inference will work for
this just fine.
compose takes a pair for
its arguments, so let's call that
T1 * T2 -> T3, where f has type T1,
and g has type T2.
All right, now we just need to
look at this function body,
and see that it is a anonymous function.
So we have this argument x, and
it's going to have to take in some T4.
And the body, being a function,
has type T4 -> T5.
The body of compose here has
to be some function, and
that has to equal
the return type of compose.
So let's say that T3 has to equal that,
okay, for some T4 and T5.
So from g being passed x,
which has type T4,
we actually know that T2,
which is g, g has to be a function.
If you're going to write g space x,
it's going to have to be a function,
so g has type T2.
T2 is going to have to equal T4 -> T6 for
some T6.
T4 is the type of x, okay.
So now,
from f being passed the result of g, T1,
the type of f, is also going to
have to equal some function.
And it's going to have to equal
a function that's the return type of g,
as its argument, so T6.
And then some T7, say, for
what it returns, for some T7.
Okay, we've looked at everything.
But now we have to say, from f being
the body of the anonymous function.
Remember, our anonymous
function was this T4 -> T5.
From a call to f being the body that
function, we know that T7, the return
type of f, has to be equal to T5, the
return type of that anonymous function.
Because we call f, and
then that's our result, okay.
So now we can just put it out together,
so put it all together.
We end up with the T1, the type of f,
has to be T6 -> T5,
because we just decided T7 = T5.
We had T2 = T4 -> T6,
that was the type of g.
And T3, which is our result for
compose, well, that's T4 -> T5, okay?
And if we actually put this all together,
just for T1 * T2 -> T3 here.
What we end up with is (T6 ->T5)
* (T4 ->T6) -> (T4->T5).
And that’s actually a good type for
compose.
Take in something, g takes a T4,
returns a T6, f takes a T6,
returns a T5, so the whole thing
takes in a T4 and returns a T5.
But we always replace these capital T's
consistently with type variables shen
we're all done,
there are no additional constraints here.
So let's just use a,
we'll just go left to right.
So the first thing that we see is T6,
so we'll use a for that.
The second thing that we see is T5,
so we'll use b for that.
The third thing that we see is T4,
so we'll use c for that.
And now when see another T6,
we have to use a again.
And when we see another T4,
we have to use c again.
And when we see a T5,
we have to use b again.
And except for these unnecessary
parentheses over here on the right,
this is exactly what the repl will
print out, as the type for compose.
It's something that takes in
a function from 'a to 'b, and
a function from 'c to 'a, and
returns a function from 'c to 'b.
So the process was exactly the same as for
the other examples.
Gather all your facts,
constrain everything as much as you can.
And then replace any unconstrained
types consistently with type variables.
And that is our examples
of type inference.