[MUSIC] This segment is about mutual
recursion.
It's a small topic that we just didn't
need before, but, it would be a mistake
to move on from ML without discussing it.
Mutual recursion is just when you have
two or more functions that need to call
each other.
So what if you wanted to have f call g
sometimes and g call f sometimes?
Now, is this useful? Yes,
it's useful in a number of idioms and
patterns that come up and we'll show a
particular example in this segment where
we're going to implement a little state
machine but there's a problem.
And that problem is that we've seen in ML
that you have to introduce bindings in
order, that the only functions in your
environment are things that were defined
earlier into the environment and yourself
for recursion.
So, how are we going to get f to call g
and g to call f? Well, I'll show you two
ways.
The first way is ML does have special
support for this and you should use that
special support,
because it's good style when you want
mutual recursion.
And second, I'll point out that we don't
actually need the special support,
there is a workaround with high order
functions and it's just another example
of using high order functions to
accomplish something useful.
So, here is the built-in support I just
never showed you before.
It turns out that if you have a bunch of
function bindings in a row, and if for
after the first one you use the word and
instead of fun. So it's fun f1, and f1's
definition, and f2, definition, and F3
and you can have as many of those as you
want,
then, this is all in some sense one
bundle of mutually recursive functions
They are all allowed to call each other.
They are all added to the environment for
all of the others and they're type
checked and evaluated as, as one package
if you will.
So that is all we really need to have f
call g and g call f, we just have to put
them next to each other in our file and
use the key word and.
Now interestingly, we can also do this
for data type findings, this is really a
separate construct, but suppose you
wanted to introduce two types that
referred to each other, so one of the
constructors of t1 holds a t2 and one of
the constructors of t2 holds a t1.
We also have not been able to do that
before, and it's the same idea where we
replace the keyword datatype with the
keyword and. Okay?
So that's the, it, kind of it for the
language construct.
Now, let's see this thing useful.
The idiom I want to show you for using
mutually recursive functions is just one
of several things mutual recursion is
useful for, is implementing a little
state machine.
Now, in case you've never seen a
finite-state machine, it's a very
important concept in computer science, I
encourage you to learn about it.
But the idea is that we want to process
some input of unknown length, so some
list of input that can have any size.
And as we process it, we're always in one
of a finite number of known states and we
read the next level of the input and that
tells us what state to go to next.
And then when we're all done with the
input, certain states are, true, yes, we
accept, and certain states are false, no,
we reject.
That's the idea of a finite state
machine,
they come up all the time in computing.
So the way we can implement a
finite-state machine with mutually
recursive functions is we just have one
function for each state.
So we could call those states state one,
state two, and so on it, depends what
kind of state machine we're implementing.
They would all take the remaining input,
they would all look at the first element
of that input, and then they would just
call whatever function represents the
next state.
So let me show an example of that, since
I don't expect you got it from the slide.
Here's a function, match, that takes in,
in this case, an int list, and what it
does, is it only accepts lists of ints
that look like 1, 2, 1, 2 some number of
times.
So the empty list would actually pass,
because it has 1, 2 zero times but, if
it's anything other than a 1 or a 2, it's
going to reject and otherwise, it's going
to be 1, 2, 1, 2, 1, 2 and it has to end
with a 2.
So, all I'm going to do inside my body of
match is call this helper function I
defined s_need_one on the whole list.
These are my two states,
need_one is the state that says I better
have a one next if I have anything and
s_need_2 is I better have a two next if I
have anything.
So here is how it works,
s_need_one looks at that list,
if there's nothing left, then on before
when I need a one, so that's true.
I saw a two last or I started with the
empty list.
Otherwise, if I have a one first and I
don't think I ever showed you, you can
put integer constants in patterns, but
that really is an orthogonal issue not
particularly relevant here.
then what I want to do is switch to state
two with the rest of my list.
Now, in general, for finite-state
machines, I could have other
possibilities where I have other states,
but there's particularly simple example
where I just have two states, I go back
and forth between.
And, any other case, I'm going to
immediately reject and return false.
S_need_two takes in the input list,
if there's nothing more, it says false,
because whenever I call s_need_2, I need
another two because I just saw a one.
If I have a two at the beginning of my
list, then call s_need_one with the rest
of the list.
And so on, we go back and forth, if I see
anything other than a two, I return
false.
Now, let me be honest with you this is
not the simplest way to implement this
particular function,
but this is a particularly simple problem
that can be answered with a finite-state
machine.
Anything, any function that processes a
list of say integers or strings or
whatever by looking at one element of it
at a time,
and moving between things that don't need
to keep track of any more state than a
finite number of possibilities can be
implemented in exactly this way.
You could actually even automatically
take a description of a finite state
machine and translate it down into a
collection of mutually recursive
functions.
So I thought I would show you that idiom
as a general phenomenon in computing.
Alright, let's do a second example.
This example is going to be silly just to
keep it short.
[COUGH] But what I have here is a
mutually recursive datatype binding.
So type t1 is either a Foo of int or Bar
of t2 and data type t2, I really am
defining two datatypes here, is either a
Baz of String or a Quux of t1.
So each of these datatypes refer to the
other one. Alright?
Now, suppose I wanted to write a function
that took either a t1 or a t2, these will
be different functions,
and made sure that there were no zeros
anywhere in it and no empty strings
anywhere in it. Okay? So, here is how I
would do it.
I would write a function
no_zeros_or_empty_strings_t1 that took in
an x.
If it's made out of the Foo constructor,
I need to make sure i <> 0.
If it's made out of the Bar constructor,
then what I have here in y is a t2.
So I want to call this other function I
wrote for no_zeros_or_empty_strings_t2
with that argument y.
And here is that other function, I've
made these two mutually recursive because
that other function, well, if x is a Baz,
then just make sure it's not empty, its
size is greater than zero.
But if it's a Quux, then I want to call
the first function I wrote.
So there is no good order here. I really
do need them to be mutually recursive.
Okay?
So that works, that's fine, it's not a
particularly interesting example.
thought I would use this example to show
you a different work around.
So a work around if you did not want to
necessarily put these next to each other
or if you were in some setting for some
reason that you really could not use
mutual recursion.
So the idea is to use our old friend, the
higher-order function and have one of
these functions take in the other one as
an argument.
So here, what I've done is I've written a
version where they are not mutually
recursive,
so this thing takes a t2 and make sure
that it doesn't have any zeros or empty
strings.
So the Baz case is still the same, make
sure you don't have the empty string.
For the other case, I want to call this
function up here.
Now, this function up here is not
going to be able to call this function
directly, because it's not in its
environment,
but I could still pass it as an extra
argument.
So what I've done is I've made my
function over t1 take not just an element
of type t1, but also take a function,
this function f happens to have type t2
-> bool, Alright?
So I could pass in any t2 -> bool, but
the one I'm going to pass in right here
is the function I want to call.
So one way you can get an earlier
function in your file to call a later one
is to pass it as an argument, and once we
can do that, everything works out just
fine and this is an equivalent solution
to the one that used the built-in support
for mutual recursion.
By the way, this is a slower
implementation, the built-in support will
implement this in a much more direct and
efficient way, but I just thought I would
show you this as a technique and flip
back to the slides quickly to show you in
general what we do. That if you want to
have some earlier function, call a later
function, change your earlier function to
take in an extra argument f, and then,
when you call the earlier function, pass
in, I'm sorry not f here.
I'll fix this after I finish the
recording, pass in later, right?
So call earlier with later and y and
everything will work out correctly.
And that's really everything I have to
tell you about mutual recursion.