[MUSIC]
This segment is going to introduce
an example that we are going to use for
the rest of our study of module systems.
So we'll get very used to it and
it's worth going through
the code before we get started.
The example is going to
implement an abstract data type.
It's just a module that exports some new
type of data and some operations on it.
And for a simple example that
doesn't take too long to implement,
I've a little library for
rational numbers.
So these are numbers that
can have a numerator and
a denominator where both the numerator and
the denominator are integers.
And the operations I'm going to
support are making these things,
these fractions if you will.
Adding two of them together and
then converting them to a string.
So for example,
if you had number three halves,
would turn out three slash two
when you convert it to a string.
So I'll show you the code
in just a second,
let me give you a high
level picture of it.
I'm going to have
a structure named Rational1,
because in later segments I'm going to
define rational two and rational three.
I'm going to have little data type for
my rational numbers that has either
the constructor Whole, for whole numbers,
carries one int, or Frac for
fractions, that carries two ints.
I've got an exception BadFrac in case
someone tries to make a fraction with
a denominator of zero because I want those
to be undefined in the raise an exception.
And the function make_frac that takes
in a numerator and a denominator and
returns a rational.
Add for adding two rationals and
toString for taking a rational and
returning a string.
Now the implementation of my module is
going to have local helper functions,
that I'll show what those
do in just a second.
And in the next segment,
when we give this structure a signature,
it will not surprise you that
we will choose to hide those.
So the outside world doesn't
have to rely on them.
So next, let's go over and
show you the code.
So here it is.
It has the datatype definition, just
like I promised you and the exception,
just like I promised you.
And as we're going to talk
about more in a minute,
the implementation of
this module is going to
keep a couple in variants because
it's going to promise a few things.
What I didn't tell you yet about this
module is that I'm going to make sure
that we always return strings
that are in reduced form.
So we would never return
the string nine slash six.
We would instead return three slash two.
And we wouldn't return
the string eight slash two,
we would return the string four.
So we're going to do that by
having a couple helper functions.
The key helper function
is this one reduce.
Reduce takes in a rational and
returns a rational and
what it does is it return
something in reduced form.
So if it starts with a whole number,
just return the whole number.
Those are always reduced.
Otherwise, if it's a fraction of an x and
y,
if x=0, the numerator is 0,
then the whole thing is 0, right.
Zero over anything should be zero.
Remember we're not going to
allow zero denominators.
Otherwise, it turns out what we need to
do is compute the greatest common divisor
of x and y, but my gcd function
assumes that x and y are positive.
So I'm going to (abs x, y),
my denominators will always be positive,
that's another invariant that
this module is going to enforce.
Then if d, the greatest common divisor,
divides y,
then we should be a whole number, x div d.
Otherwise, we should div the Frac(x div d,
y div d).
And I will leave it to you to either trust
me or check me on the arithmetic that this
does reduce a fraction to reduced form
as long as gcd is implemented correctly.
I have that right up here.
This is another algorithm that I will
not convince you is correct but if x and
y are greater than zero,
this will do the right thing.
And believe it or not this is a recursive
algorithm that is over 2000 years old.
It goes back to ancient Greece I believe.
And so humankind is fairly convinced
that this algorithm is correct.
So that's kind of neat.
These are just helper functions.
Now let's talk about the functions
that our clients are going to use.
I have make_frac which is going
to take in an x and a y, if y=0,
you're trying to grade a fraction with a
zero denominator, I'll raise an exception.
If y < 0,
I don't want negative denominators,
that's one of the invariance this
model is going to maintain, so
instead I'm going to return Frac(-x,-y) so
that's going to make y positive.
And x will have the opposite sign of
whatever it did when it was passed in.
And then I need to reduce that,
because maybe you call make_frac
with 9 and 6 or 9 and negative 6.
And then I want to return
negative three over two, okay.
Otherwise y is positive so
we'll just reduce(Frac(x, y).
So now we've created fractions
that are in reduced form.
If we want to add the two together, we're
going to assume they're in reduced form
and make sure the result
is in reduced form.
This is a great example for
nested pattern matching.
If you have two whole numbers,
return the whole number that's
the sum of those two numbers.
If you have a whole number and a fraction,
it turns out if that fraction is already
in reduced form, then so will be
the result of adding a whole number.
So we can just return j+k*i,k.
If you have two fractions, then we can
compute a new fraction as a*d + b*c, b*d.
But then we need to reduce the result and
again this is a primary
school arithmetic but I know I am always
a little forgetful on these things.
It's okay if the exact arithmetic
is a little surprising to you.
It's not really the point
of studying module systems.
Okay.
And then finally we have this thing
that prints out the string.
Now this is very interesting.
Because we keep all our
rationals in reduced form,
we can just go ahead and print it.
So if it's a whole number,
just convert it to a string.
Excuse me, we're not actually printing
here, we're just converting to strings but
then the REPL prints out our results,
so that's why I keep saying printing.
And if you have a fraction
then just (Int.toString
a) concatenate that with a slash and
(Int.toStrig b).
So let me show you an example
of using all of this.
[SOUND] And then we'll talk a little bit
more about the structure of our module.
So there we go,
I've defined my whole module and
now I could say val x =
Rational1.make_frac(9,6).
All right and how about val y =
Rational1.make_frac(-8,-2).
And I'm just misspelled Rational1 in here.
And misspelled make_frac.
[SOUND]
Okay, there we go.
Now we could say Rational1.add(x, y).
And I could just immediately have
a Rational1.toString of that.
[SOUND] And I get 11/2,
which is in fact three-halves plus 4,
which is the reduced form of nine over
six and negative 8 over negative 2.
So this is how I would use
the module as a client.
So, that's the idea.
We see the structure here.
We define our data type, our exception and
these public functions make_frac, add and
toString.
Now I want to talk more about
how abstract data types
are typically implemented with modules.
And I want to focus on the specification
of the library in terms of
properties and how it's implemented
in terms of invariants.
So what I'm calling properties
are externally visible guarantees.
Things that the library writer is
promising any clients of the library.
Some of the things that this module
that I just showed you is promising,
are the following.
We will disallow any denominators of 0.
If you go to make such a fraction,
we will raise an exception.
You will never see a rational
with a denominator of zero.
That all the strings we
return are in reduced form.
Well you see 4, not 4/1 and 3/2 not 9/6.
And that except for
disallowing denominators of zero any time
you call a function it will terminate,
it won't raise an exception,
it always produces the correct answer.
So there are additional properties,
this is not a full specification but
these are particular things
I want to emphasize that
I'm going to say our library must do,
even though it's not in the types
of the functions we're providing
like add and to string.
Now that's all the outside
world should care about.
Internally, our implementation is
maintaining some important invariants.
And what this means is that all of
the functions are going to have to
guarantee these extra things or
other functions might do the wrong thing.
Now the outside world
should not care about this.
These are implementation details but
they're things that are across the module
so that one function can rely on
another function doing it correctly.
So the first thing we're going to
require is in fact that all denominators
are positive.
So the outside world can make a fraction
with negative 8 and negative 2, but
we'll return the fraction that doesn't
have a negative denominator, okay.
And so
all of our functions can assume that.
Second thing that's
internal invariant is that,
all of the rational values
are already reduced.
So we never even create a 9/6,
we immediately create a 3/2.
So let me emphasize that our functions
are maintaining these invariants and
relying on them in several places.
So if you look back at the code,
you'll see a number of things.
So you see that make_frac,
when we get started and
we build a rational number,
explicitly disallows a 0.
It had a special case to
remove a negative denominator,
it immediately negated both
the numerator and the denominator.
And it called reduce on the result to
make sure that we created a rational in
reduced form.
Then our add function assume that
the two arguments were in reduced form.
And it actually used that to avoid calling
reduced in some cases where it did
not need to.
But in other cases, to be careful and
to make sure it preserves the invariants,
it did call reduce, okay.
We're relying on these invariants and
several other places as well.
The gcd function is not correct for
negative arguments and there are certain
places where we called gcd with arguments
that we only know are non negative.
Because all of our module is
maintaining this invariant.
And similarly, in toString,
remember toString,
we promised the outside world would
always return things in reduced form.
But toString didn't check for
that and did not call reduce,
because it's relying on the invariant
in the rest of the module.
So that's our example and now what we
want to do is use signatures to make
sure that this properties and
invariants cannot be violated by clients.