[SOUND]
In this segment we'll start studying
lists.
Right now we're just going to learn the
basic rules for them, and then in the
next segment, we'll program with
functions that either take lists or
produce lists, just to break things into
slightly smaller pieces.
we've already seen one way to build up
compound data, and that was with tuples,
and they're a nice contrast with lists.
Tuples, even though we can make them as
wide as we wanted or as deep as we
wanted, touples inside of touples.
We still had to pick that size when we
were writing the program.
So there was no way with tuples, as they
take in a number like 10, or n, or x, and
then produce a tuple that had that many
pieces,
because there be no type to write down
for that thing,
because you don't know the size until you
run the program.
So lists don't have that restriction.
We're going to be able to build lists
with any number of elements and we won't
be limited by the type of the list.
But there's a tradeoff here, and that is
that any list we build will have to have
pieces that all have the same type.
And that's just the rule for lists in ML,
and we'll learn in future a segments and
parts of the course how to program around
that restriction by using other concerts
of the language.
Alright, so to understand lists just like
with tuples, we're going to have ways to
build them and we're going to have ways
to use them.
So let's start with how we can build
lists.
The simplest list has zero elements in
it,
and you build that zero element list by
just writing left bracket, right bracket.
This is itself a value, so the evaluation
rule is trivial.
The syntax evaluates to itself, and
that's the empty list.
Now, if you wanted a list with multiple
elements in it,
you can just write those down seperated
by commas.
So let me show you a few examples here so
I can really write the empy list,
and that's its value.
You see the type there, quote A list.
We'll get back to that in a few minutes.
Let's ignore that for now.
I could also make a list three, four,
five, and that would hold three, four,
five.
You can see from the type here.
It's a list of, of ints,
so it doesn't matter how many elements
are in it.
A two-element list has the same number,
has the same type and so does a
four-element list,
and so on.
these are all values because a list of
values is a value.
But, I could put expressions in here,
three plus four seven, like this and it
will evaluate each of those.
So, this is the list holding a three and
then a seven and then a seven.
You don't have to have lists of integers
you can have list of Booleans as well.
So here's a three element bool list,
but you can't mix them.
So if I had something like three, four
plus five, true, than that's going to
give a type error, the same way four plus
true gives a type error.
All the elements of the list have to have
the same type.
Of course these are just values, I
combined a list to a variable and so on.
Okay, so there's one other way to build
lists, which is very useful,
and that's using this colon, colon
operation, which I'll pronounce cons, for
constructing a list.
Cons, C, O, N, S,
and here's how it works.
All it does is evaluate e one to some
value.
E2 to some value that is itself a list.
And then it makes a list that has one
more element than that list E2 evaluated
to.
Mainly it puts the result of E1 on the
front of the list.
So if I flip back here,
remember, X is this list 789 I could say
five cons onto X.
Now it produced the list 5789.
You can even say six cons don to five
cons don to x.
The parenthesis would go like this, you
don't actually need them.
and that would be 6, 5, 7, 8, 9, and so
on.
Alright?
One thing you can't do is something like
this, alright, and that just doesn't type
check, and that's because we're trying to
take a list of integers, namely the list
holding six, and put that on the front of
a list of integers.
And a list of integers can't hold a list
of integers. It is a list of integers, so
this is the correct thing to do.
You can have a list of a list of
integers, so I could cons that six onto a
list of list of integers, maybe like
this.
Alright, and now indeed, I have a list
holding three lists of integers.
The first is the list six, the second the
list 7, 5, and third the list 5, 2.
Alright, so that's how to build lists,
now how about using them.
Well, we need a way to access the pieces,
and we need to know a way to find out if
our list is empty or not, because if you
try to access the pieces of an empty
list, you get a runtime error.
So let's do that test first.
There's a function in ML called null, n,
u, l, l.
Do not think of this like the null in
Java or C+++ or any number of other
languages.
This is a function that takes a list as
an argument and returns true if that list
is empty and false otherwise.
So for example, if I ask null of X, I'll
get false because remember, X is not the
empty list,
but if I ask null of the empty list I get
true and indeed if some other list was
empty and I asked null of that, I would
get true.
So, once you know a list is not empty,
it's reasonable to ask for its head, the
first element of the list, or it's tail,
which is the list, which is all the
elements except the first one.
And these are the two operations we are
going to use to access the pieces of the
list.
So the head function, spelled HD, just
takes a list and returns the first
element.
The tail function takes a list and
returns all the other elements.
Alright?
So these are just functions.
So I can just call them like any other
functions.
So if I ask for head of X, I get seven
cause remember X is this example list,
7-8-9.
I can ask tail of X, that will give me
back the list 8-9.
If I wanted the first element of that
list, I'd have to ask head of tail of X,
then I would get eight.
Can ask of course, also get tail of tail
of X.
That would be the one element list nine.
You could also ask tail of tail of tail
of X.
What's the tail of a one M element list?
It's the zero element list.
So this is the empty list.
Now if you asked head or tail of that,
that would type check just fine,
that if I actually evaluate this, I get
an uncaught exception for trying to take
head or tail of the empty list.
I get the same thing if I use head.
Alright.
So that's accessing the pieces of lists.
We've really focused here on the syntax
and the evaluation rules.
So now let's switch to talking a little
more of the types of lists and the types
of functions for making them and using
them.
So,
just like when we had a tuples, we had a
new way of writing types.
So int star int was a pair of ints for
example.
We have a new types for lists.
So for any type t, the type t space list
describes the values that are lists
holding key elements in them.
So, as we've seen in the examples, int
list is a list of int.
bool list is a list of bools, and so on.
Now these things can nest, I think I've
shown you a little bit of this, if I make
a list of pairs events.
That's fine, that's an int star int list.
It's a list whose elements have type int
star int.
So I try to do something like cons, three
onto that, it won't type check,
but if I try to cons a pair of ints onto
that,
will type check just fine.
Alright,
so you can nest these things however you
want.
You could have a list with another list
of ints inside of it.
I've shown you one of those.
You can have a list with a pair in it and
where that pair has a list inside of it
and so on.
All right,
but what about the types of the
operations I've given you for building
lists and accessing lists?
So probably the hardest one to understand
is the type of the empty list.
So I've showed you before, this has the
type written quote, a space list.
And I always pronounce quote a as alpha,
like the Greek letter.
So we say that the empty list has type
alpha lists.
What that actually means is that you can
replace that alpha with any type you
want.
So the empty list can have type int list,
but it can also have type bool list, and
it can also have type int star int list,
and so on.
And that's good, because that's what
let's us cons three onto the empty list
to get an in list or true onto the empty
list to get a bool list.
So, the empty list is a special thing
that can have lots of types.
Its type is alpha list that lets it also
have type T list for any type T.
Alright, so we're going to see that as a
theme with these other operations as
well.
The cons operator also works for any kind
of list.
The rule is E2 has to have type t list
for some t, and then E1 has to have type
t, because you have to add something of
the correct type onto the list you
started with.
Then we have our operations for accessing
list, testing if they're empty, getting
their head, getting their tail, and these
really are just functions in ML.
So I have their types written here but we
can also see that the read eval print
loop.
So null is just a function.
Again, it's nothing like null in other
languages, that takes in a list of any
type alpha.
So for all types alpha, you can take in
an alpha list, and we'll give you back
true or false.
And that's why I can't ask null with a
list of integers or with a list of
Booleans.
In a couple sections later in the course,
we'll learn how to write our own
functions that have types with these
alphas in it, and other Greek letters if
you like,
but for now we're just going to use ones
provided to us by the ml language.
Similarly head takes in a list of alphas
for any type alpha, and what you get back
is an alpha.
That's why, if you call head with a list
of integers, you get back an integer,
and if you call it with a list of
Booleans, you get back a Boolean.
And finally, tail takes a list and
returns a list, alpha list to alpha list,
and those two type, lists, have to have
the same type,
which is why, if I say tail of 3,4, I get
an int list back, because I passed it in
int list.
Alright?
So now we know our key operations for
building lists and accessing lists.
What we'll do next is a very powerful,
very common thing in functional
programming,
which is to write useful functions that
take in return lists.