[SOUND]
Alright in this segment I just want to
pick up a few odds and ends that we didnt
do before in the interest of, of getting
you ramped up with our useful thing to
know.
and thats basically ways to combined
boolean expressions with and, and or, or
negation things like that.
And also how to compare numbers with
comparison operations I think I've only
shown you equal and grater than so far.
So let's start with the boolean
operations.
I actually showed you once because it
came up for an algorithm we needed.
the construct e1 and also e2.
So, and also is just a seven letter key
word.
And the type checking rules are that e1
and e2 can be any expressions that have
type bool.
And the evaluation rule is that we
evaluate e1.
If we get false, then the result of the
entire thing is false and we never
evaluate e2.
Otherwise, we evaluate e2 and then that's
the result of the entire expression.
So this is exactly what in most
programming languages these days is
written with the && operator.
But ML is an older language that chose a
different and longer syntax.
So you just have to write out and-also
when you want to do an and like this.
similarly we have or-else, where we
evaluate e1, if we get true that's the
result for the whole thing and we never
evaluate E2.
Otherwise we evaluate E2 and that's the
result for the whole thing.
And we have, actually, a function, not,
an OT, that evaluates e1.
If you get true, the result is false.
If you get false, the result is true.
So again, the syntax is most languages is
different.
&&.
a pipe, pipe for or.
And the exclamation point for not.
If you try those in ML, they're not going
to work.
And, and, and or.
And, and or with amper, amper and pipe,
pipe don't mean anything.
So you'll get a syntax error.
the exclamation point actually means
something totally different related to
mutation, which we might see at the very
end.
So you'll get a stranger error message.
And the last thing I wanted to point out
is because and also and or else have this
property that don't always evaluate both
sub expressions.
They really are key words and they're not
functions whereas not can just be a
function.
So let me show you that.
If I say something like true andalso
false I get false.
That's fine.
And if I said true andalso true then I
get true.
That's fine.
And if I say not true I get false.
And if I say not false I get true.
But if I just say andalso.
it's asking for more input.
It's like that doesn't make any sense.
That's not the right syntax, this is a
syntax error.
Because it says if you use andalso, you
have to put an expression on the left and
an expression on the right.
But if I just say not, it turns out
that's not special syntax at all.
It just says, oh, well that's just a
function that was already defined, that
takes a bool and returns a bool.
And that works just fine for not, because
we always evaluate it's expression.
But we wouldn't want to define andalso
that way, because we know that.
If we have, a function, we evaluate all
the arguments to it, before we call the
function. And since that's not the
semantics for andalso and or else,
they're not functions.
Alright?
Okay.
let me just point out one other thing
here.
going back to the slides, and that is,
that a language, a programming language,
if it has if-then-else expressions, it
doesn't need andalso, or else or not.
So it turns out, as you see here on the
slide, if you were ever going to write e1
and also e2, you could just write if e1
then e2, else false.
Because both versions have the exact same
type checking rules and semantics.
e1 and e2 both have to have type bool.
We evaluate e1.
If we get false, that's the type, result
for the whole thing.
If we get true, then we get the result of
evaluating E2.
Similarly e1 or else e2 could just be
written if e1 then true else e2, and not.
Can be written if e1 then false, else
true.
So from a how powerful is your language
standpoint all you need is if then else.
But because we have and also or else and
not, these longer versions with if then
else are considered poor style.
And that's because someone reading your
code can tell much more easily, oh this
is and, this is an and or this is an or.
If you use the special syntax for it
rather than these more verbose versions
using the more general expression.
And as long as we're on the subject.
Please make sure that you never, in any
programming language.
Write the equivalent of if e, then true,
else false.
Let's understand what this is saying.
It says, evaluate e to a result.
Which has to be a Boolean.
Either true or false.
If that is, result is true, then our
whole thing is true.
And if that result is false, then our
whole thing is false.
That sounds very natural when you're
programming.
But do you know a simpler expression that
has the exact same semantics?
E.
E is an expression, that if you evaluate
it and you get true, then the whole thing
is true, and if you evaluate it and you
get false, the whole thing is false.
So please just write e, not if e then
true, else false.
Okay, so those are the Booleans.
Let's just finish up with the comparison
operators.
If you have two ints, you can see if
there equal of equal.
We've done that.
You can see if they're not equal with
this second one, the less than greater
than.
You might be used to in most programming
languages exclamation point equals.
It's just not ML syntax.
You can think of this as  if you
like.
The other comparison operators are more
familiar.
>, >=, <=.
Just a couple weird things in ML, thanks
to the type system.
And that is that the last four, for
greater than and less than, greater than
or equal to, less than or equal to, can
also be used for floating point numbers,
which ML calls things of type real, but
you can't use it for an int and a real.
So let's just show you what I mean by
that.
You can say 3 > 2 you get true.
You can ask if 3.0 is > 2.0.
That also gives you true.
Notice, that three has type int and 3.0
has type real.
You can't do this.
You just get a type error.
The over need to convert an int to a
real, there's a library function that
does that called real.fromint.
You can call it with 2, you get back 2.0.
These purple messages are just the ripple
telling you that it loaded the library
that has that functionality and you're
welcome to ignore that.
Now just one more complication now that
I've mentioned reals.
it turns out you cannot in ML, use = or
not equal on reals.
You can use them on lots of types, we'll
talk about this in the future, things
like equality types.
Int's are just one example of an equality
type.
But real is not in a quality type its
actually enforcing something that's good
in any programming language because
floating point numbers are subject to
round off errors it is rarely, rarely the
right thing to do to actually take two
floating point numbers and see if they're
equal or not.
You should always see if there within
some small epsilon, some small range of
each other.