[SOUND]
In this segment, which is optional, I
want to continue our discussion of the
benefits of not being able to mutate,
mutate data by showing you an example in
Java.
So, as I said at the end of the previous
segment, in ML, we can create aliases and
not worry about one of those aliases
causing an update,
being used for an update that then
effects other aliases.
But in languages like Java, we really
have to be careful about where we create
aliases versus where we make copies.
So, the example that I have here I've
simplified so it fits on the slide, but
this is the exact idea behind bugs that
until they were fixed, caused real
security violations in real Java
libraries, including things in the
standard Java library related to class
loaders and other things.
So, let me walk through what I'm trying
to capture, the, the basic idea here.
So, I have some resource, which I'll put
in the field the resource, and I don't
want everyone to access this.
I really want this to be private. So,
I've used this private field, it should
be hidden, I'm not going to let anyone
use it,
just anyone. But I want some people to be
able to access it, and so I'll have
something reminiscent of say, passwords.
So, the allowed users will just be in
this array of strings.
So, if someone is in that list, then they
can use the resource and if not, if they
try to use the resource, I'm going to
raise an exception.
Now, I'm happy to let everyone know who
is allowed to use the resource.
That's not secret, just the contents of
the resource are.
So, I have this method, get allowed
users, that will return the string array.
So, you can see who the users are, you
can even see if you're in the list so
you're allowed to use it.
Could even find out the current user.
So, maybe when the code is executing,
there's some notion of a current user.
So, that allows the, the main method
here, if you will use the resource to do
the right thing.
So, what it's going to do is for every
element of the allowed user's array, it's
going to see if the current user is the
same string as in the i-th position of
allowed users.
And so, if you find the current user in
that array, then go ahead allow access
use the resource in whatever way your
supposed to.
Otherwise, if this for loop actually
finishes without returning here in this
if statement, then throw an exception,
okay?
So, it turns out, this code probably
makes sense to you.
I encourage you to figure out how it's in
fact insecure and it would let any user
who's just a little bit clever to
actually use the resource whether they're
supposed to or not.
So I'm going to tell you the answer in a
few seconds.
Click pause if you want.
And don't be too tough on yourself if you
can't find the bug since a lot of other
people, including the people who have
written code like this, have made the
same mistake.
Okay? Ready? Here we go.
The get allowed users method returns an
alias to the array,
right? So, all a malicious user has to do
is call get aloud users to get an alias
to the array and then update one of the
elements of the array, say position zero,
to be the current user.
Then, if you call use the resource, I
guarantee that name will be in the array.
So, clicking back here to the previous
slide, the error's in fact not in use the
resource.
That's doing exactly the right thing.
It's in get allowed users for leaking an
alias to the allowed users array.
It's sort of is like, I assume that
clients were only going to read this
result. And in a language that didn't
allow you to mutate array elements, that
would be a fine assumption.
But java is not such a language.
And so, clients can do something like
this.
And then, they'd be able to access the
resource whether they were supposed to or
not.
And so the fix which Java programmers
have to remember to do, they get no help
from the language or the type system
unless they use final in the right place
or try to use libraries that encapsulate
this idea, is to change that get allowed
users method to return a copy of allowed
users.
You have to copy the array so that what's
given back to clients can no way update
the internal representation of our
private resource object which then causes
use the resource to do the wrong thing.
So, if that's tough to reason about, I
agree with you.
I find the simplest way to avoid
reasoning about that, to get rid of
mutation for most of the data in my
program.
But if you prefer to have mutation, then
you get to be in the business of writing
your program such that you have copies in
all the right places.