[MUSIC] So, let's now jump in and get the
Racket basics out of the way.
Let's learn how to define functions,
variables, conditionals, and so forth,
covering a lot of the ground we already
did in ML.
I have a few slides posted with this
lecture but I think I'll primarily just
stay over here in Dr.
Racket and write a bunch of code with
you.
So, I already have #lang Racket, and this
thing, so that I could test in a second
file if I wanted to, although we'll just
use the RPL here.
And now, let's do a couple of variable
definitions.
So, (define, the name of the variable you
want to define, and then an expression
that you evaluate to the variable.
So, this is really like, val x=3 in ML,
okay? And now, we can do another one.
So, a definition can use x.
So, suppose I want y to be x+2.
So, what I do is I call the plus function
with x and 2.
The way you call a function in Racket is
you write parenthesis, the function you
want to call, and then the arguments.
So, plus plus is really just a function
so plus is a function and we call it
here.
So, this variable y is being bound to the
result of this function call and in
general, function calls are written with
a perenthesis before the function your
calling, then the argument, then a
parenthesis after the arguments.
It's a different syntax than in languages
you may be familiar with but that is a
function call calling the plus function
with x and 2.
So now, let's define our own function.
Let's I'm going to write a few versions
of the cubing function, so I'll call this
one cube1, and now I'm defining a
function.
So, what I'm going to do is I use this
key word lambda, it's spelled like the
Greek letter.
Racket, in earlier dialects of this
language, like Scheme have been using
that Greek letter for decades, it's a bit
of a strange choice.
Then, the arguments in parenthesis, so
this will take one argument.
So, lambda is a keyword that says I
wanted to find a function, put the
arguments in parenthesis, and then you
have the body.
And the body I want is to call the
multiply function with two arguments.
With x and with the result of this other
call x and x.
And then, and that call, this call the
lambda form and the defined form.
So, this body, the, just the body here
this part here would be like in other
languages writing x times x times x.
But in Racket, everything always has the
function first, and all these operators
are just functions, and so it looks like
this.
We get very used to in Racket, ending
things with lots of parenthesis.
I'll talk more about parenthesis in a
future segment, but for now, notice all I
did was introduce a val binding,
right, for cube1 and bind it to this
anonymous function.
So, lambda is like ML's fn,
right? It takes in, this an anonymous
function that takes in one argument, x,
and has this body that ends up cubing x,
alright?
Let me write a nicer version.
It turns out that you don't have to write
it that way because the multiplication
function, which is provided to us already
by Racket, can take any number of
arguments and it returns their product.
So, we really kind of just write it like
that.
So, multiply, in this language, is a
function that can take any number of
arguments.
There is a way in Racket to define your
own functions that take any number of
arguments but I'm not planning to show
that to you.
You can consult it the guide, if you need
it you won't need it for any of our
homeworks.
the other thing I wanted to point out
here, is that this really is just a
function call and so it makes sense that
we're calling it that way.
Our function cube2 takes one argument,
multiply takes any number of arguments.
Unlike in ML, I'm not lying to you, this
is not syntactic sugar.
In Racket, our a functions really do take
0, 1, 2, 3, 4 or any number of arguments.
It's not syntactic sugar for coupling or
for currying, okay? let me show you
something that we do have syntactic sugar
for though, you do not have to write
lambda every time, if you want to do
this.
This is exactly like the previous
version.
So, what you can do is instead of
essentially defining a variable and
binding it to this anonymous function,
you can use this syntax instead, but it
is exactly the same thing.
This is syntactic sugar for define the
variable cube3 to be bound to a function
that takes one argument x, and returns,
has this as its body, x times x times x.
If you had multiple arguments here, you
could just do like that before that first
right parenthesis.
So, there are three versions of cubing
functions.
Now, let's write some recursive
It turns out that unlike in ML, we don't
need anything new to do recursive
functions, but you can just use the
lambdas like we have been doing or the
syntactic sugar I just showed you.
So, if I wanted to find the
exponentiation function, I'm going to do
this two different ways.
So, I'll call this pow1.
The purpose here is x to the yth power
and I think my solution y only works if y
is non-negative, alright?
I just need a body here and now I need an
if.
the way you write an if in Racket, is you
write left parenthesis if and then three
expressions.
You want e2, e3, and that is the thing to
test for.
The true branch and the true, false
branch, so we don't use keys then and
else, so they don't exist in Racket, we
just write the three expressions in a row
and then end with a right parenthesis.
So, the way I want to do this, I want to
say if y=0, equals is function that takes
two numbers, returns true if they're
equal then 1.
So, I've written two of my three
expressions for if.
And now my third one can be * x.
and then recursively call pow1 with x and
y-1.
Notice that like every operator in
Racket, minus goes first.
And, there it is.
So, pow1 is a function that takes two
arguments, x and y, and its body is this
if expression, this, sorry, if
expression.
The if expression has equal y0, for its
first sub expression, 1 for the second
and multiplying x by the result of this
call, this call, pow1 with x and y-1.
so this is the exponentiation function.
You'll notice that we, every time we have
a function call, its parenthesis function
you want to call, arguments, okay? So,
this will work fine.
Why don't we go ahead and run this? I
haven't been running much for you.
So, I just clicked Run.
Now, I can say pow1, how about 3^2,
right?
So, it's a function call.
I pass in the two arguments.
I get nine.
And if I ask pow1 3^0,
I would get one,
great,
okay? So, let's define just a couple more
functions.
let's do another version of pow, that's
curried.
So, currying has nothing to do with
anything other than an idiom with
closures.
and so we can, we can do that in Racket.
it's not as common in Racket because
Racket has built-in support for
multi-argument functions but there's no
reason why we can't use curreying so
let's see.
Well, here's a simple version.
I could just call pow1 with the two
argument,
right? So, this pow2 is a function that
takes in one argument, x.
Its body is this lambda, which returns a
function that takes an argument y and
then I just call pow1 with x and y.
Of course, I could have my own
conditional down here if I preferred,
okay? And now that I have this this pow2,
I could partially apply it and I could
say something like pow2 3,
okay? And if I save all that and run it
I could say, three-to-the with 2, and I
would get 9,
right? Because I end up, taking this
function that pow2 return, calling it
with 2.
That ends up calling pow1 with 3 and 2,
and I get 9.
So, it's currying exactly like an ML.
because it's less common, if you're not
partially applying things you know, so if
I wanted 16, it's quite convenient to
call pow1 with 4 and 2.
But if I want to do it with pow2 well,
what do I need to do? I need to call pow2
with 4.
That gives back a function and now, I
need to call that function with 2.
This parenthesis matter.
Parenthesis always matter in Racket.
If I want to call pow2 with 4, I have to
write it like this,
then that gives me back something that is
the function, and if I want to call that
function with 2, I need this parenthesis
to its left and then here.
So, it turns out that in Racket, there's
a little bit of syntactic sugar for
defining curried functions.
The code posted with this segment will
have that.
You don't need to use it.
We're actually not going to use currying
so much in Racket.
there is no syntactic sugar for calling a
curried function.
This line that I have here, really is the
best that you can do.
I bring up currying here, both because
it's something familiar and I wanted you
to see it in multiple languages.
And also, because it emphasizes that we
have anonymous functions, first class
functions, and whenever you want to call
a function, it's always,
e0, so parenthesis e0, for the expression
that evaluates to the function you want
to call, then e1 up to en for the
arguments, then the other parenthesis.
This is what function calls look like in
Racket.
Now, if e0 is not an expression, if it's
something like if or define or lambda,
then those are not function calls,
those are other constructs in Racket.
We'll continue to see those and
understand those in the segments ahead.