, In this segment, I want to introduce
mcons cells, which are separate from cons
cells, and the difference is an mcons cell
supports changing the contents of the car
encoder fields. So what if you had a cons
cell, like we've been studying, like we've
learned is just a pair, and you wanted to
change its car, so it didn't have 42, it
had 43 or you wanted to change its cdr so
it didn't have null, it had some other
value. Well, in Racket it turns out there
is no way to do that and this is the
biggest change between Racket and its
predecessors like Scheme and Lisp. And the
reason why they made this change is so we
could use cons cells to make pairs and
lists that were immutable and get all the
advantages we had in ML when we saw that
lists and tupples were immutable. The
biggest advantage we'd like to emphasize
is that it made aliasing irrelevant. It
did not matter if one part of a list was
aliased with another part of another list,
because no one would have ever been able
to tell the difference, because we
couldn't update things. We made a big deal
about this back in section one and it's
nice that we can program with cons cells
in Racket and get the same advantages. As
a minor side point, it turns out in a
dynamically typed language like Racket,
there is another advantage, which is the
implementation of the list question mark
procedure we saw in the previous segment
can be more efficient. Because, when we
create a cons cell, we know at that moment
whether or not it'll be a list and it will
always be a list because no one can ever
change any of the contents of any of the
cons cells that are relevant to it being a
list or not. And so, the implementation is
able to record that fact and not have to
implement list? by running down the entire
list, seeing if the list is actually
proper or not. But, suppose that you did
want to mutate things, how might you go
about it? What would work? What would not?
And this is important, because we are
going to have some programming idioms come
up where mutation is g oing to be useful
and its typical limited only because we
really want to do it way. So the first
thing I want to emphasize is that set bang
really does not mutate cons cells. So here
is a little list I've defined, I've
bounded to x, x holds the list 14. If I
say that y is now x, then y also holds the
list 14. suppose I said set bang x to be
some different list. We saw set bang. What
that does is change x to refer to some new
and different thing. So if I ask what x
is, I get this new list. But if I ask what
y is, it's still the list holding 14,
because when I defined y, previously, I
looked up x, I got the current value for x
14, and null, and so that's what y is. Set
bang changed x, but it did not change the
cons cell that x referred to. There is
still a cons cell out there with 14 in the
car and null in the cdr, and so if I ask
car of y, I get 14, x now refers to a
different cons cell, so car of x returns
42. So if we wanted to change the contents
of a cons cell, something, so that if say
z and x both referred to the same thing,
and then I wanted to update that thing, so
that the car the cdr would be different,
that is what Racket does not support. So
you might think you could do something
like oh, let's change the car of x to be
45 and that's just not what set bang does.
Set bang only works on identifiers, on
variables, and change what, changes what
they refer to. Now, Scheme, the
predecessor to Racket, had a feature
set-car! that would do exactly kind of
what we want. It would look up x in the
environment, get a cons cell, and mutate
the car field of that cons cell to be 45.
And it's an advantage of Racket that we
cannot do that set-car! simply does not
exist, but what if we want it to? Well,
Racket understands there are situations
where you may want that, and so, it
defined a different built-in data type for
that thing, and the function that you can
use is mcons, which is just like cons
except it does not make a cons cell, it
makes an mcons cell. So here is a little
example wher e I'm actually going to make
two mcons cells, where the outer one has a
car of 1 and a cdr of true that is itself
an mcons cell, and then the nested mcons
cell has a car of true and a cdr of hi.
Now, you can't ask car of an mpr, you
can't ask cdr of an mpr, but you can ask
mcar of an mpr and mcdr of an mpr. And of
course, since the mcdr in this case is
itself a cons cell, we could ask something
like mcar of mcdr of mpr and that would
get out the Boolean true. Now, the
difference between mcons and cons, is
that, these things are mutable and there
is in fact something mcdr-bang!, right,
mcdr!, I could apply to the cons cell in
mpr changes to 47, and now sorry mpr holds
the cons cell where the car is one and the
cdr is 47. Alright? I could change it
back. Right? I could change it back to
mcons #t hi, alright, and now mpr is back
like this. I could even set-mcar! of mcdr
of mpr to say 14. And now, if I ask mpr,
you'll see that the car of the cdr of mpr
is now 14. It's been changed. Okay? So
this is how it works. you cannot mix and
match things as I pointed out, so length
is a wonderful built-in function that
works just fine on lists like this, so
this is a plain old list that returns
true. Length gives an error on improper
lists like we saw in the previous section.
Length also gives an error on an mcons
even if that, you're using mcons in a way
that is like proper lists. You cannot use
mcons to make proper lists. Length
requires a proper list and so you're not
allowed to mix and match these things. And
of course, something like mcar bang is not
going to work on a cons cell that is not
an mcons cell. Okay? So that's the idea.
Let me just flip back to the slides to
emphasize it. All we've really done is
introduce a new set of functions and
constructs that are separate from cons
cells. We make a mutable cons cell with
mcons, get its first thing with mcar,
second thing with mcdr. We can find out if
we have one, this is the one thing I
didn't demonstrate for you with mpair?.
Set the content, set the car field with
set-mcar! and set the cdr field with
set-mcdr!. So when we need a mutable data
structure Something that has multiple
pieces whose content can change we'll use
mcon cells, and when we do not want
mutability, we'll use regular cons cells.