, In this segment we're going to begin
emphasizing, in our semantics, when
expressions get evaluated. This is a key
concept in programming languages and it's
going to be essential for understanding
the programming idioms we're going to see
in the next few segments. So for every
language construct and every programming
language, the semantics does have to
specify if or when those sub expressions
appear to get evaluated. For two crucial
examples, let's focus on function calls
and conditionals. So in ML and Racket and
other languages you're probably familiar
with. When you have a function call, the
arguments to the call are evaluated before
the call starts, before you evaluate the
function body. Each of them is evaluated
once, and then the function body uses
variables. The function parameters to look
up the results of those computations that
already occurred. Conditionals work very
differently. If you look at an if, that
takes, three expressions, the test, the
true branch, and the false branch, we do
not evaluate all of them. Eagerly like
that. We evaluate just the first one and
then use the result to decide which of the
other two we evaluate and then the other
one is never evaluated. So we have not
emphasized this quite as much before, but
this piece of the semantics of language
constrcuts is essential for programming
correctly, so I'm going to switch over to
the code, which I have written out here,
and show you a number of examples that
show that. So let's start with an ordinary
function, a totally normal implementation
of factorial, we've seen such an example
many times. And if I click run and use it,
it will work as expected, normal of 5,
I'll get 120. And by the way this function
grows very fast and Racket has no problem
with large numbers. So if I ask factorial
500 It's happy to print out this very
large number that I will trust is 500
times 499 times 498 and so on, and
everything works correctly. And what
happened is when I called factorial normal
of 500, if I had it evaluated 500. That w
as a value.
Went into the body, decided oh, x is 0, so
I will evaluate the false branch because x
is not 0, excuse me. So only because 500
is not 0, do we decide to do this
multiplication. And when we do a
multiplication, we eagerly look up x. We
get 500. And then, we do this recursive
call, which after a whole lot of work
returns a very large number. And then we
do a multiplication And then we return. So
why am I emphasizing this? Let me show you
a slight variation. Suppose I try to write
a little wrapper for if. So I have a
function, my-if-bad, it takes three
functions, three arguments, e1, e2 and e3.
And then it just calls if with e1, e2, and
e3. So it looks like it's just an
unnecessary function wrapping of if. And
here's a version of factorial-bad that
uses my if-bad. Now I encourage you to try
this out on your own. I'm not going to do
it while we're recording, but if you call
factorial-bad with any number whatsoever
It will never terminate. It will never
terminate. The reason is you call
factorial-bad with an argument, 0, 500, 5,
I don't care what it is, negative 7, and
the 1st thing it has to do is call the
my-if-bad function. And before you call a
function, you evaluate all three
arguments. So you see if x is 0. That will
go quickly. You see if 1, you evaluate 1.
That goes quickly. But then, you have to
evaluate this as well. And that will do a
recursive call, and that will do a
recursive call, and we will never end the
recursion. See it's essential to all of
our recursive functions that if, as we saw
up here in the good version, does not
evaluate both of its branches. It only
evaluates the one we need. But my-if-bad
being a function evaluates both. So it
turns out that I'm going to make a third
version of the example, which is actually
going to work. This is not good style. The
first version is good style, but it's
going to introduce an idiom that's going
to prove very useful to us in upcoming
segments. And that is if you really want a
function It takes three arguments a nd
acts like if. You have to change what it
takes for some of those arguments. Have it
take for e2 and e3 not the result you
want, but a zero argument function that if
you call that function. You get back the
result you want. So what
my-if-strange-but-works does is it
evaluates e1 to get an answer, and then it
either calls e2 with no arguments, or
calls e3 with no arguments, because
remember in Racket, if you want to call. A
zero argument function that's, in some
expression, e, you write e inside a
parentheses. So e to an e3 and any call
my-if-strange-but-works have to themselves
be zero argument functions. So we're doing
higher order functions here. And now, if
you want to write factorial using
my-if-strange-but-works, you can do that.
Let me just make this on the screen for
you. So factorial okay takes in a number
x. Says if x, is z- it calls
my-if-strange-but-works with three
arguments. The result of is x 0. This
function, and this function. So, functions
do not evaluate their bodies until you
call them. We know that. So all three of
these arguments. Evaluate very quickly. If
x is zero, that's very fast. These other
two are already values. We just make the
right closure, and then we call
my-if-strange-but-works, and
my-if-strange-but-works decides which one
of these lambdas to call. And it never
calls the other one. And if you never call
a function, its body is never going to
execute. So this works just fine. If I say
factorial-okay of 500. I will get my very
big number, 'kay? So that is the code I
wanted to show you. Let me emphasize yet
again what is going on and what we call
these things. There's some terminology I
want to introduce related to this idiom.
Okay, so we know how to delay evaluation.
If you have an expression that you don't
want to evaluate yet, you want it to
evaluate later or maybe not at all, put it
in a function and don't call the function.
Thanks to closures, you can really do this
anywhere. Anywhere you want, you can just
take some expression e, replace it with
lambda, take no arguments of e And now you
have a procedure that when you call it,
will produce the answer of then. But you
do have to remember to call it. So that's
what we saw here. You see it on the side,
compared to the example that did not work,
our definition of my if function had to
remember to either Call its 2nd argument
or call its 3rd argument and then our use
of it in factorial had to not pass in the
expressions that we wanted to evaluate,
but to pass in 0 argument functions that
we could then call to get the answers we
wanted. So we have names for this. so let
me, actually let me go back on this slide
here. I forgot to say this middle part I
wanted to say. So when you have these
0-argument functions, we actually have a
name for them. They're called thunks. YOu
can read on the Internet where people
think this word came from. Nobody is quite
sure. Or at least I have not heard a
definitive account, but it's just a funny
word that computer scientists use. A
zero-argument function that is used for
the purpose of delaying evaluation in this
way is called a thunk. You can even use
this as a verb. If you want to tell
someone, No, no, no. YOu're evaluating
that thing too eagerly" We might not need
it passing a function that produces the
result. You can just say, oh, thunk that.
Thunk the expression or the function needs
a thunk. You can say all of these things,
okay? So let's emphasize, 3 very different
things in racket. They look similar, but
it's essential we understand the
difference, or you're going to find it
very difficult to do your next homework
assignment. When you have some expression
e, we evaluate it and we get a result. So
maybe e is plus 3, 4. We evaluate that, we
get 7. But if instead we have a thunk with
e in it, this is a function. That will not
evaluate e at all until you call it. And
then every time you call this thunk, we
will evaluate e and get the result. So
lambda no arguments plus 3 4 is a
procedure. That when you call it, you get
7. And how do you c all a thunk? It looks
strange for people not used to
parentheses, but if you put e in
parentheses, we evaluate e. To get a
thunk, and then we call the thunk that
evaluates the thunk's body, and that is
our final result. We've seen this. It's
why if we put 37 in parentheses we get an
error. 'Cause 37 is not a thunk, and we
put something in parentheses You're
calling it with 0 arguments but if have
lambda (, ) 37, then we could call it as
you see here with parenthesis around it
and you would get back to 37. So we
haven't done this in a useful way yet, the
if that's built into Racket is the right
thing to use. But the upcoming segments
are going to use thunks to code up some
very powerful things in racket. to use the
idea that often delaying or avoiding a
computation is exactly what you want to
do.