, So let's now continue our study of using
thunks to delay computations we might not
need. See how it's, that's a good idea and
how that is a less good idea. So, thunks
let you skip an expensive computation if
you're not going to need it. So this is
great in this sort of first code skeleton
you see here. If I have some function that
takes in a thunk, and I have some if that
ends up taking the true-branch, the branch
that doesn't use the thunk, this is much
better than passing in the result of some
expensive computation. If I didn't use a
thunk here and I had to pass in the result
of the expensive computation, I would have
done a lot of unnecessary work. So, that's
fine, and in those situations, using thunk
is straightforward. But what if you're
more in the situation like here at the
bottom where I have a bunch of separate
conditionals? I don't know if any of them
are going to evealuate to true or evaluate
to false. I don't know how many. But they
do all need, if they're false as in this
case, doesn't matter whether they're true
or false, they do all need the same
result. So should I precompute the results
of the expensive computations for all of
them? That would be wasteful if none of
them need it, but if multiple of them need
it, this situation with the thunk is
actually worse, because I'm going to
reevaluate the thunk every time one of
these ifs ends up being false. So that's
the trade-off, we're going to end up
getting the best of both worlds in a few
minutes. But first, I want to show you an
actual example it's a silly example, but
it's actual code instead of something
where I've left out all the interesting
parts. So just to make this interesting,
this first function is ridiculous, it adds
its arguements, but I've put in enough
extra code that it takes a long time to
evaluate. So if I do something like
slow-add 3 4, you see it actually takes a
second before it produces 7. that way we
can actually see the difference in, in the
example I'm about to show you. Okay? Then
I have this functi on that does
multiplication, but in sort of a strange
way. It takes in a number x, and it takes
in a thunk y that when you call it,
returns a number. And here is how it then
multiplies x and the result of calling y.
If x is 0, it returns zero without ever
executing the thunk, because that's how
multiplication works. We don't care what
the thunk is. If x is 1, then, we evaluate
the thunk and that's our answer.
Otherwise, we evaluate the thunk and we
recursively call my-mult with x minus 1
and not the result of calling the thunk,
but with the thunk itself, because that is
what the my-mult expects, it expects a
thunk for its second argument. So if you
look at this, this is going to end up
calling y-thunk once every time for x. So,
if, if x is seven, its going to call the
thunk seven times, alright?
So, indeed, therefore, even though,
something like slow-add of 3 and 4 is very
slow. Right? If I call my-mult with 0 and
a thunk of slow-add 3 and 4, that's very
fast. want to see it again? Very fast. But
if I were instead multiplying by 1, well,
this is sort of unavoidable. I need to add
three and four, but that's okay. I mean,
what, what else am I going to do? But if I
called it with 2, it's actually going to
take twice as long, because it's calling
that thunk twice. and I don't even want to
sit here while I did something like
multiply by 20. Okay? So thunking was
great in the zero case. It was fine in the
one case, we did have to add three and
four. but it was terrible if for anything
greater than one, because it was actually
a net loss compared to the version of
multiplication that just took in an x and
a y, and therefore, the caller would have
to precomputed the two numbers and
therefore, it would have already done
slow-add. In fact let me show you that
version as well. I can actually do it with
my-mult. So suppose I passed in zero, but
then for the second argument, I
precomputed slow-add, put that in a let,
and then in my lambda, just look up x.
Alright? So, all I'm doing is my second a
rgument to my-mult, which is evaluated
right away, it evaluates x to slow-add of
3 and 4, and then, creates a thunk that
when you call it, will look up x. So, this
is going to call slow-add 3 and 4 once
before you ever call my-mult. So now, if
you call it with 0, it does just take a
little bit because we did call slow-add.
But two doesn't take any longer, and in
fact, 20 doesn't take any longer. They all
take about the same amount of time. Okay?
So that's all fine, but I gave up zero
being fast. It's not fast anymore. Okay?
So that's sort of our motivation. So, what
if we could get the best of both worlds?
What if we could take some computation
that always return the same result, had no
side effects, didn't matter when it was
executed, and we did not compute it until
we needed it? But then, once we did need
it we remembered the answer, so in the
future we, didn't have to compute it
again. We would just return that
remembered result immediately. Well, this
has a name, it's called lazy evaluation,
and languages where most constructs work
this way, were in fact all function work
this way, are called lazy languages and
Haskell is the most well-known, successful
example today. But what I'm going to do in
the next segment in racket, is show you
how we could just code this up. Now,
racket does not work this way for function
argument. Function arguments are all
evaluated at the call site. We do not have
lazy evaluation in Racket just like we
didn't in ML. But we will be able to code
it up, just ourselves. Racket does have
some built-in support that is very
slightly different syntactically in what
it's doing. I'd rather show you the
implementation, so we will use our own,
and then, we will come back and revisit
this multiplication example. So, in our
implementation, all we're going to need
are thunks and mutable pairs, and the
cons, two things we've seen from previous
segments. So we're going to be able to put
together some previous ideas and get these
best of both worlds.