[MUSIC]
So now I want to continue our discussion
of avoiding unnecessary computations
by showing how we can use this
idea of delay in force to get lazy
evaluation implemented ourselves.
So we're trying to get
this best of both worlds,
where we have some expensive computation.
We don't want to compute it unless we need
it, but if we need it more than once,
we want to store the previous answer so
that we can use it again.
So here in one slide is
how we could do this.
We're just going to use a technique of
a little bit of mutation to get what
we want.
So we're going to define two functions
called my-delay and my-force.
So that we don't conflict
with the notional force and
delay provided by the standard library
of racket, and here's how they work.
If you want to delay a computation
call my-delay with a thunk.
Because it's a thunk
whatever body is in there,
fortunately has not been evaluated yet,
okay?
And then let's return a mutable
pair of false and the thunk.
So we never called the thunk,
there's no parenthesis around the th, so
that's going to happen very fast.
We're just going to return that pair.
We haven't done any
expensive computations yet.
Then when you want to use the thunk,
we you need the result,
you weren't able to avoid it,
you're going to have to do it.
Then you call my-force on the thing
returned from my-delay, and
we'll call that thing a promise.
Racket calls them the same thing.
This says,
I promise if you need this thing,
you can force me to give it to you and
I will.
You just do that by calling my-force.
Here is what my-force does.
If the car of the promise is true,
then just return the cdr of the promise.
Now that is not going to be true the first
time you call my-force with a promise.
because you can see right here,
the first thing is false.
So all the action is
here in the false branch.
We use this begin construct that
does a sequence of things and
the result is the last one.
So here's what we do in the false branch.
We do three things.
First, we change the car
of the promise to be true,
indicating that we not
have evaluated this thunk.
We're never going to
evaluate it more than once.
Then we're going to change the cdr of
the promise so that it does not hold
what it used to hold instead it holds
the result of calling the thunk.
So let's look at these parenthesis
when you call mcdr of p that gets
out the thunk.
The next set of parenthesis calls
the thunk then we take that result and
we put it, in the cdr of the promise.
We don't store the thunk anymore,
because we don't need it anymore,
we just have the result of the car.
So after we've done that,
when we look up, mcdr of p,
we have the result of car in the thunk and
we return it.
If anyone ever calls my force on this
promise again, the mcar will be true.
We won`t evaluate the thunk,
we won`t have the thunk anymore,
we'll just return the mcdr.
So all that's really going on here,
is this is a little one of type.
Where the car is true or false,
indicating whether or not you have
to evaluate the thunk or the thunk is gone
and you have the result in its place.
And ideally,
this would be a little abstract data
type that you would hide in a module.
But I haven't shown you Racket module
system, so we'll avoid that and
I'll just show you these
functions as they are here.
So this is the implementation of force and
delay.
How would you use it?
Well the simplest thing to do is
if you had some function somewhere
that maybe need some computation.
Maybe you needed it multiple times, maybe
you didn't need it at all, is you would
just call f, not with a thunk, but
with this pair my-delay returns.
And then anywhere you needed
the computation, you would write my-force.
And by writing my-force,
that would either evaluate the thunk that
happens the first time or just look up
the answer that you used the mutation to
store that's what you do every other time.
So now let's go back to the example
that we had in the previous segment.
Where I have this multiplications
that took in a thunk where I
was passing in very slow thunks.
And I don't need to evaluate the thunk for
0.
I do for 1, and if it's greater than 1,
then I need to multiple times.
And now I'm going to do a little trick.
Here's the implementation of delay in
force, I showed you on the slides.
It's exactly the same.
And now I can use these to
call my-mult in a better way.
In a way that, even if I didn't
know what the first number was,
I would never have to evaluate
the thunk more than once.
So that's the idea, okay?
So here's what I want to do.
I'm going to just run this and
do this in the REPL for you.
Okay, so first,
suppose we don't know what the number is.
I'm going to have to replace this
because I don't have an x, okay?
But what I want to do is I'm
going to create a little
let here to create this delayed thing,
okay?
So this delayed thing,
This promise, all right?
Is now held in this value x.
And now what I need to pass in the my
model, it doesn't expect the promise.
I've wrote in the previews segment
when we didn't have promises.
It expects a thunk.
So I'll just pass in a thunk
that when you call it forces x.
In fact, instead of calling it x,
how about I call it p to
emphasize that that is a promise?
So I create a promise that when
you force it, will add 3 and
4 which remember is this
very slow operation.
And now I'm going to pass into mult
a thunk that says if you call this thunk,
okay, I'm going to force p and then
whatever that result is I will return.
But notice,
we call this thunk more than once,
its going to force the p more than once.
The force will therefore return very
quickly and we'll be fine, okay?
So that is the idea,
it just we don't have an x.
We need to try this for different numbers.
So it turns out that if you try to
multiply it by 0, this is very fast.
But it is not do that for
any of our fancy, all right?
This is because we never
evaluate the thunk, and
we never evaluate the slow ad and
so everything's very fast.
If we do this one time, if we multiply by
1 then we are going to end up forcing this
promise one time and
it takes a second and then we get 7.
But if we multiply 107,
thanks to our lazy evaluation,
the fact that after the first
time we forced the promise,
we updated the promise
to have the answer 7.
So it's just sitting there,
the next time we call my-force,
it just says, the car is true.
I'll return the cdr, the cdr is 7 and
we get the result immediately.
So we didn't have to slow add 3 and
4 100 times, we had to slow add it 1time.
So let's review the example.
I know I split it across two segments
in the interest of time, but
we basically called my-mult
three different ways, okay?
The first time, we just pass in
the normal thunk for the second argument,
delaying evaluation.
And that delayed evaluation was great
when you were multiplying by 0.
It's fine when we were multiplying by 1,
we delayed something we were going
to have to do and then we did it.
For greater than 1, it was terrible
because we ended up slow adding 3 and
4 multiple times.
Even though it would have been better to
now use thunks at all and just do it once.
The second version I showed you,
this was also in the previous segment.
I precomputed I passed in a thunk
that just looked up a variable
that already had the answer to 3 plus 4.
Now that precomputation
was something I paid once,
regardless of the other argument.
So that's okay, I only did it once, but
I didn't get to great thing
when I was multiplying by 0.
This was just the normal or
lesser value of everything once and
that's as best as I can do and
that's okay.
Now with promises, I'm getting the both
best of these two these two worlds.
That when the first argument was 0,
I never forced the promise, so
I never did the slow add.
If it was one, I did do the slow add.
That's basically as good as
I did in the first version.
But then thanks to how promises work,
I stored the result, okay?
So if it was going to be called again,
I would have it.
And in fact that is what happened
when I multiplied by a 100,
the first time that it's lowered and
the other 99 times.
I just looked up the answer
that was stored in the promise.
So that's our example of how we
can use mutation and thunking.
To get this idea of lazy evaluation
which can be the best of both
worlds in terms of delaying
computations you might not need.
But making sure you do not
do them more than once.