, In this segment and the next, we're
going to talk about streams which are a
different programming idiom that also
needs some notion of delaying evaluation
and the implementation will use thunks. In
order to accomplish that. So, a stream is
a word that we use in computer science to
mean an infinite sequence of values. All
right, something that can go on for as
long as you need. It behaves like
somethings infinitely big. Now, one thing
about infinite sized things, you can't
actually make them. Right? We need
something that's going to represent
something that could go on forever. And
the key idea we're going to use is to use
a thunk to delay the evaluation of most of
the sequence and only generate some prefix
of the sequence That some other
computation needs. We're not going to need
any new language constructs. This is just
a program idiom using thunks and things
like that. But it's a powerful concept for
dividing labor up in a way that works in a
lot of different software systems. So, the
idea is that. The, the program, part of
the program producting the stream,
creating the stream, knows how to create
any number of values you need. But does
not know how many you need. Whereas the
stream consumer can ask for these values
as it goes along, without knowing anything
about the process that is generating So it
turns out this comes up a lot in software
systems. It's okay if you're not familiar
with any of these examples, but I thought
I would mention them for those of you who
are. one way is if you're implementing
code that need to respond to a whole bunch
of user events, mouse clicks, keyboard
presses, things like that, we saw earlier
in the course we could do that will call
backs. But another way to do it is to
think of that as some stream of events.
We'll as for each one as we need it, and
then we'll compute some result with that
thing so far. And someone else will
generate those events as they occur. Have
you ever programmed with pipes in the UNIX
shell system? It turns out that the second
c ommand, pulls data from the first
command as it needs it so it views the
first command as a stream. And the first
command's output is generating that
stream. There's also a nice connection
with electrical engineering and circuits,
that if you think of a timed circuit with
feedback. You can think of the different
output values it's sending on it's output
wires as forming an infinitely long
sequence. And then the, the circuits
reading those values Can read the ones
that they're interested in. Anyway, just
optional things just showing this is kind
of, of a universal concept even if you
find it a bit abstract. You'll also see
some simpler and more fun examples on the
homeowrk assignment associated with this
material. Okay, so we want to represent a
stream. In some way that we don't actually
generate an infinitely long list or
something like that. So here's how we will
do it. We're going to represent a stream
as a thunk. So a stream will just be a
thunk, but not just any kind of thunk, a
thunk that, when you call it gives back a
pair, where the car is the next thing in
the sequence. The first thing in the
sequence. And the CDR, is a stream for
values 2 through infinity. So it is a
stream that, if you use it, you get the
next value. So in this segment, I'm just
going to show you how to use this thing
Then in the next segment, we'll see how to
define our own. Using them usually helps
explain what they are and get a little
better sense before we try to create them.
So I've already loaded the file where I've
created the streams I will show you in the
next segment. And one of the streams is
the infinite sequence of powers-of-two.
Two.
So you know, the first thing this thing
returns - I, I forget if it starts at 1 or
2. And the 4, and then 8, and then 16, and
then 32, on forever. Because we don't know
how many powers of 2 we need. But when I
said powers-of-two, as you saw here, all I
got back was a procedure. Because our
streams are thunks. That when you call
them return a pair. So, how do you call a
thunk? You put it in parentheses,
powers-of-two. And look at that. I got
back a pair, who's first component is 2,
so I did set it up to start at 2, and a
second component is another procedure.
Turns out that's a thunk. So, if I wanted
the first thing in the sequence, I could
just say car. Of calling that. And if I
wanted the second sequence. Let's think
about this. Need to call the cutter to get
another stream, a stream is a thunk so I
need to call it. And then I need the car
of that. And that gets me four. What if I
wanted the next element of the sequence?
Well this thing is four, the cdr is
another stream, a stream is a thunk so you
call it. That gives back a pair and I made
the car. of that.
And that would give me 8. Now of course we
wouldn't keep programming like this to get
16 or 32. The idea is we would have some
sort of recursive function that is passing
this next stream onto say some recursive
call. And then we. Apply that string, to
get a pair, and we take car to get the
next thing. And so if you wanted to say
add up the first 100 powers of 2, you
would just have some little recursive
function, that would be using this string
as you go along. So what I thought I would
do instead of showing you that is show you
something even more general. Let's define
a recursive function that I'll call number
until. That's going to take in a stream.
And the function which I'll call tester,
alright, and the idea of what this is
going to do is it's going to count how
many stream elements you need to process
before tester returns true for the first
time. So if it doesn't ever returns true,
we're going to an infinite loop. But
otherwise, we'll stop as soon as we get
our first true and we'll return the count
of how many we've got. So I'm going to do
this with a little tail recursive helper
function. So I have a little letrec here.
So I'm going to take in my current stream,
the stream that has all the elements I
haven't processed so, So far, my
accumulator which is my answer so far, I'm
goi ng to have to put some stuff in here.
and then I'm just going to call F the
stream I started with, and 1, that's my
initial accumulator. So now the idea is
all the body of F has to do, where I've
left this dot, dot, dot. is see well, what
does tester have to say on the first
element of the stream. If that's true,
return answer. Ohterwise, call f again
with one more and with the tail, if you
will of the stream. The rest of the
values. So here's how I'm going to do
this. Let's first of all call that stream.
We know a stream is a thunk. All right?
I'll get rid of these so you can see it.
So I know a stream is a thunk. So if I
call it, I should get back this pair.
Right, of the first element, and then the
stream that is the rest of the elements.
'Kay.
Now that I have that pair, let's call
tester on the car. If I get back true, I'm
done. Return ans.
All right? Otherwise, call f. On the cdr
of the pair, that's my new stream, right?
Don't call it yet, right? We don't want a
pair, right? This would be a pair. But f
expects the stream and then f itself calls
that thunk to get back the pair. So just
with the cdr and then one more for the
accumulator. That's my call to f. That
finishes my if, my let, my definition of
the lambda for f, and this letrec that I
then to use to start by calling f with the
stream that was passed a number, until.
End 1. So, and then I need to end my
define, my letrec, and my define, and now
I've just defined a function, that's all I
did. Okay.
So now if I call number-until with the
stream powers of 2. Alright? And how about
a little function that takes in a number
and says, does that number equal 16? I go
back to 4. It took me four times through
the stream until I got something that
equaled 16. Let's have a little more fun.
How about I keep going until I get a
number that is bigger than This number.
Ok? The great thing about powers of two is
they grow really fast, so that took 339
tries. If I had come up with a number ten
times bigger it'll take 343 tries, and ten
times better than that it'll probably take
346 tries. because powers-of-two multiply
really fast. Let me point out that when
you program your streams, you tend to make
lots of mistakes with parenthesis. Think
very carefully about, do I want to pass in
a stream or a pair that I get back when I
call the thunk? If I get this wrong and I
put parenthesis here And are passing to
number until a pair. And therefore right
here you can just see at the top of the
screen. That's going to be pair when you
try to treat a pair as a function, you get
a big nasty error function. It says,
procedure obligation expected procedure
given the pair two and some string. So you
have to think very carefully about the
difference between a thunk and a pair. And
if you do that, you can do some beautiful
programming by using streams with
beautiful recursive functions to get
interesting results.