[MUSIC] Let's talk some more about
parentheses, and let's particularly
understand that parentheses are not
optional in Racket.
They are common, but every time we use
them they have a meaning.
So this is a habit you have to break
yourself of.
In languages that don't have a syntax
like Racket, you're used to just putting
in extra parentheses to help you
understand something, and if something
isn't working, maybe you'll just put in
more parentheses and then it will start
working.
It doesn't work in Racket.
The parentheses always have a meaning.
In particular, in most places, if you
write in, something in parentheses that
means evaluate e To a result, and then
call it as a function with 0 arguments
because the way we do a function call is
parenthesis, thing you want to call, and
then argument.
So if there are no arguments, this is
call it with 0 arguments.
So, look at this one with 2 parentheses.
This says evaluate e, call the result as
a function with 0 arguments.
Get back a result and call that as a
function with zero arguments.
This makes perfect sense.
We might even do things like this, but if
it's not what you mean, you're going to
get an error message.
You're going to try to treat something as
a function that is not a function.
Now without static typing, this sort of
thing will work just fine when you save
your file, when you click run, but once
you actually execute the code, maybe it's
inside a function body somewhere, then
you can get an error message.
It can be hard to diagnose and your first
reaction is to just start playing with
the parentheses,
and it's only going to get you into more
trouble.
So let's work through some examples to
give you some practice with this.
And the moral of the story is always,
slow down, think about your parentheses.
If you're confused why they're there,
delete them and start over.
Indent your code well, it'll always work
fine.
So what I'm going to do is just show you
a bunch of versions of a factorial
function, 1 of my favorite little
functions for examples.
And I'm going to start by getting it
correct, okay.
So, so far what I've written while I was
talking to you is In factors of one
argument function, so these parenthesis
have to be here.
Then, I have an if, and I need 3
arguments.
This is the first one.
It's a call to the equals function.
This is the second one, which is 1.
And then this is the third one, which is
multiplication of n.
And then another call.
Always put a parenthesis before the call,
a fact, to get the argument to that I
need to call minus with n and 1, close,
close, close, close close.
And let's run this, and if I do fact of
5, I get 120 in, and if I do fact of 10 I
think I get about 300,000.
Oh, 3, 3.6 million excuse me.
Okay? So, that version was right.
Now, let's do a bunch of versions that
are wrong, and try to figure out why.
So let me do, I'll call it fact 1.
N if equal n 0, then 1,
else n fact 1 of -n1,
close everything, and run it.
It all seems to be fine.
I call fact one with five, [COUGH] and I
get procedure application expected
procedure given one.
No arguments, and that's exactly right.
If you look up here, what I did while I
was talking to you and typing is I put
this 1 in parentheses, and as an
expression, that means call 1 as a
function with no arguments.
There's no type checker to separate our
functions from our integers, but when we
went execute this in the base case when 1
was 0 That's when we got the error.
So, we had already made about five
recursive calls, and then we got the
error.
And we would fix this us by deleting
these parentheses.
We can just leave this in here, because
As long as we don't call that function,
it won't be a problem.
Let me show you a small variant is
fact1b.
Suppose I made the same mistake.
Alright, just like this.
Alright, so you might think, if you're
not paying very careful attention, that
this fact1b is exactly like the first
line, and yet it totally seams to work.
In fact, this will work for almost every
argument.
The only argument it won't work for is 0.
So what's going on here? well here I, I,
I actually made a totally different
mistake, this is wrong.
If you call fact1b with a 0 you will try
to apply 1 with 0 argument, but I'm not
actually using fact1b recursively here,
I, I wrote fact here, right.
I didn't write fact1b I wrote fact, and
so in fact pardon the pun, when I call
fact1b with 5 I end up not calling fact1b
again but going up to this first correct
version.
And so that's why we didn't get the error
unless we called fact1b originally with
0, okay.
Good, let's try another 1 how about fact2
excuse me.
I need this parenthesis here.
how about if = n 01.
Otherwise, n of fact 2.
I will remember, now, to call the correct
thing recursively.
[SOUND].
And like that, and click run.
And this is actually a syntax error.
So this, it will not allow.
To start.
I don't have to test it out to get an
error.
Dr.
Racket will detect that, with a good
error message here.
If has five parts after the keyword.
If is always supposed to have three
parts, and yet clearly, syntactically, it
has five,
equal n zero, one, and this
multiplication.
And that makes no sense, If has to have
three and what happened is I forgot the
parenthesis around the function call to
equal, ok? How about if I do it this way?
If, so I'm going to get almost all of
this right.
Three terms multiplied by N fact of minus
N one.
Just like this, click run, and I get bad
syntax multiple expressions after
identifier, indeed I do.
So if I say define in a variable, notice
I forgot this parenthesis after the
fact3, then it's expecting like a val
binding in ML, right, that I evaluate
something here.
But I have 2 things after the variable,
this is the first one, this is the second
one, right.
I messed up 1 parenthesis, this left
parenthesis is supposed to be over here
before the name of the function, not
before the argument.
Okay, parenthesis matter, I know I am
typing fast in order to keep the video
short but you should think which concerts
am I using.
And in this case if you are defining a
function you put a parenthesis before the
function name.
You do not put a parenthesis before the
argument list.
Look how it up here in the correct
version I have this and then I have my
function buddy.
Ok, alright lets do another one this one
oh so I need to comment these out these
ones so I can get the other ones to go
ahead and click run so I can test them
out.
Here is my fourth version of fact how
about if equals zero one other wise
Multiply n by my recursive call to fact
4, with -n and 1.
[SOUND].
Click run.
This compiles just fine.
Call fact 4 was zero.
I get the right thing, 1.
But if I call fact 4 with 5, I get an
error message.
And it says that * expects type number as
second argument, given procedure fact4.
That's exactly right.
So, it turns out, that multiplication, we
saw back in our first or second segment
on Racket, can take any number of
arguments, and here I'm passing it three
arguments, n, the function fact4, and n -
1.
Functions are first class, so you can
pass them to other functions, but then
the body of multiply says wait a minute,
I don't have a number.
I'm going to raise an error.
A typechecker in a language like ML would
catch this.
In Racket, we have to test our functions
to test this sort of error, then we need
to fix up our parentheses.
we need an extra parenthesis before
fact4.
And then a after it in order to call
multiply with two arguments not three.
OK let's do a couple more here's fact
five n if equal n zero one otherwise
multiply n by fact five minus N one.
So here, we saw in fact four we had too
few parenthesis.
It made us annoyed.
We just wanted to get our homework done
so we added some more.
The problem of course is this still
works, but we added too many.
And what it says is Procedure Fact five
expects one argument given zero.
That's exactly right, right here.
I'm calling fact 5 with zero arguments.
Fact 5 which I'm defining recursively
right here, expects one argument.
You are not allowed to call functions
with the wrong number of arguments, and
we get an error.
And then let's do one last one, just
because it's good practice.
n times, so this is a very natural thing
to do, because we've all grown accustomed
to writing arithmetic a certain way.
And you can probably see the error this
time.
I wrote * second.
That's supposed to be the function I'm
calling.
Instead, what do you think would happen
here? Well, again, the base case is fine,
but if n is not 0, then I'm going to try
to treat n as a function.
So it expects some sort of error message
where the number I called fact 6 with is
trying to be called with some arguments,
alright?
When you look at your code carefully you
can sometimes come up with a better error
message then you would get from a system
that has no idea what it is your trying
to do.
Here I think it will actually do a pretty
good job.
So the procedure application, expected
procedure given one arguments where
procedure times 1.
And, what actually happened is, you would
think this happened when n would be 5.
Why, why does it say given 5? Well, it
never got to this call.
It went ahead and did the recursion, and
that did the recursion, and that did the
recursion, and it's on the way back out
of the recursion that it first detects
the error.
When it tries to say, 1 times, and the
recursive result, 1.
And if, I'm going to write this out here
in Racket, you have 1*1, that's going to
give the exact same error message,
because it's going to say that it
expected a procedure in that first
position, and you have a 1.