[MUSIC] In this segment, I want to have
out first discussion about how Racket is
a dynamically typed language, and
emphasize how it lets us build up our
data structures without any type system
or type checker getting in our way.
So, this is a major topic that we'll
discuss later.
After we're more familiar with them,
dynamic typing,
I want to contrast it with static typing
and discuss the advantages and
disadvantages of each.
But, for right now, we just need to get
used to the idea that Racket doesn't
detect a lot of things as type errors,
and understand what that let's us do.
Now, you may get frustrated by the lack
of a type checker.
As much as you don't like type error
messages, they're often better than not
getting them.
So, if you made a mistake in your Racket
code, like write something like n*x
instead of times nx, Racket will let you
run that code without any problem. and if
you don't execute that particular
expression,
you'll never see that it's an error. So,
it's only if you have a test case that
actually gets there, looks up and in the
environment, presumably does not find a
function expecting two arguments, the
first of which is times that you will get
an error message.
Okay? So, it makes testing for this sort
of error actually more important.
But the advantages, it let's us build
very flexible data structures without
having to go through a bunch of work to
tell the type checker what we're trying
to do.
So, the example we're going to do in this
segment is we're going to end up writing
a sum function, that sums up all numbers
in a list.
But its not just a list of numbers.
Our list can either have numbers or other
lists of numbers, or inside those list
more lists that have more lists or
numbers.
And so, what we're, what the idea is to
allow arbitrary nesting of lists and
numbers as deep as we want and still sum
up all the numbers that appear anywhere
in any of those lists.
So, you can't do this in ML without
creating a data type binding and
constructors in order to put numbers and
lists in the same list.
You can't do that according to the type
checker that's why you have to use a data
type binding.
But in Racket, there is no type checker,
so we'll just be able to do this.
So, let's just go over here and explain
what I'm talking about.
So, let me first define a couple example
lists, so you know the sort of thing I'm
doing.
So, my first list here, xs, I can just
have a normal list of numbers,
4, 5, 6, okay?
But I could also have a list we say had
another list in it with 4 and 5, and then
had 6 and 7.
And then, had a list 8, and then may be a
9 and 2 and 3.
And then, list a 0 and 1, okay?
So, what I've just to find and bound to y
is a list with a bunch of elements.
Here is the first one.
Second one is 6, third is 7, fourth is
the list 8, then a 9, a 2, and a 3, and
then this list with two more elements.
And this list has a 4 and a 5, and this
list has a 0 and a 1, but I can list more
deeply. Maybe here I have a list of a 5
and another 0.
And so, I can nest these things as deep
as I want and it's still going to be the
sort of thing I want my function to work
properly on, okay? So now let's actually
define it.
I'm going to define two versions in this
segment, so we'll start with sum1 and
I'll call the other one sum2.
And I forgot a parenthesis here.
And I want to take an a list let's call
it xs.
this is just shadowing, this is just a
function parameter.
It's not the list xs I defined above.
and what I wanted to do is if this
argument xs is null,
then zero, right? The sum of the empty
list is zero.
Just like we're familiar with.
Otherwise, I can't just go and add the
car of xs because the car might hold
another list.
So, I better not just do that.
I better check whether it's a list or a
number.
I can do that with this number function.
For all the built in types in Racket,
they all come with these functions that
test at run time, do you have one of
these things? In a statitically typed
language, you wouldn't need this. The
type checker will tell you what type of
thing you have where.
But in Racket, we can pass anything
anywhere, and so these functions are very
useful.
So, if that evaluates to true, then we
definitely have a number. So, let's go
ahead an add the car of xs to the
recursively summering the cdr of xs.
So, add those two things together and
thats a good true branch for our
conditional. Otherwise, we'll assume that
if it's not a number it must be a list,
because the sort of thing someone is
supposed to work on is this combination
of lists and numbers that go arbitrarily
deep. So, let's do sum1 car of xs so that
is going to sum up everything in the car.
The car is itself a list, so recursively
sum all of those. And then, let's
recursively sum the cdr of xes.
Add those two things together,
that's a good false branch.
That takes care of the false branch if we
don't have the empty list,
and that takes care of our definition.
So, let's try this out.
You can see the sum function up there.
And we can try sum1 on xs, and it works
fine.
We get 15.
We can try sum1 on ys, and we get 45. And
I'll hope that that's correct, that, that
sums up all the numbers we have up in
that long list.
and let's try one more.
Let's try list of list of list of 4 and
then a 5 and list of a 7 and a 2.
And that works fine.
We get 18 which looks right.
But, won't work is that maybe deep
inside, one of these lists we have
something that's not a number or a list,
okay? Then we'll get an error because
eventually we'll, we will recur to that
position.
And R function assumed that we would
never hit a string.
So, something wasn't a number.
So, we tried to treat it as a list.
We tried to take the car of a string.
And if you take a car of high that does
not make any sense.
And you get a runtime error, okay? okay.
So, this is fine.
someone misused our function.
When you misuse a function in a
dynamically typed language, you often get
these sort of errors.
But, if we wanted to support this, we
could write a second version that if you
hit something in a list that is not a
number and not a nested list, let's just
skip it.
You know, treat it as zero,
right? Just skip over it in our summing.
Now, there's probably a number of ways to
do this.
I'm going to show you one that is you
know, as much like our first version as
possible.
So, if I have the empty list, zero's a
good answer. And if I have a number in
the car of the list, then I definitely
want to add that number to recursively
summing everything in the cdr, okay?
But now, let's not assume I have a list,
all right? This is a matter of style
whether, you know, it's up to you to
force callers to do the right thing and
they'll be in error otherwise.
Or if you want to say, alright,
well, if it's a list, then I'll do what I
did before,
sum2 car xs and sum2 of cdr xs,
right? So, I have a list in the first
position.
So, recursively add all that.
The cdr is always another list.
And so, add all that, and then add the
two together.
Otherwise, I don't want to touch the
thing in the car because it might be
something like a string.
So, let's just sum the elements in the
cdr of the list,
okay? So, that's the case we didn't have
before.
We were assuming we had a list down here.
And now, we're explicitly checking.
I can run this.
if you just do Alt P in DrRacket, you get
your previous commands.
You can cycle through those.
And now, this was the thing that gave us
an error before.
But now, instead of calling it sum1, I
just go back here and edit it to be sum2,
then I get the right answer, alright?
That 14 it skipped over.
and if this five were instead something
like -3, sorry, I want something that's
not a number or a list. How about false?
Okay? Then, it'll just nicely skip it and
I'll get 13,
okay? Now, sum2 doesn't work for just
anything.
It still assumes the initial argument is
a list.
If I tried to call it with hi, I would
still get a error message.
And that's because right here I start
checking the car before I even know it
has a list.
And that's a third version.
If you really want it to work for
anything, and maybe for something else
like this return zero, then I'll leave
that as an exercise for you.
But, what we've seen here is that we
could do correct versions of sum that
work for lists of numbers and numbers of
lists without having to create ML style
data type bindings.
There's no type declaration at all.
We can just, flipping back here to the
file, define x's and y's to be lists
holding anything we want.
And, in fact, you can hold, have a single
list, hold the false, and hi, and 14, and
Racket has no problem with this
whatsoever.
We can run this, we can ask for the car
of zs, we get false, we can ask for the
cdr of zs.
We get the list holding hi and 14, and so
on.
And so, this is more convenient for us.
But, of course, it also makes it a little
harder to test our functions and to
document what type of argument they
expect.