[MUSIC].
In this segment, I want to introduce the
cond construct into racket.
it's useful in place of nested
if/then/else expressions.
It's better style.
And it's not very hard to learn.
I just put it off to get us started with
the bigger ideas in Racket.
But you do want to use this.
Whenever you have a bunch of nested ifs
where your else branch, your false branch
is another if.
And then the else branch of that is
another if.
Cond is definitely better style.
You can think of cond as just syntactic
sugar for nested if/then/else
expressions.
Or if you prefer to think of if/then/else
as syntactic sugar for a cond with just 2
branches, that's fine too.
So here's how cond works.
It's just a special form, COND.
So of course, it has a parenthesis at the
beginning, and at the end.
We then have, in parentheses, n pairs of
expressions, right? So I have a bracket,
because that's the convention.
Semantically, it doesn't matter.
Just, syntactically, it's better styled
at the bracket.
matter.
You can use round parentheses if you
want.
Then, 1 expression.
Then another expression and that branch,
another one, another one.
The way this works is all these first
ones are tests and all the second ones
are what to do if that test is true.
So if the first one is true Then do the
second one.
Else, if this is true, do this one.
Else, if this one.
And you stop, and your result is the
first branch, where the thing on the left
was true, and then you evaluate the thing
on the right, and that's your answer.
Now, as a matter of style, it's very
important that your last branch typically
be just true, which we write in Racket,
#t.
This is your default case.
This is saying, in any other case, I want
to evaluate this last expression, and
that's my.
My answer.
If you do not do this and your last test
expression also evaluates the false then
cond will return some strange void object
which is a bad idea in Racket, it will
not produce an error here but probably
it's going to return some result that
someone else doesn't want to use.
And you'll end up confusing yourself.
So always make your last branch have as
it's test a true, okay.
So let's go over here to DrRacket, here
is the sum functions that I wrote in the
previous segment.
So this first, this First one works on a
list of numbers that could have nested
within them other lists of numbers and so
on, as deep as you want.
And it's an error tab, anything in there
that's not a list or a number.
And then the second version that if
there's some non-list or non-number
nested somewhere on the list, we just
skip over it.
[UNKNOWN] And we can rewrite each of
these just using cond, and so I'm going
to do that just in a different file here
there we go.
And, this will not be very difficult so
I'll call these sum 3 and sum 4 to
continue what we were doing in the
previous section and I can have a cond
which of course can have any number of
branches I want and the first branch will
be that if the input X's is the No list,
the empty list, the results should be 0.
Otherwise if the 1st element is a number,
so number of car of x's, then add the car
of x's to the recursive sum of the cdr of
x's.
That will end that branch.
Notice you can type round parentheses and
if they match square brackets, Dr.
Racket will turn it into a square bracket
for us.
And in any other case for this version,
so for #t, I'll go ahead and assume that
the first element of xs is itself a list.
So I know how to sum a list.
I call sum3, and then I need to sum3 the
cdr of xs.
Codes that, and this should all be
correct if we compare it to our other
version, I'm going to flip that over
here, you'll see that we have the same
three cases.
If it's null 0, the first number first
thing to list as a number, do this
addition.
Otherwise do this addition but you'll
probably agree with me that it's easier
to read laid out as this [UNKNOWN] we can
see that three tests null, number and
true quite easily and then what to do in
each case by the expression that follows
that test, k, so that's sum three now let
me quickly do sum four.
It's the same idea.
I'll have a con and if the list is empty
then return 0, if the first thing in the
list is a number then, sorry, number car
of xs.
And in fact it's exactly the same as
before, car of xs, sum4 For now cdr of
x's, alright? Otherwise I have another
test in this version where I ask, well is
x's a list? Because if it is, then I want
to do what I used to do just by the
default assumption but this time I check
that it was the list.
So you can see the difference between the
2 versions quite easily and in any other
case.
Skip the car of xs and just cdr of xs and
if you look back this is exactly like
some 2 just laid out nicely with the cond
construct.
So that's our example.
Now what I want to do is go back to the
slides and talk about one other issue,
okay.
as before o sorry here's where I want to
to go, okay.
So for both if and cond.
I just didn't tell you this for if and
now I'm telling you for both.
The test expression, that first
expression does not have to be true or
false, #t or #f.
It turns out, it can be anything.
It's never an error and it's fine.
So what is the semantic? The schemantics
in Racket is that anything other than
false, counts as true.
So, the only way to take the false
brancgh is if you have #f.
But, to take the true branch you so not
need #t.
You just need anything that is not #f.
This is very common in dyanamically type
languages, some dynamicaaly type
languagees make other things false.
Things like the empty list or the empty
string, or things like this.
That's not true in Racket.
In Racket there's exactly one thing
that's false, and that's #f.
Everything else counts as true.
Now this makes no sense in a statically
typed language.
In a statically typed language We would
insist that a conditional expression take
something of type Buhl[UNKNOWN] for it's
first argument.
Since everything has exactly one type,
there is no point in allowing anything to
be in that first position.
But a language like Racket, you can You
can do this.
Now, a lot of people consider this bad
style.
A lot of people consider this convenient
and okay.
And some people are kind of in between
and say it depends on the situation.
I'm not a huge fan of this construct, but
since it reinforces the idea That Racket
supports dynamic typing, I though I would
show it to you.
So let's do couple quick examples here.
so first of all let me just click run and
do something at the repel here.
So what if I said if 34 then 14, l's 15.
Well since 34 is not false it must be
true and I get 14.
Okay? So it's just that simple and I
could say if empty list.
14 else 15, and I would get 14, and so
on.
But if I saw hash false, then I get 15.
So now, let me just paste in a quick
example of where this is useful, and I
want to take the time to type it all out.
and you don't need this, okay? You could,
you know, get by in, in Racket without
this feature.
Woop.
There we go.
So what this function does is it cou, it
takes in a list, just a list no nested
list or anything, and counts how many
falses are in it.
Okay? So let me just run this.
So we can see it in action.
And so if I count falses of the list 34,
true, and hi, I should get 0.
But if I add in here a couple falses,
maybe one at the beginning, one there,
and how about a couple at the end.
Then I get 4.
That's all it does, it counts how many
false's there are.
Use cond, which we introduced here, and
we say that if the list is empty then
there are 0 false's in it.
If the car of x's is not false, well here
is one way to do that.
Right? If car of x's is anything other
than false Then this test will be true.
And so we'll recursively count the falses
in the cdr.
And in any other case, the only case
that's left, it that the first thing in
the list was false.
And then we would add 1 to count falses
of cdr of xes, okay? So that is an
example of using this feature that
everything that is not #f is true.
The only thing that is false is #f. But
the main idea in this segment was using
cond for better style, and now we can use
it in all of our homework problems in
Racket programming, rather than nested
if/then/else.