[MUSIC]
In this segment, I want to
introduce Racket's local bindings.
This is what in ML,
we use let-expressions for.
Racket also has let-expressions, but
it actually has a variety of them.
And that'll let us
understand some interesting,
different semantics between
the different kinds of let-expressions.
But before we get that let me
show you an initial example,
it's one of the same
examples I showed you in ML.
Let's compute the maximum number in
a list, we'll assume we're past the list,
and assume that lost only has numbers.
Let's use cond which we now know.
And let's ask first,
if we have an empty list.
There's no such thing as
the maximum of an empty list.
So there is a built in feature in racket
called error, that we can pass a string.
And if this evaluates execution will stop
with this error, so that seems reasonable.
Otherwise, if we have the one
element list, how do you check for
a one element list?
You check if the cdr is empty,
that makes sense.
Then let's just return the car because
the largest element of one element list is
that element itself.
Otherwise, we know we better not make
multiple recursive calls on the same list.
We saw an exponential blow up when
we did this sort of thing in ML.
So let's create a local variable to hold
the max of the cdr and
then we will compete with that here.
Now before I go on, let me show you
since I just introduced syntax,
let is the new special
form I'm showing you.
Then you have the starting right
preferences and that will eventually be
matched by this close preferences and
then you have the body.
And then you close the let, okay?
And what goes here on the dot, dot,
dot is one or more variable bindings.
Each one goes in parenthesis as
a matter of style use square brackets,
and then it's x1 expression 1,
x2 expression 2 and so on.
You can have as many of these as you want.
So this is just like in ML having
a number of val bindings in the same
let-expression.
And so in this particular case,
I didn't need en of them, right?
I only needed one, and so
I'll just put that back up here.
And so when you have one,
it's often easy to forget,
you need this extra pair
of a parenthesis around it.
But you do need those extra ones,
otherwise,
it just won't work syntactically.
So now I have the place
where I bound my variables.
There was one here tlans, and
now I just need the body.
And my body will just be,
if the tlans is greater than the first
element on the list, the car of xs.
Then return the tlans,
otherwise return the head of the list and
that should work as
a definition of max list.
So this is just an example of showing
you this let-expression, right?
Where the body is this if, and
then the list of bindings is here.
And this one had one binding in it,
which is right there.
So that's our example of a let expression,
but now let me
do the rest of this in the slides and show
you we have actually more to understand.
So it turns out racket has four different
ways to define local variables.
Let, let*, letrec, and local defines.
And these varieties is actually good,
they have different semantics.
And so with that different semantics,
we can use the best one that's most
convenient for the code we're writing.
And which helps communicate to
the person reading our code,
which of the different
semantics we mean here.
And is most convenient for
that computation we're doing, okay?
So this will help us learn
things about scope and
environments better by seeing
the two actually can get three
different reasonable definitions to
the meaning of the let-expression.
Let versus let* versus letrec.
So I'll just go through of these in order,
we'll start with the let.
We know that a let-expression can
bind any number of local variables.
I showed that to you in Dr. Racket,
but the expressions are all evaluated
in the environment from before
the let-expression, okay?
So given a let-expression, we of course
the body of the let-expression uses
all the variables we defined.
But it turns out
the expressions that initialized
those variables do not use
the earlier variables.
They are all evaluated in the environment
from before the let-expression.
This is not how ML let-expressions work.
Different languages have
different semantics for things.
Let's look at the example
here on the slide,
this is a function that takes
in a number x and doubles it.
Just does it in a silly way to
emphasize the semantics that I want to.
So here when I say let x be x + 3,
this x on the right hand side is going to
be the x from before the let-expression,
the parameter to the function.
So this is parameter + 3.
y with + x 2,
this x will also be the parameter.
This is not how ML works.
So since it is also the parameter,
y is parameter + 2.
So if I take these together,
I end up with 2 times the parameter + 5.
So if I subtract 5 back out,
I get twice the parameter and
that's why it's a silly double function.
So why do you want this semantics?
Well, if you're not reusing variable names
here, the way this x is shadowing that.
This doesn't really matter and so
if you're not doing any shadowing,
it's best style in racket to just use let.
But it's also convenient in
certain other situations.
Like if you wanted to have
some body where x was y and
y was x, you can write it like this.
And under ML semantics this does not work.
That x would be bound to the outer y, and
then y would also be bound to the outer y.
Because under ML semantics the second
x would be bound to the first one.
But under Racket's let, let x be y and
y be x would properly change the bindings
of x and y to each other for the body
of the let-expression, so that's let.
Now, let me show you let*.
So syntactically let* works exactly like
let, it just has one more character,
it has a * after the t, okay?
And this is ML's let, okay?
The expressions are all evaluated
in the environment produced from
the previous bindings.
If we didn't have this,
we would have to nest our lets
when we wanted this behavior.
So here's our example,
you're probably comfortable with this one,
only because we used ML first in
our study of programming languages.
Here, when I say + x 3, that will be the x
that is the parameter to the function.
And now for
y, when I say + x 2, I use the environment
created by all the earlier bindings.
So I will use the shadowed x, so y will
in fact be bound to the parameter + 5.
So if I have parameter + 3, and parameter
+ 5, when I add those together and
subtract 8, I end up doubling
the argument, so that is let*.
It's much more like ML's let-expression,
okay?
Another one, so that's let and let*.
Now we do letrec syntactically
it's just like the others,
except instead of running let or
let*, we write L-E-T-R-E-C, letrec.
This is for, the rec is short for
recursion and the expressions
are evaluated in an environment
that includes all the bindings.
The earlier ones and the later ones.
It's more like MLs and for
finding mutually recursive things.
So here's an example,
it's a little more complicated actually
triples its argument instead of doubling,
we're getting into fancier stuff, right?
So I have three local variables,
y, f, and w.
And if you look at f, it's a function.
Then when you call it, uses it's
argument z, but also uses y, w, and x.
And x because we don't have
any shadowing anywhere here,
will be the parameter to the function.
y will be the earlier binding which
we could have also gotten with let*.
We could not have done that with let,
and w will be the later binding.
And this is what you have to use letrec
for, it will not work with let or
with let*.
So when we call f-9, z will -9,
y will be the parameter + 2,
w will be the parameter + 7.
And x will be the parameter as we
put it all together you end up
tripling your argument.
So why does the language have letrec?
Well you need this sort of thing for
mutually recursive functions,
f calls g, g calls f.
All defined within a define like this,
but we have to be careful here.
I recommend only using letrec for when
you have mutually recursive functions.
It's generally not so useful otherwise.
Because the expressions
are still evaluated in order.
You have to be really careful here.
What if y,
instead of saying + x 2 had said + w 2?
Well w is in the environment,
that's the rule of letrec.
But we have not evaluated it yet
because at runtime,
when we evaluate these bindings,
we do still evaluate them in order.
So Racket would not like this very much.
It turns out not to raise an error instead
when it hits that x, sorry, that w.
It will return some funny
undefined thing and then we will
get an error because we call plus on
undefined, that causes an error, okay?
So this would be bad style,
it would surely be a bug.
The reason why it works for
f is because the use of w,
the forward reference, the use of the
later binding is inside a function body.
And we know that when we evaluate
this expression, this Lambda,
we don't evaluate the function body.
We don't evaluate function
bodies untill we call them.
So we evaluate y we get parameter + 2,
we evaluate f we create a closure,
we evaluate w we parameter + 7.
And now when we call
that closure we created,
w has been nicely initialized we'll look
it up and there will be no problem, okay?
So that is is letrec.
Here's an example where letrec is actually
needed, is actually properly used.
I'll let you puzzle through
this code on your own.
It's actually taking an argument and
returning true if it's,
sorry, if it's taken the number mod2.
So if it's an even number it returns 0,
if it's an odd number it returns 1.
It only works for non negative numbers and
it does it via these very silly
mutually recursive functions.
But my point is to use letrec, so
that even is bound to a Lambda
that in its body called odd.
And odd is bound to a Lambda in its body
called even, so forward reference and
backward reference.
I am using the Greek letter Lambda here,
just on the slide rather than
writing out the word Lambda.
It turns out you can do that in Dr.
Racket, but I prefer you write it out.
So that when you submit
your homework assignments,
we don't have unicode characters that
don't always print well everywhere.
But if you really want to use Lambda,
I suppose we will survive.
And here's another example
of not using later bindings,
because you get this undefined issue that
we talked about on the previous line.
So that's my discussion of letrec.
I told you there's one other
way to define local variables.
So in certain positions in your function
body, you can actually use define.
So for example right here,
I'm defining another version
of this silly mod function.
My function body is the everything but
the first line,
the function body is the second,
the third line and the fourth line.
You can actually in here write define,
and then have bindings.
And you can have any number of these and
those will be local
variables to your function.
And the semantics is the same as letrec.
Exactly everything I told you about
letrec is true for local defines as well.
It's just a different syntax as long
as we are using all the constructs
we will use in this course and
I prefer to use let*r and letrec.
It's the more traditional style.
It emphasizes the different semantics,
but I should be honest with you.
The biggest users and designers of
the Racket language now say that local
defines as the preferred style
that you should use let and
lets* when you want those semantics.
But if the semantics doesn't matter,
meaning the result would be the same for
all three.
Or if you actually need letrec, then
they'd prefer this local define syntax.
And so on your homework,
I will let you choose.
If you want to use local defines, you can.
But I find it easier to think about
the traditional expressions let,
let* and letrec, okay?
So that's our introduction to scope.
Remember not only do you need to know
the differences between these concerts,
to read Racket code and
to write Racket code in good style.
But it's wonderful that we have
a language that lets us think about three
different definitions for
how let expression should work.
Because each of them is more convenient
and most useful in different situations.