[MUSIC] So, now that we've discussed how
local bindings work and the semantics of
them, I just want to tell you the
semantics of top-level bindings that
defines in a file because it would be an
omission not to go through that.
So, the short version is, when you have a
bunch of bindings in a file, they work
like a letrec, or they work just like a
local define.
So, you can have things referred to later
by names.
So, like in ML, the things are evaluated
in order and you can refer to early
bindings. But unlike ML, you can also
refer to later bindings.
Now, because this evaluated an order
issue, you should only refer to later
bindings in function bodies, and you
should make sure that those functions do
not get called until after the thing
you're referring to has had its
expression evaluated.
Unlike insider functions where you get an
undefined result, you'll actually get an
error in racket, but that's a detail that
we don't need to focus on.
but, you might be thinking, oh, great,
finally I can refer to later things.
Everything is better.
Well, it turns out there's a couple of
disadvantages to this semantics.
One, as we've seen, is you can get these
errors if you refer to something too
early.
But the second is, you cannot shadow
inside of a file.
That wouldn't mean anything.
If you have two bindings of the same
variable in the same file, this doesn't
make any sense because we're trying to
add them to the same environment and
you'll get an error if you try to do
that.
So, quick example here.
this is just silly code.
In this first line, I define a function,
f.
And if you look in its body, it not just
uses its argument but it also uses some
variable b that is actually introduced
later in the file.
This is okay because the body of f is not
called until after we have the binding b
initialized to 3.
In fact, in this file, we don't call it
at all. But once someone uses this
module, uses this file or clicks Run, we
will be bound to 3 and any call to f will
work correctly.
Now, you can go ahead and use in earlier
binding, even not inside a function body.
This works just like in ML, or just like
with a letrec.
we evaluate things in order.
So, by the time we get to the +b4, b is
already 3,
so c would be evaluated to 7, there's no
trouble.
You cannot do this to a later thing.
So, this is what I've been emphasizing.
If I uncomment this line, then trying to
execute this line d will give an error, I
can just click run here.
It says reference to an identifier before
its definition,
that's exactly the mistake we made, okay?
so and then on this last line, define
f17.
This would also be an error because you
can't introduce two variables f in the
same file like this, you would get
duplicate definition for identifier in f,
okay?
So, that's the advantages and
disadvantages of this letrec-style
semantics for the top-level bindings, and
that's really what you need to know from
this segment.
Now, a couple other details, just to
finish up. One is the REPL doesn't quite
work like letrec.
It doesn't quite work like let star.
In fact, it doesn't quite work properly
at all.
And I'm not going to go into the details
of how the REPL works because in normal
uses, the REPL will do what you want,
just like we've been a REPL in ML, and
now in Racket. But, it turns out there's
some things that don't work well. If you
shadow something that's already been
defined even in the standard library, and
you're defining a recursive function,
things can go very wrong.
And so, the easy work around is in the
REPL, do not define your own recursive
functions.
It's fine to call recursive functions
that have been defined by a file that you
are running.
Don't define your own in the REPL, go
ahead and put them in a file and then we
can avoid this issue.
And then, one other optional thing is
later in the course, I'd like to at least
optionally study Racket's module system.
And I'm being technically incorrect here.
Inside of file and Racket is not really
top level bindings, which is what I
called the segment.
In Racket, every file is implicitly in
its own module.
Now, in that module still has letrec
style semantics, so all the code I showed
you is correct.
But it turns out that across files, it's
not one big letrec, it's actually a
separate letrec for each file.
And you can include things from another
file.
And you can shadow things from another
file from another module.
So, in fact, since plus is just a
function and it's just defined in some
other module that's part of the standard
library,
you could even shadow the plus function
inside your own file, but each file can
only define it once.
Of course, that sort of shadowing is, is
poor style, but it helps explain Racket's
module system.
Which as I mentioned, will be an optional
topic later in the course.