[MUSIC]
In this segment, I'm going to admit to
you that Racket actually has mutation.
In fact it has assignment statements,
because we need them for
some of the idioms we will be
studying later in this section.
But in this segment,
I'm going to show you how they work and
some of the problems they cause.
Because if you use mutation
in places you should not,
bad things happen to your software.
So Racket really does have
assignment statements and
we use them only where appropriate.
People generally programming a Racket,
do not use them a lot.
But when they need them the Racket
concert is called set!,
it's spelled S-E-T-!, and
everyone pronounces it set bang.
And the way it works is set bang takes
a variable that should already be
in the environment and an expression e.
It evaluates e to a result and it updates,
it actually mutates what x is bound to?
So anyone who's using that x in
their environment after this
set bang will see the updated value for
x, all right?
So any later look ups for
x by anyone who's using that x,
they'll see the later value.
If they already looked up x, well they
saw the value before we did the set bang.
And this really is like
the assignment statement and
languages you may have seen before Java,
C, Python and so forth.
The syntax is just set bang
with parentheses around it.
Now once you have side effects like this,
some times you want to do
a bunch of things in order.
I'm not going to use this in this segment,
but I should show you that Racket in
general has this form where you say begin.
And then some sequence of expressions,
and this is the sequencing operator.
You do each of these expressions in order,
and
your overall result is just
whatever the last one evaluates to.
So these earlier ones are useless,
except if they do set banging,
they do any updating or any printing or
anything with a side effect then we need
to execute those just for
their side effect.
So let me show you an example of using set
bang that's actually mutating a variable.
So imagine this is a file and
I want to sort of emphasize to you
why this sort of assignment
statement is probably a bad idea.
So let's go through this line by line.
On the first line, we create
the environment where b is bound to 3.
On the second line,
f is bound to a function.
But if this were ML, I would say f always,
always, always adds 3 to its argument.
Because given x, it does multiply by 1 and
the addition of x and b, all right?
So I made this big point
that ML thanks to closures,
this function will always
add 3 to it's argument.
Now, what I have to say is in fact,
we still have closures.
And this function will always,
when it looks that b at this b,
we still have lexical scope.
But when it looks up b,
it will get whatever the current
contents of the b are.
Because with set bang, we have to
start talking about current contents.
If you don't use set bang, you can
forget that, the initial contents or
the contents for all time, okay?
Line 3, when we look up b for
this expression, we use 3, so we get 7.
So in the environment, c is 7 period.
I have it here on the comment, c is 7.
At this point we set bang b to 5.
So hence forth b in this environment is 5.
So now when we call f with 4, when
the body of this function is executed,
it looks up b in the environment and
it sees 5.
So we end up with 5 + 4, that's
the + x b multiplied by 1, we get 9.
On this last line however, where we just
look up c and put the result in w, c is 7.
We already did this plus before
a long time ago, three lines ago.
And what's in our environment is c is 7.
Having done that addition, any subsequent
changes to be are not relevant.
So that is why z is bound to 9, because
the call to f saw the new value for b.
But w is bound to 7 because c
holds the result of adding b and
4, where we looked up b
before the set bang, okay?
So when you can set bang,
when you can assign to top level bindings,
a lot of things can start
going really wrong.
So suppose that we thought that function
f really was supposed to always add
3 to its argument.
How could we fix that?
Well no one programs this way in Racket.
Do not do this on your homework.
But I want to make a point about how if
you had to deal with the potential of set
bang correctly, you'd have to do
a lot of extra copying of bindings.
So a general principle in
software development is if you're
worried something might change,
make a copy of it before it can change.
And we can do that with
our example function f.
If we wanted f to always add x
to the value of b when f was
defined rather than the updated
value of b when f is called.
And what we can do is we
can make a local copy.
We can define f to be the result
of this let expression.
What this let expression does,
is it initializes some local b that the
outside world cannot get to in there for
cannot set bang to be whatever
the outer b currently is.
So we have that 3 and
now this function whenever called,
we'll look up the find us local b.
We already copied the outer one and
we're fine.
So you normally use the same variable
when you use this technique.
But if it confuses you this inner b does
not have to be the same as the outer b,
we could have said let c be b
when the x times 1 + x and c.
And that would've still made
an appropriate local copy that would make
sure that this closure is unaffected by
any later set bang of this top level b.
But it turns out that wouldn't
necessarily be good enough,
in a simple elegant languages
design you'd say wait a minute.
That function also uses addition and
multiplication and
those are just variables
bound to functions.
And if we have set bang, we have set bang.
What would stop someone from set
banging the plus variable to
be bound to some different thing
no longer the addition function?
So now for our function f to be safe,
we have to make a local copy of b and
a local copy of plus and
a local copy of times.
So that we know that this function body
down here when it looks up times and
plus and b will get the code we want
even if there's a later set bang.
Nobody programs like this,
don't worry about it.
But semantically this is what you
would think you would have to do.
And then older Racket like languages like
scheme, this would actually be a problem.
If someone did a set bang of plus,
all sorts of codes would start breaking,
because they all assumed it was
still the addition function.
So the designers of Racket decided,
this was just too much.
We don't want to have these sort of
problems creeping into our software.
So in Racket you cannot
set bang things like plus.
They made a strange compromise
that if the file that defines
something does not set bang it in that
file then nobody else can either.
And since the file where plus is bound to
the addition function does not have any
set bang for addition.
We don't have to worry about anyone
else assigning to it either.
Okay, let me be clear about this.
I did not want you on the homework
making local copies this.
It's a strange idiom, it's not necessary.
What everyone does in Racket is just
assume that no one is going to do set bang
of top level bindings.
So why did I show this to you?
Because I don't want you to use set bang
on top level bindings in any language.
Assigning to top level things
that lots of your code might be
relying on is just a bad idea.
And if you don't mutate things,
then you have much simpler semantics.
And it's actually quite dubious whether in
your language, you should even allow top
level bindings to be mutated,
and that's why we have set bang.
But Racket went ahead and
had some reasonable compromises
about what you're allowed to set bang and
what you're not.