[MUSIC]
In this segment, let's get right to
studying probably the most common use of
first class functions which is passing
one function as an argument to another
function.
So, I want to emphasize that there's
nothing really new here in terms of
language features, we just never thought
to do this before.
So, we could define a function binding in
ML, say, f that took as one of its
arguments another function g. And then
inside the, the body of f,
g would be a variable.
That when we look it up, we get a
function.
And so, we could call that function with
some arguments.
And so, we could use f in one place
calling it with h1.
And in another place, calling it with h2.
So, that makes f more useful, more
parameterizable because different callers
of f can pass in different functions.
This is going to be a very elegant
strategy for us.
We're going to be able to take common
pieces of code and abstract them out
which is one of the best things to do
when you're designing software.
And the way we can abstract them out is
instead of having n very similar
functions, we could have one function
that has all the common parts and then,
pass in n different shorter functions
that just describe in their bodies and
their computations the parts that are
different.
So really, the rest of this segment is
going to be over in Emacs showing you a
good example of this, a simple example of
this to give you a sense of how this
might work.
So, to start with, I already have written
here three ordinary non higher-order
functions.
Plain old first-order functions, we call
them.
but they all have quite a bit of
similarity, which we'll see.
So, they're a little silly, but bear with
me.
This first one just takes two arguments n
and x and increments x, n times.
So, if n is zero, it just returns x.
Otherwise, it returns one, plus the
result of incrementing x, n minus one
times.
Now, this really is quite silly.
This is an addition function.
It's just taking x and adding n to it,
but, but that's okay.
The second example is a bit less silly.
There's no built-in operator for it in
ML.
It takes a number n and another number x
and it doubles x, n times.
Put it another way, if you're a little
more familiar with your math, it's two to
the n times x, alright?
And the way it does it is it says if n is
zero, return x.
Otherwise, multiply by two the result of
doubling x, n minus one times.
The last example doesn't necessarily work
with numbers at all, it works with lists.
Takes a number n and a list x's and it
takes the nth tail.
So, for example, if you pass it three and
the list 4, 8, 12, 16, then you would get
back the list 16.
Because if you take tail of tail of tail
of that input list, you end up with the
list holding just 16,
okay?
How does it do it?
If n is zero, then just return the entire
list.
Otherwise, take tail of the nth tail of n
- 1 and x's.
Alright.
So, three simple functions we could have
already written ourselves.
But hopefully, it pains you to see so
much similarity between these functions.
All of them take two arguments.
If the first argument is zero, return the
second one.
Otherwise, do something to the recursive
call with x or x's and n minus one.
So, somehow we'd like to separate all
this out so we don't have to write all
that stuff three times.
And in general, these might be bigger and
more complicated.
and the only way we can do this without
first class functions which would be some
ugly kluge, where we had some flag.
Do I want to be increment or double or
nth tail?
And that's not extensible.
What if there's a fourth function that
comes along that is like this?
But first-class functions do this very,
very well.
So, what I'm going to do is write a
function n times.
That, in addition to taking n and x,
takes another argument, f.
And that f is going to capture the
differences between the three functions
above.
So, in every case,
I want to say, if n0, = 0, then just
return that second argument.
Otherwise, I definitely want to call n
times with the same function n - 1 and x.
And then, what I want to do to that
recursive result,
well, that depends.
And it depends on whether I want to do
doubling or incrementing or tailing.
but in all cases, we'll just have the
caller pass in an f that does what we
want.
So, that is our useful higher-order
function and now let's see how we can use
that to do incrementing and doubling and
tailing.
And so, let me first just define a couple
very simple and very short helper
functions like this.
There are various ways you can double
there's one, right?
And now, what I can do is use n times in
various ways. So, if I wanted to double
seven four times, then I would just do
that.
And if I, oops, sorry.
x1 equals, there we go.
if I wanted to increment seven four
times,
then how about I make the exact same
call, but I pass an increment instead.
And similarly, if I wanted to take the
tail,
so maybe two tails of a list like 4, 8,
12, 16, it'll work just like that.
And sure enough, if I come over here and
run it,
functions as arguments.sml.
You'll see that x1 is 112, x2 is eleven,
and x3 is 12,16.
So, we saved a lot of code reuse here.
We got a lot more code reuse.
All we did here was use n times,
increment double, which are very short
and then, use it in different ways.
Now, you might be thinking, well, that's
great.
But, you know,
callers, you know,
users of my code shouldn't have to go to
this extra work.
But, of course, they, they don't have to,
right?
If I want to write my own increment
function that takes n and x.
And how about I change its name, since we
know this is really just addition.
As long as n is greater than or equal to
zero,
none of these functions work for negative
n.
I can just define this like this,
right?
The function that takes n and x and
increments x n times can be implemented
by calling n times with increment n and
x.
And similarly, double n times could be
better written as this body.
[SOUND] And finally, nth tail,
n, x can be written as this.
And as always, callers of these functions
don't need to know and don't need to care
that we've implemented them using the
same common code, n times, under the
hood.
And then finally, suppose we did this, we
are very happy with ourselves,
we can now go up and really get rid of or
for the sake of simplicity, I'll just
comment out all this repetitive code.
So, all we have now is n times and these
three helper functions, and then maybe
sometime later, you'll realize that that
pattern,
that reusable code,
that higher-order function n times is
even more useful.
Maybe you come along and you realize that
oh, you need to triple some number n
times, n, x.
And you're like oh,
well, I'll just call n times with a
little helper function triple that I'll
write and n, x.
and, of course, I need to define triple
here.
And it'll be three times x, alright?
And this is all wonderful.
and let's go back and make sure we got
that all right.
And sure enough, what we now have are
functions additional, addition and double
n times, both of int star int arrow int.
We have nth tail of type int star alpha
list arrow alpha list and triple n times
of int star arrow int.
So, n times which fundamentally just
takes a function and an n and an x and
ends up returning f of f of f of f. N
times of those applied to x is a
generally reusable, beautiful high-order
function that we can reuse by passing in
different functions in that position for
f.
So, that seems like a great example. The
only thing that might be a little
confusing to you is this type of n times
which looks a little complicated in
polymorphic. And so, let's talk about
that a little bit more in the next
segment.