[MUSIC] In this segment, I want to show
how we can use our understanding of
lexical scope to avoid unnecessary
recomputation of things when we're using
closures.
So, here's what we know. We know a
function body is not evaluated until the
function is called.
That's not even relevant to lexical
scope, that's the way functions and
methods work in every language.
You don't evaluate the body until you
make the call.
We also know that the function body is
reevaluated, if you will, every time the
function is called using the arguments
for that call.
But we also know that a variable binding
evaluates expression,
its expression once when the binding is
evaluated,
not every time the variable is used.
These are three things we've definitely
seen, definitely used.
And if you take a minute to understand
exactly what's being written here, you
probably understand those three things as
well.
Now, I want to put those three things
together to point out that with closures,
we can use these things to avoid
repeating any computation that you would
naturally put in the function body, but
is not actually using any of the
function's arguments.
This can improve performance.
It can make your code a little longer.
It can make it more or less readable,
depending on your preference, but it's a
good example that helps emphasize the
semantics of how functions and function
closures work.
So, let me show you the example I'm going
to use to demonstrate this.
First, I just have our old friend, the
very famous higher-order function filter,
no change there.
And now, I'm going to use filter with
this function here, it takes in a list of
string xs and a string s and it returns
another string list.
So, this has type string list star string
arrow string list, okay?
and what it does is it filters out all
the strings that are longer than s, okay?
So, all we're going to do is call filter
with xs for the list and with this
perfectly reasonable anonymous function,
take in an x, that'll be an element of
the list and ask, is its size less than
the size of S?
If it's strictly shorter, then we'll have
it in our output and if not, we'll filter
it away,
alright? There's nothing wrong with this,
this will produce the right answer.
But it turns out that we are going to
recompute the size of s for every element
of the list xs.
Because filter is going to call this
function, one time for every element of
the list And and time we call it, we
compute the size of x, which we need to,
x is changing every time,
and the size of s.
But that's an unnecessary recomputation.
The size of s is not going to change.
The way to fix that is as we see in this
second example.
Let's just create a local variable that
holds the size of s,
call it i, alright?
And now in our anonymous function, just
ask,
is the size of x less than i?
This will produce exactly the same
answer.
There's nothing any caller can do to tell
whether we use the first version or the
second version, except to notice that if
our list is very long and/or if the
length of s is very long, we could see a
performance difference.
So, that's exactly what I wanted to show
you and notice we need closures here.
If we don't have lexical scope, if we
don't store with this closure, the
environment where the function was
defined, we're not going to be able to
use this variable i.
So, this is yet another example of where
closures and lexical scope are very
natural thing.
So, I wanted to show you this, that it
actually works but it's a little hard to
do because you can't see the difference
in all shorter than one and all shorter
than two.
So, for the purpose of showing you the
difference, how about we put in some
print statements so we can see where
things happen.
So, I haven't done this with you before
but there is a function Print in ML that
takes a string and prints it out.
There's also this semicolon operator.
when you use it as an expression in
general, let me put this in a comment
here, if you have e1;e2,e2, it does e1,
throws away the result then does e2 and
that's the result for the whole thing.
In functional programming, you don't need
this sequencing very often because what's
the point of performing a computation
that wouldn't have assignments of side
effects if you're just going to throw
away the result.
But printing is a good example where it
does have a side effect and that's what
we're actually trying to do here.
And similarly, let us put in a print
before this call.
So, my idea here is to print one
exclamation point before any time that we
call string.size of s.
So, in fact, let me change this up here.
I like it a little better if I put it
right here so you can see it really is
related to the size of the string s,
okay?
So now, I have my two functions.
And now, down here, I have some testing
code where I had the prints commented
out,
alright? So, what it's going to do, it's
going to, it's going to print with
allshorterthan1 and then it's going to
call allshorterthan1 on an length four
list with this string.
And then, allshorterthan2 on the same
list and the same argument, okay?
And if we just run this, say use
closures_and_recomputation,
it's going to end up doing those print
statements before the other stuff from
the RPL as soon as I fix my parentheses
here somewhere.
yes.
One too many there.
or [SOUND] let's see.
Try it that way.
Yup.
Good. And we see that with width
allshorterthan1, which was the version
that did not use the local variable, we
got four exclamation points for our
length four list.
But when we called allshorterthan2, we
only did this let binding a single time.
Once, when we computed the size of s and
even though we called this function four
times, we looked up i four times but
looking up i just returned, I think
three, the length of that list.
There's no recomputation when you look up
a variable.