[SOUND]
Now I want to show you another famous
higher order function that recursively
traverses over data structures and then
use that to show you more examples using
closures and emphasize what these sort of
iterative these higher order functions
are really all about.
So it's called fold, it's very similar,
possibly even a synonym to similarly well
known names like reduce or inject.
And the idea is to traverse a recursive
data structure like a list, in order to
produce a single answer.
Okay?
So the wave fold is going to work, we're
going to define a function fold, is we're
going to pass in a function f.
An initial value, which I'll call ac for
accumulator and a list.
And what we're going to do, as you can
kind of see here, is apply f to the
accumulator and the first element of the
list.
Take that result and pass it to f with
the second element in the list.
the third element in the list and so on.
So you can imagine, if you imagine your
list laid out from left to right, that
you really are folding over it.
You're going over it starting with the
accumulator, applying f to the
accumulator in the first element to get
another value.
Applying f to that value in the second
element, that value in the third element
and so on until you reach the end of the
list and that's your final result.
As co, as common a language with higher
order functions and convenient syntax
like ML, I can write that function in
about three lines.
take in f, then initial commuter and x's,
if the list is empty, then the
accumulator is itself the result we want.
Otherwise.
Compute f of accumulator in x and pass
that, twofold, with f and the rest of the
list.
Here, I'm shadowing, this x is here in my
pattern.
So this is folding left over the list.
If we write down our list elements, left
to right,
we can write a different version of fold
that would go from right to left.
that version couldn't be tail recursive
quite as well.
And the order doesn't matter, unless it
matters for f.
So that's why, in the standard library,
they actually do distinguish left from
right.
And the type of fold tells you a lot
about what it does.
If we type this into the read of l print
loop, what we would get is that the
function f can take any two types alpha
and beta.
Maybe they are the same, maybe they are
different but it has to return something
of type alpha because the older
accumulator and new accumulator have to
be values of same type.
That type alpha has to be the type of
acc, the accumulator.
The list has the ty, the elements of type
beta, that other argument we passed to f.
And then the result of the entire thing
has the same type as the type of our
accumulator, and that's alpha.
So you start with a beta list, and an
alpha, and an initial answer.
You use f to fold over the list,
producing a new answer at each position
in the list.
When you get to the end of the list, your
final answer is that last alpha.
So that is fold.
Let me talk about why we're so excited
about these things.
So these iterator like functions are not
built into the language.
There's just a programming pattern.
We just wrote it on the slide.
It's three lines of ML.
Now many languages provide built in
support for iterating over a data
structure and computing a result like,
like we would do with fold.
And there's nothing wrong with built in
support.
These things are so common.
Maybe that's a reasonable thing to do.
they also provide special features like
usually you could stop half way down the
list.
Whereas fold is all the way, going to
always go all the way down the list.
But when we have fold, we can just write
it in our language we have higher order
functions and it's really a concept.
We wrote fold here over lists.
If we had a different data structure like
an array or a tree or a graph or a set,
we could write fold over that as well.
And then, of course, we're going to use
fold with lots of different clients
passing in lots of different f.
So what I love about this is that it's a
separation of concerns.
One group of people can worry about
writing fold over some complicated data
structure, lists are not complicated but
there are much more complicated things
out there, and then someone else can
worry about how to compute over a
particular for a particular result.
And then, if you change and you start
using a different data structure other
than a list, you can reuse your function,
you just need a new fold.
And conversely once you've written fold
for list, lots of different people can
use fold for list for different
computations.
So it really separates two things out
simply by using a higher order function
and passing one function to another.
Okay.
Enough hypothesizing and theorizing.
Let's get to the code and show you a
bunch of example uses of fold since you
may still be getting the hang of how it
works.
I've purposely given all of these
functions non revealing names so you can
kind of play along.
So here is fold up here.
Right?
Remember it's going to apply f to the
accumulator in the first one on the list,
get a result, apply that to with that on
the second on the list and so on.
So what we do here in this first call is
we pass in some list x's.
Our initial accumulator is zero, and what
we do every time, the first argument to
this anonymous function is going to be
the next, is the accumulator, the current
accumulator, and the second thing is the
next element on the list.
You can see that right here in full.
So what we do here at each step is we
take what was the accumulator, and the
next element on the list, and we add them
together.
That will be our new accumulator.
Then we'll get to the next one on the
list, and we'll add that.
Get the next one on the list, and add
that.
So when I describe it that way, it seems
pretty clear that this is a one line
solution, give and fold, to summing the
elements on a list.
Let's do another one.
Here I also have a list, my initial
accumulator is true.
So at each step, I am going to produce a
boolean.
You can't change the type of your
accumulator, so the language with a
strong type system and here is my
anonymous function.
Remember x is going to be, what the
accumulator, fold is going to pass back
into our closure, whatever the next
accumulator is and y is the next element
on the list.
So what we do is we take our accumulator
and is y greater than or equal to zero.
So if y is, negative, we're going to get
false for this whole thing.
If x is false, we're going to get a false
for this whole thing, and x keeps
updating with each element of the list.
So what this ends up doing is, are all
list elements, positive?
Excuse me non negative, if you want to be
picky, alright.
Alright?
Okay.
So, both those examples do not use
private data.
Alright?
These closures we passed in, only use
their arguments.
Now, lets see the real power of closures,
which is that you can choose other
things.
So, here is a call to fold.
x's is my list, 0's my initial
accumulator.
x is always the current accumulator.
y is the next element of the list and I
am adding to it.
So I'm summing something here, but what
I'm adding here is if y is greater than
or equal to low and y is less than or
equal to high then one else is zero.
Okay?
So notice I am using private data here,
low and high, referred to these things
that are only in scope here where I
define the function.
But that's great.
Closures are powerful that way.
And then I compute either one or zero.
So what this is actually doing is
counting the number of elements between
low and high inclusive.
Me.
It's almost one line long.
It got a little long for me.
Okay, here's another one.
this is similar to something we did in
the previous segment, now I'm going to
take in list of strings and a string.
And I'm going to call fold, I'm going to
produce a boolean here, starting with the
list exis, and my closure here says x and
also something, so I'm doing the same
game as I was doing previously of
computing is something true of every
element of the list.
If you fold over in this way you're going
to do a for all if you will,
are all elements of the list such that
there size is strictly less than i, where
i is this variable I can bound up here
computing ones to avoid recombination,
the size of the string s.
So, what this ends up doing is computing
our all elements of the list, strings
whose size are strictly less than the
size of s.
Okay.
And I avoided recomputation like we saw
in the previous segment.
one more example here of some different
function, this one is more generic.
Okay.
So f5 takes in a function g and the list
x's.
And it passes x as the fold, initial
acumulator of true, but what it does is
it says x and also g of y, so now call is
of f5 will pass in a function that says
well this is how you decide if this
element to the list passes the test.
And it's f5's job to use full to see if
therefore do they all pass the test?
So this is really saying do all elements
of the list produce true when passed to
g?
And now, given that reusable function,
I could redefine f4 without using fold
directly.
I could just use f5 as my helper
function.
And all I have to do is call f5 with this
simple anonymous function, and the list
x's.
So this is just another way to use higher
order functions.
f5 is using closures here.
Notice this g is defined where the
function is defined.
Alright.
So that was several examples, and let me
just remind you why I'm showing you this,
which is that map filter and fold do
become much more powerful, thanks to
closures and lexical scope.
We can pass in any private data that are
function f means, just by using scope.
and the iterator folded itself doesn't
need to what data is there or even what
type it has.
So our first couple of examples, f1 and
f2 I believe didn't use private data and
that's fine.
f3, f4, and f5 did and that's fine too.
Fold works the same way.
It just calls f once for each element in
the list and f can use whatever is in
it's environment.
So, now we've seen map, filter and fold.
Probably the three most important higher
order functions there are.
Of course, there are many other useful
ones.
In fact, the f5 we just defined is itself
a very useful higher order function.
It's easier to use, simpler to use than
fold.
But we nonetheless defined it using fold.
And that's the end of our study of fold.
Now we can continue to study other
idioms, other important ways that we can
use closures.