[MUSIC] This is the first of several
segments, where we're going to take what
we already learned about function
closures, and discover additional and
powerful programming idiom's that, that
semantics's will let us use.
So we know the semantics.
We know lexical scope.
We know function closers.
And we've already done one of the key
idioms.
That is passing functions to iterators.
We're now going to do several more.
You see the list here.
And in this segment we're going to focus
on this combining functions.
This is going to be writing things like
function composition.
So without further ado, how about I just
go over to, Emax here and write function
composition for you.
So, what I want to do is write function
compose that's going to take in two other
functions f and g.
And return a function that, when you call
it, just calls, returns f(g,x).
And we can do that, alright? So, f(g,x).
And if you call compose with 2 functions,
and get a function back.
That function you get back is absolutely
using the semantics for closures.
So that when you call it, it can look up
f and g in the environment.
That was present back when we defined
this function.
Alright.
Function composition is a fundamental
idea in mathematics and in computer
science.
So, let's take a minute just to study it
a little bit.
I like to think of its type as something
that takes.
These two arguments, so a function from
alpha to beta, or a to b, if you will,
that's the g, and a function from b to c,
that's the f, and returns a function from
a to c.
And once you look at the type like that,
it's, almost painfully clear, what the
function does.
It, it pretty much has to call f of g on,
its argument a here, to eventually return
This argument of type C.
Now, just to warn you.
If you try this out in ML, you get the
REPL, which has no idea that a is the
first letter of the alphabet, and b the
second or anything.
returns this type here.
It's missing a couple parentheses and
it's used different type variables for
different parts of the type.
But I promise you that it's an
absolutely, equivalent type alright.
Now it turns out that functioning
composition is nice enough, that it's
been provided by ml and it's been
provided as an in-fix operator.
The same way plus, is a function that
takes two arguments, but we happen to
write it between that arguments.
In ml they took the lower case O, zero,
like the, O, like this.
Not zero.
O, and said that's the function
composition argument, so you can write f
composed with g, and that's exactly the
function we Right up here.
So let me show you an example of using
it.
I'll start with the old boring way that
doesn't use this.
Let's write a function, square root of
absolute value.
It's going to take an integer, it's
actually going to have type int arrow
real is ml's floating points.
And I'll I want to do Is take the
absolute value of I and then convert that
to a real number, because that is what
this other library functions, math.sqrt,
requires.
All right, so this will work absolutely
fine, but let's write a version that
instead uses function composition.
So here's a second version Where I can
better express, better indicate to the
person reading my code that what I really
am doing is composing three functions.
We could put more parenthesis in here but
the order won't actually matter, function
composition is associative.
And I'm just now taking the function
return from this higher order function
call.
And applying it to i, and now you might
notice that this has our standard pattern
of unnecessary function wrapping.
So we could express even more clearly and
directly what we're doing by saying that
the sqrt-of-abs is the variable, the
value you get by composing Map that
square root with Real.fromInt and the
absolute value function.
So that's using function composition.
We see that we need closures for this to
work out correctly.
What I thought I might do now is point
out that as nice as function composition
in that order is in math, we kind of have
to end up reading this right to left.
Take the absolute value, convert to a
real, then take the square root.
Which is a little bit backwards,
especially if you're reading your code in
English, where most programmers are used
to reading left to right.
So, in more recent years, a different
operator has become more popular.
This is used a lot in f sharp, which is a
dialect of ml, and functional programmers
just like to use this a bit as well, And,
I've defined it here on the slide, but
I'll think I'll just go back to the code
and redefine it for you here.
Now on the slide, and in f sharp, this
operator is usually written with the pipe
character, and then the angle bracket.
I discovered that in the current version,
of sml mode for emacs that I'm using,
using that Pipe character, snarls it up,
and makes it think I'm using a different
language feature.
So instead, I'm just going to use
exclamation point, angle bracket.
But in either case, we can, make up our
own infix operator.
The same way plus, is something that
takes it's argument on either side, I'm
going to use this keyword that's kind of
fancy and special to ml, it says I want
my own, infix operator, that I want to be
written That way, and once I've done
this, which tells it, this is always
going to be written between the 2
arguments, I can now define it as a
function.
Now, this is And then a function, f, and
then calls f with x.
This is really not very interesting
semantically, it's just taking a function
and argument, and calling the function
with the argument, but by putting the
argument on the left, it lets us write
our square root of abs in a way that many
programmers find quite easy to read and
pleasant, and it's nothing more than a
program idiom.
Just say alright, use our new operator
with i and abs, and that will return abs
of i.
And then that result can go to
Real.frontInt, so that will get me the
real number that is the absolute value of
i.
And then, Math.sqrt.
And we call this a pipeline, because it
almost looks like we're setting up a pipe
where we start with our.
Number i passing through a sequence of
functions combining all that to get the
answer we want.
So, that's kind of neat.
That's the pipeline operator.
A lot of people like it.
It's not doing anything fancy.
It's just programming, once we've defined
it with a very simple high order
function.
So, I've showed you function composition
in pipelines.
There are certainly more interesting
things you can do, with combining
functions.
So those are probably the most common.
But let's, let's do some others that we
just think might be useful.
So I'm going to define a couple functions
here I'm going to call backup functions.
So suppose you took in a function f and
g, and what you wanted to do is run f,
but if f wasn't the right thing, then
return the result of g.
So we're combining functions.
I want to return a new function that
takes x.
And what it does, is it turns out f of x,
the way this is written returns an
option.
And if that option is none, then I want
to call g of x.
Otherwise, if it's sum, let me reformat
things here for you.
Sum of, sum argument y, then just return
that y.
M'kay.
So that kind of makes sense, kind of as a
back up.
let me show you what that looks like in
terms of its type.
Because that will be nice and revealing
of what's going on.
And sure enough, if you look up backup
one, it says f has to be an alpha arrow
beta option.You can pass it any type you
want.
But the think back has to be an option.
Because we pattern match on it with none
in some.
The second argument had,
g has to take the same thing that F does
because we might call g with the same
acts we called F with.
The result type has to not have the
option on it because that's the result of
our entire function just like in the
other branch of the case expression, we
return to beta.
So in general, if you pass an F, as in
alpha, arrow, beta option and g as in
alpha, arrow, beta You will get back, the
parentheses just aren't printed here, an
alpha arrow beta.
So, it's like function composition,
except we don't compose them.
We either return the result of f with the
option stripped off, or we return the
result of g.
you might prefer a version that worked
with exceptions instead, so let me just
show you that.
I won't, try it out or anything.
So this, f and g will both just be alpha
arrow betas.
But if f, when called with x raises any
exception using a little pattern matching
here in my handle expression.
Then call g of x instead.
Alright? And if I show you the type of
that one, we'll see that f no longer, has
the return.
Option.
So those are a few examples of combining
functions.
That's our next closure idiom after
passing data to iterators, functions to
iterators with private data, and we'll
move on to our next idiom in the next
segment.