[MUSIC] There are just a couple more
topics I want to cover with currying, and
the first is that sometimes the function
you want to call isn't organized the way
you might wish it were.
Maybe you want to curry function and it's
a tupled function, or you want a tupled
function and it's a curried function.
Or maybe you want to use partial
application but not with the first few
arguments.
Maybe with the later arguments and you
can't do that.
Given a curried function, you have to
pass the first argument to it.
But what we could do is use our idea of
combining functions to, once and for all,
write very generic, very reusable
functions like we did with function
composition, that let us change one kind
of function into another.
So let me motivate that with a short
example.
We've seen this example before where I
wanted to take this function range, which
takes two numbers, i and j and returns a
list with all the numbers from i up to j,
use that to create a helper function
countup that just goes from one to the
number and then use that A countup
function.
So this code as written, will not work.
And that's because this version of range,
is tupled. It takes a pair.
And here I tried to use partial
application.
Now of course, I could work around this,
or I could change range, but there's a
very general thing I could do, which is
to take a, write a function that takes a
function expecting a pair and return the
same function in curried form.
So it's basically takes a function and
curries it.
So what if I did this, I can take this
function f and then I would return a
function that takes 2 arguments in
curried form.
And then calls f with the pair because f
expects a pair but curry of f will return
a two argument curried function.
And now, down here, for count up, I could
just, and still call, instead call, curry
of range.
And this, will now work.
So that's pretty neat, let me clean it up
a little bit more, just by using the
syntactic sugar we've seen before.
I could of just written it like this.
That's curry and at the call site, these
parenthesis, are optional.
We can go the other diretion as well.
If we add a curry'ed function but we
wanted to pass it a tuple and that could
actually be useful, if you are composing
functions, or chaining them together.
We could take 2. We, we we could take f,
and x,y and return a function, that would
look like this.
So now when you call uncurry, with some
functions foo you would get back a
function that expected a pair and then
called f with 2 arguments in curried
form, so that's pretty neat.
let me quickly show you the types of
curry and uncurry.
They're very generic and I will leave you
to puzzle over them, but I want to point
out one very neat thing.
There is a very deep connection to logic
here, you're not responsible for this,
but if you have studied logic Read these
as logical formulas where the star is
and, and the arrow is implies.
And you'll see that these are actually
true logical formulas and that hints that
there's actually a very deep connection,
a very mathematical connection between
tuppling and currying.
And I'm going to leave that as a
mysterious statement for you.
one other thing I wanted to show you that
also has these logical formulas.
Once you look at their type, is switching
the arguments of curried functions.
So if you had a 2 argument curried
function and you wanted to partially
apply it to the first argument, or to the
first argument instead of the first, you
couldn't do that unless you took that
function and passed it to this function
first instead.
So, f takes two curried arguments, but
other curried of f will just take the
arguments in the opposite order.
It takes an x and a y and then it calls f
with y and x and we've seen before
there's syntactic sugar for this. We
could just write it, that way.
Okay, so just more fun playing around
with combining functions.
Hopefully I've shown you that this thing
is at least a little bit useful.
And functional programmers do often
program with these things, in order to
get things elegant, and pretty, and
arranged just how they want.
So, that was one topic I wanted to
discuss.
The other, is people often want to know,
isn't currying really slow? If I want to
create all these closures to call a
function.
And it turns out, that it depends, and
that's up to the language implementation.
And language implementations can actually
make curried functions very efficient.
So in general, both calling a function
with a tupple, and calling a function via
currying with multiple arguments.
These are plenty fast.
These are constant time operations.
You should program in a way, that, makes
your code elegant, short, concise, and
correct.
Alright.
Well then maybe you might want to know
which is, is faster.
This is not part of the language
definition.
It will depend on the language
implementation.
And it turns out that the implementation
of SML that we are using, the SML New
Jersey compiler, does faster with tupling
than with currying.
So kind were in fact were be a bit slower
for the function calling times and times
and times of time for performance
critical application where it actually
matters, I should point out this is
actually not necessarily the case, in
fact most of their functional programming
language implementations out there today
OCaml Fsharp Haskell to better with
currying, than with.
Coupling.
Now, the optimizer might do very well
with both of them.
But in those other languages, we tell
performance conscious programmers, use
currying.
It'll work just fine.
If you use partial application, which is
something up to callers.
That might be a little bit slower.
But in languages where currying is always
the norm, we tell programmers even when
they're learning to program, oh it's just
the 3-argument function.
And the same way I lied to you at first
and told you that tuple's version was a
3-argument function and then went back
and told you the truth.
That's what these other languages do with
currying.
Currying is the default.
Almost everything is curried and you only
tuple things in those situations where