[MUSIC] In this optional segment I'm
going to show you one more closure idiom,
that's significantly more advanced,
combines a number of the fancier features
we've seen, but no new language
constructs and we're going to do
something pretty neat.
So, what we're going to do is implement
an abstract data type that's going to
feel a lot like an object in an object
oriented record.
What we're going to do is implement,
actually, a set of integers, just to keep
the example simple.
But what we're going to do is have a
record of functions.
So, a set is going to be represented by
that record.
The only thing in the fields of the
records are functions.
So the only thing clients of our
abstraction are going to be able to do is
caller functions.
But because those functions are closures,
they're going to have access to private
data.
And in fact, we're going to set this
whole thing up so that all the functions
in the record have access to the same
private data.
And that's how they're going to be able
to work together to implement an
abstraction with multiple operations,
like inserting into a set and finding out
if something is in a set.
Now, we could have made that private data
mutable or immutable.
It actually would have been a little
simpler if we had made it mutable.
But I want to encourage more
function-able programming style.
So were not going to do it in a mutable
way, we'll do it immutable.
And, in fact, so if you insert anything
into a set of integers, that doesn't
change the set you did insert on, it
returns a new set that has another
element in it, if that element was not
already in the set.
So the goal here is to make it feel a bit
like object oriented programming.
This will be the first time in the course
that I give you a hint that OOP and
functional programming actually have deep
similarities, but even if you're not
familiar with OOP, it's just a closure
example.
I admit this is advanced and clever, but
it's a good way to put together a lot of
stuff we've seen.
Lexical scope, data types, record and
closures, and even those the
implementation of the abstraction is bit
sophisticated, using it from the client
side, once I show you how to do it, isn't
going to be so tough.
So, we'll do the rest of the segment in
the code where I'll just show you what
we've got.
So I'm going to start with a type
definition.
Now, I'm going to put this back to how it
is in just a second.
But this is the type I would like to
implement.
I would like to say that a set, just to
find a nice type synonym here, is this
record type.
So remember records are just things with
fields.
You write colon, and you write the type
of the field.
And there's no reason why fields can't
hold functions, or things of function
type.
So the insert field would hold a closure
of type int arrow set it may enter to
give you back a new possibly different
set that contains that int.
Member of type int arrow bool for is the
int unit set and how about size which
takes no argument and tells you it how
many element are in the set.
Now, unfortunately this won't quite work
because in ML type synonyms can't be
recursive.
So this use of set is not going to work.
So that's why I'm doing this ML-specific
thing of let's make it a datatype
binding.
Of course, datatypes need constructors
and of, so this is actually a reasonable
use of a A data type binding that only
has one constructor.
I'm only using data type for the purpose
of being able to mention set in the
definition of set.
The same way we mentioned list in the
definition of list.
Okay.
So now I'm going to have this type,
this s constructor is going to be a bit
of a pain.
But we'll be able to use pattern matching
to get rid of it when we need to, and so
on.
So, the next easiest thing to show you is
to keep this type in mind.
In fact, why don't I make a copy of it so
we'll be able to see it.
I need to put this in a comment, and
bring it down with me to show you a
client.
Okay.
So I'm going to copy this down here is an
example client.
Just little function use sets of type I
think unit arrow int.
So we don't know how this set is
implemented but we do know its type.
We know it has, it's a record with
fields, insert member and size, each of
which are functions.
So, lets just start with the empty set.
Oh, I should have emphasized that, the
only public value that's going to be
available to us, is empty set of type
set.
And I'll show you how we implement that
later.
and so we are going to have to build our
set starting from the empty set.
So, I have this empty set value, and I'm
going to be able to say, let val
essentially s1=empty_set.
I'm putting a constructor here to pattern
match away the constructor Don't worry
about that.
I don't want to focus on that, but you do
need this because otherwise this s1 would
not be a record of functions.
It would be s and then we'd have to
pattern match later.
So s1 is now this record of functions.
So what I can do is take s1, read out the
insert field, that will get me back an
int arrow set function.
So I could call it with 34 and I get back
a set.
I can then strip of the s constrictor of
that and have a new record of 3
functions.
So I really like this because you might
be in other languages more used to
writing something like insert 34 but you
know, your way my way, it's just
rearranging the same ideas.
You can't really argue one is more
complicated than the other.
So I could then take that s2, insert
again.
the same number, 34.
So, it would not actually add it, because
that's not how sets work.
So, sets don't have duplicates, so that
would produce s3.
And then s3, I could insert again and
have 19.
And so, this would logically be the set
holding 19 and 34.
but rec, represented in s4, is just a
record holding 3 functions.
So then, down here, I could use the
member function.
I could take s4 and I say, if 42 is a
member of that set, then 99.
it's not else if member s4 19.
19 is a nautset.
I could say 17 plus the size of s3, and I
believe therefore, this whole thing will
valuate to 19.
It's a silly client, but it shows that
once I'm given this abstraction, using
it, as a set, is pretty much like we
would want to program with sets.
We just use the functions that are
provided to us.
Okay.
so that was actually easy part.
That's what clients would do.
We always want the client to be easier
than the library, because we only what to
implement the library once.
So now let me show you that fanciness.
All we have to do is implement empty set.
But we've to do that in a way that's
actually correct, that when we call
insert, we will get back something that
you know, will then act as an appropriate
set.
That is not empty.
So there's a lot of ways to do this.
I think this is a short and elegant way,
though I don't claim it's particularly
easy to understand.
So I'm defining a vowel empty set.
Alright, what I'm going to do is I've
this little helper function that I'm
going to use.
And what this helper function does is it
takes a list of elements It assumes that
list does not have duplicates, but it's a
local helper function so that's a
reasonable assumption.
And then, what we just return for empty
set is make_set of the empty list.
All right? So now, all we have to do is
understand make_set And we're done.
So let's understand mixed set.
It has this little helper function that
we'll explain in a minute.
But fundamentally what it returns is this
record wrapped in the s-constructor.
So all we have to do is return a record,
where insert does the right thing for a
set contains the numbers and xs, member
does the right thing, and size does the
right thing.
So, let's work bottom up, which is from
easier to more difficult.
So, remember, we know that xs has no
duplicates in it.
That's an invariant we're going to make,
maintain here and so all we have to do is
just take the length of that list.
So size is a record field that contains
this anonymous function of type unit
arrow int which is exactly what we need
for the size field and it does the right
thing.
Notice we're using private data here.
We're returning a record that is using xs
which is in scope right here, alright?
For member, well we just need to go down
this list and see if there's anything in
the list that equals the number we're
looking for.
So I actually, for reasons we'll see in a
minute, I have put this in a helper
function here contains.
So contains take a, takes a number i and
returns true if i is in xs.
So again I can use private data here I
can use xs, I can use a nice library
function List.exists, which works just
like the exists function I wrote for you
a few segments ago.
It's curried, I pass in this predicate
function that says for each element in
the list j,
does i equal j, and then, this is a
perfectly good function of type int arrow
bool.
So, that's exactly the function that I
want to put in the member field of the
record I am returning.
Okay, now all we have to do is insert.
The tricky thing about insert, is that it
is going to use make set, recursively.
And that does make sense.
Since, when you insert an element into a
set, you make a new set.
Alright? So insert has the type, have
type int arrow set.
So here's an anonymous function that does
what we need.
Takes in that integer i.
If i is contained in xs.
So there's my second use of my helper
function contains, which is why I made a
helper function.
For it.
Well, if I already have it, then I want
to return the same set I already have,
but there's no harm in making a new set,
and the easiest way here, is just call
make set with the same list xs.
Alright, and that will work fine.
Otherwise, make_set with i;;xs.
And that's it.
You can look at this, you can stare at
this, and see that the three functions I
put in here Do exactly the right thing in
the case that xs are the elements we want
in our set.
The trickiness is that make_set is
recursive and that we provide the
empty_set where we make_set of the empty
list and the recursion of make_set takes
care of the rest.
So I have this all compiled over here,
you'll see that we defined our type
definition for sets.
empty_set is just something of type set.
It is a record of 3 functions wrapped
with this s constructor, and then our
example client is something that just
read out the fields of the record and
used them in various ways, and if I call
it, I actually get back 18.
Earlier, I said it was 19.
I must have been misreading the code.
I'm sure the compiler is right, so let's
flip back here to the file.
And look down here at the client and sure
enough 17 plus the size of s3, I think I
thought we were taking the side of S4 you
see here that s3 is this one that only
has one element in it, 34, because we
don't put duplicate in there and so 17 +
1 is 18.
Alright? So that's our implementation,
our client, and our testing code.
And we really have implemented an
abstraction using nothing except data
types, recursion, closures, and records.