[SOUND]
In this segment, I want to talk about the
type of the n * function we wrote in the
previous segment.
And more generally, talk about the types
of these higher order functions that are
taking other functions as arguments.
So, often, the higher order functions we
write end up being polymorphic.
They end up having those type variables.
A quote a, which I pronounce alpha.
And often, also, a quote b or a quote c,
or even a quote d.
Where multiple type variables in the
type.
So that can make them seem a little more
sophisticated or inscrutable, but it's
actually really helpful.
It shows that these functions are so
reusable that they can often take
function, arguments, of various types,
the same way we saw n times work over
numbers when we were doubling, and we saw
it work over lists when we were taking
the [INAUDIBLE].
But the notion of polymorphic types, and
the notion of functions taking other
functions as arguments are actually
separate issues.
There are high-order functions that are
not polymorphic; I'll show you an
example.
And there are non-higher-order functions,
first-order functions, we call them, that
are polymorphic.
And I'll show you an example you've
actually seen before, so I'm really just
reminding you of this.
In general I think it's worth focusing on
this because it's always a good idea,
when you write down a function, to
understand it's type.
What sort of arguments does it work for?
And that's especially true for
higher-order functions because the
functions themselves, and their types,
are more interesting and complex.
So now let's look at this N times
function.
The type it actually has is here on the
slide, it's alpha arrow alpha for the
first argument, ent for the second
argument, alpha for the third argument,
alpha for the result.
So it works for any type alpha provided
that first argument takes and returns
alphas, second is an ent, and third is an
alpha.
Result is also an alpha.
Now to understand N times it's often
helpful to simplify it first.
We could have, given N times a more
restrictive type, we wouldn't have been
able to use it as generally but we could
have given it a type where all those
alphas are replaced by N's.
And this simpler type say if F is a
function that takes and ent and returns
an ent.
N is an ent and X is an ent then it
returns an ent.
And if you look at the code up here, that
makes sense.
Whatever the type of X is, has to be the
return type of the entire function.
Because we sometimes return X.
So if one of those is INT, the other has
to be INT.
And then, the return type of this
recursive call N times, has to be an
argument to F.
And the result type of f has to be the
result type of m times.
Because the result of this called f is
what's returned.
So it turns out that the argument to f
has to be the result type of f.
And that has to be the type of x.
And that has to be the return type of the
function.
But we don't actually care, as the writer
of n times, what that type is.
And that's exactly what this polymorphic
type with the alphas in certain
positions, is saying.
It's saying, all of these alphas have to
be replaced by the same type.
But it works for any type.
So, type inference figured this out for
us, but once we have this and we can see
it from the [INAUDIBLE] print loop as
we'll see here it's extremely useful to
look at this, understand this, and say I
see.
F has to be a function with the same
argument and return type.
That has to be the type of x and that's
also has to be the same return type.
The same function.
So, if we look at how we used end times,
we actually did instantiate the type
alpha, or quote a, differently for
different uses.
In this call here with double four and
seven, we let alpha be INT in every
position.
Double, right here is a function from INT
to INT, four is an INT, that has to be an
INT here, seven is and INT, that's this
third argument.
And indeed the result type is INT.
For increment it was the same.
We also instantiated alpha with int.
But for nth tail, we actually
instantiated with int list.
We can see that most easily with this
argument here, the third argument.
That alpha before the arrow, is clearly
an int list.
Entail as it self polymorphic it coumored
for any type of list and returns a the
same type of list so it is correct as a
function from it list to int list which
is the correct type for the first
argument here.
And the overall result ends up being an
int list.
So that's just polymorphic functions,
it's not really anything new.
It just sometimes looks a little bit more
mysterious once you start seeing these
function arguments.
but it makes our code a lot more
reusable.
If we didn't have polymorphism here, we
would have to write one version of n *
for integer arguments.
And another version of n * for int list
arguments.
And that would make the whole idea of
reusable code and first class functions a
lot less persuasive.
Okay,
so that is end times.
That is the reason why we saw the type we
saw from the read eval print loop.
Now let me try and convince you that
there are.
Higher order functions that are not
polymorphic and polymorphic functions
that are not higher order.
So I've an example of each here.
the first is this function called times
until zero.
Let me tell you what it does.
It takes in a function F in an argument X
and it counts how many times you need to
do [SOUND] F, of F, of F, of F, of X
until you get zero,
okay?
So what's the first time, the first
number of S, at which the result is zero?
So I've implemented that right here.
If x is already zero, then we need zero
f's.
Otherwise, we need one+ the number of
times to get to zero from f of x.
So we're going to now start with f of x
for our recursive call, using the same
function F.
And since that's one extra step of F,
that adds one to the result.
Okay, and so that is a nice function and
it turns out that its type is, let's see
F has to be an ent error ent and X has to
be an ent and then the result is an ent
and why is that?
Well X has to be an ent because we
compare it to zero, okay?
F has the taken end.
Because right here, we call it with X.
X has to be an end, we call F with X.
F has the taken end.
And therefore x has to return an int,
because it's past as the second argument
to times until zero.
So it turns out that this higher order
function that is convenient and reusable.
You can imagine using it in many
situations for seeing if some function
converges or something only works with
integers.
It just doesn't make sense otherwise, you
can't say how many times do you have to
convert a string into a different string
until you get zero.
That doesn't make sense.
Strings will never be zero.
You cannot compare them with zero.
So, not a polymorphic function but
nonetheless, a useful high order
function.
Conversely, here's a function we've seen
many times.
It computes the length of a list.
and its type is, it will take a list of
any type and return an integer.
Doesn't care what the type of the
elements are.
It never looks at them.
In fact, we could replace this pattern
here with a wild card that would arguably
be better style.
So, it has a polymorphic type.
But there's nothing, there's no first
class function in sight.
It just takes a list and returns an
integer,
okay?
so that is our contrast.
Hopefully, now we understand the type of
end times better, and we understand the
relation between polymorphic types and
functions as arguments.