[MUSIC] This segment and the next couple,
which are all optional fit together and
are about taking some of our closure
idioms and porting them to languages that
don't actually have closures.
So the idea here is that closures and
higher-order programming Programming with
functions like map and filter is great.
And it's particularly easy when your
language supports closures.
Because you can very easily create things
with private data, pass them around.
Function types are exactly what we want.
But if your language doesn't have
closures you can still program in this
style.
Now it's often much more painful.
You often have to create what
conceptually is your closure environment
manually.
But by showing you how to do this in
languages you might be familiar with we
can see some of the connections between
different programming styles.
So one segment is going to do this in an
object oriented style using java, and the
key idea there is to have interfaces,
that just have one method, so that's kind
of like the function code, the call me.
Part of an interface of, of a closure.
And then in C, where we have function
pointers but we don't have closures, we
can pass the environment explicitly as an
extra argument.
So these are optional segments because
you need to be a bit of an expert in Java
to understand the Java one.
And I bit of an expert in C to understand
the C one.
Even if you do know some Java or C, you
may find this a bit over your head,
that's okay.
I want to put these segments up, so you
can refer back to them someday.
If you're in these languages, and you
find yourself wanting to program in a
functional style, then these segments
might help you, point you in the right
direction.
So it shows some connections between the
languages and the features It can help
you understand what closures and objects
are really all about, and at the end of
the day it is a bit clumsy so it may make
you just wish that more programming
languages actually had closures, so that
we didn't have to simulate them and
incode the same idioms.
In more painful ways.
So this segment just shows the ML code
that we're then going to translate, which
is often called porting, to Java or C.
It's just a little list library.
I'm not going to use ML's built in lists
because I want to show all the code,
right? And I want to find a fuller
comparison because we're going to write
everything ourselves in all three
languages.
And then the next segments are
independent.
You can watch one or the other or both or
neither And then show how to write the
same code in those other languages.
So here we are.
I'm just going to define my own
polymorphic data constructor.
Alpha my list, two constructors.
Cons which has two parts, the head of the
list, which is an alpha.
And the tail of the list, which is an
alpha my list.
Or empty for the empty list.
These are just plain old constructors.
So I can write a function map.
I'm using a curried style here, but
that's not essential.
That takes in a function and one of these
my lists, so not ML's built in lists but
one of these my lists.
If it's empty we return empty.
If it's not empty then we cons on F
applied to X and mapping F across Xs.
That is mapped over the my list type.
Filter is similar, it's just the
appropriate if then L.
I just want to expand this out here so
you can see it.
Indent it a little more nicely.
Empty list is empty list, if f of x, then
Cons x onto filtering f across x's,
otherwise ignore x and just filter f
across x's.
And finally, length, which is easier than
any of them.
Empty list returns zero, non empty list
Returns one plus the length of the rest
of the list.
Then a couple clients that are using
these functions to define their own more
specific functions.
How about something that takes a My List
of integers and doubles all the elements.
Then we would just use the map function
that's no longer quite on the screen, but
is above.
Remember two curried arguments So I'm
doing a partial application here.
I'm just calling it with, an anonymous
function that takes a number, and
multiplies it by 2.
And then, how about another function that
just takes a, a list.
A my list, of course.
And, in N.
and returns how many.
elements of the list are n, okay? And so,
one way I could do this in terms of the
functions I've written, it's not the most
efficient way to compute this but it does
work, is to first filter the list.
They so that we only have the elements
that are n.
And then compute its length.
Alright? So the result of this called a
filter will be a list that has nothing in
it but a bunch of the number n.
Then however long that number, that list
is, is the number of n's that were in the
original list.
So we're going to write that code in this
style, in Java, and C in the upcoming
segments.