[SOUND].
Now that we've learned anonymous
functions, I want to show you one
programming pattern that's actually poor
style.
It's actually an over use of anonymous
functions where you don't need them,
and that's something that I like to call
unnecessary function wrapping.
Although, I'm pretty sure I made up that
particular term for it, but not the idea.
So, let's go over here,
use our same higher order function we've
been playing around with for a long time,
n times, and try to write one of the
things it's really useful for, which is
taking the Nth tail of some list.
So I'm going to have N and Xs, which is
going to be my list, and I want to N
times take the tail of the list, so my
second and third argument to N times are
clearly going to be N and Xs.
But for the first argument, we realize,
well, we just need a function right here
that takes the tail of its argument, and
we just learned anonymous functions, so
let's use them.
Right?
Let's say, fun Y, tail of Y.
And this will work and it's correct and
we feel good about using anonymous
functions, and I'm going to argue this as
actually just a very minor bit right
there of, of inferior style.
And here's why.
Let's look at this function we wrote and
let's describe what it does.
This is a function that takes one
argument and returns the list tail of
that argument.
Is there a simpler expression, a more
straightforward way of writing down here
an expression that is a function that
takes the tail of its argument?
Yes, there is, and that is to just write
tail.
Right?
Tail is a variable that, when we look it
up in the environment, we get a function
that does exactly the right thing.
The other version is wrapping that
perfectly good function that does exactly
what we want with another function that's
going to do the same thing.
It's just longer.
It's a tiny bit slower, since one
function has to call another one, and it
obscures the fact that what we want to
pass to N times is a perfectly good
function for taking the tail.
So that's unnecessary function wrapping.
To kind of explain in general what's
going on, let me try an analogy for you.
'Kay.
We've emphasized previously, and you may
have seen in previous programming
courses, that you shouldn't write things
like if X then true, else false.
This is an expression that returns true
if X is true and false if X is false, but
another thing that does that is just X.
Right?
We don't need the if then else X is
already the expression that we want. And
similarly, if you have a function like
take NX and return the result of calling
F with X,
the expression, F, will do just as well.
So that's the most common situation,
where you'll see this unnecessary
function wrapping is when we have an
anonymous function that has this form,
that all it does is pass its argument to
another function, then we should just use
that function, like tail in our example,
in place of it.
That's really the idea.
Let me show you one other related thing.
somewhat similar, also unnecessary
function wrapping, but comes up a little
less often and is a little less obvious,
that's what's going on.
let me, for example, you probably don't
know this, in the standard library for
ML, ML, there's a function list.rev that
reverses a list.
So suppose you were going to use this a
lot, or you had trouble remembering, that
it was list dot, and in some file, you
just wanted, your own function, rev, that
did the same thing, but, of course, you
don't want to re-implement reverse,
there's a perfectly good library
function.
So you would write it like this.
So this is also unnecessary function
wrapping.
I have a function reverse that takes in
one argument, x's, and returns, it's body
is calling list.rev rev with x's.
If we use the sort of de-sugared version
of this, that might be more obvious,
since our function, rev, is not
recursive.
We could have written it like this.
And now we see indeed this anonymous
function here has exactly the pattern
that is this unnecessary function
wrapping,
and indeed, a, a superior style solution
would be to just write val rev equals
list.rev.
Right.
This may look a little strange to you,
but it's a great use of first class
functions.
I'm defining a variable rev, and what I
will bind it to is the result of
evaluating this expression list.rev.
So I look up list.rev in my environment,
I get a function back, and so rev will
now be bound to the same function as
list.rev.
So whenever you want a shorter or
simpler, easy to remember name for a
function that's defined somewhere else, I
really prefer this third version to the
first version because again it's a little
simpler, it's more direct to what it is
you're doing and it's actually even a
little bit faster because you're not
making an unnecessary function call.