[SOUND] We've now seen a number of
examples of first class functions,
including my favorites, map and filter.
But all of our examples so far have been
similar enough that I want to emphasize
now just how general first class
functions are.
So, so far our examples, N times, map,
filter and probably a couple others, have
all just had one function that took one
other function as an argument and then
recursively processed numbers and lists.
So I just want to remind you that we can
use functions wherever we can use any
kind of expression.
This is actually a useful thing to do.
So a couple things I won't show you
examples of in this segment are passing
multiple functions as arguments to a
function.
The same way we passing one function that
I've been calling F.
To abstract over some sort of
computation.
If you had two different computations you
wanted to abstract over. It would make
perfect sense to pass in, have callers
pass two different functions.
So that's the first thing we can do with
the first class functions we haven't seen
so far.
Another one is we can put functions in
data structures in tuples or lists or
records.
And I'll show you an idiom that uses that
later in this section of the course,
but we're not going to do it quite now,
because we want to have some other
features and study some other things
first.
But two things I am going to do in this
segment are have functions return other
functions as results,
just a silly example to show you how that
works.
And then, we're going to write a high
order function over a data structure that
is not a list, that's actually one of our
own data type findings.
All right.
So let's do the returning functions
first, and how about I just show you the
code to start with.
So here is a function that actually takes
a function and also returns a function.
So it takes in an argument, F, and it
calls F with seven, that's how I know
it's an argument.
So in fact, for this part to type check,
I can tell you that this function overall
has to take in an int arrow bool, that,
that needs to be the type of F.
All right.
But then, if you look at the then branch
and the else branch, in each case, it
returns a function.
It turns out an anonymous function.
Although you could have any expression
there that evaluated to a function, and
in both cases, since we know then and
else always have to have the same type,
we have functions of the same type, and
in fact, this function always returns an
int arrow int.
So the function binding for double or
triple defines a function that takes in
an int arrow bool and returns an int
arrow int.
Oops, sorry about that.
So let me show a couple of uses of this.
here's, I'm going to write down an
expression that's going to end up
returning the first function that given X
returns two times X.
So I'll bind this to the variable double.
If I, all I have to do is call double or
triple with some argument that will cause
F of seven to evaluate to true.
So there's any number of them but how
about X minus three equals four.
Okay?
If I called out I'm going to end up
getting the double function back.
Notice that double is not a number.
It's a function, because double or triple
returns a function.
We could take that and then call it, or
we could take another call to double or
triple, maybe something that returns
false, like fun X, X equals 42,
that will not return true when applied to
7.
If we could just take that entire
expression which will end up being the
function that takes its argument an
multiplies it by three and if I call that
with 3, I'll end up with 3 times 3, which
is 9.
Okay?
So how about we try all that out real
quick?
Use generalizing dot SML.
And sure enough, double or triple is just
about the type I told you.
We'll get back to that in just a second.
Double is indeed an int arrow int,
and to make sure it's the function we
think it is, yes indeed, double zero four
returned eight, and this last expression
I wrote down did indeed evaluate to nine.
Alright, so now the only remaining thing
I want to talk about here is how I said
the type of double or triple was this,
taken int arrow bool, returning int arrow
int.
And the REPL said this type, and just
left off the parentheses around the
result type.
It always does that, the REPL never
prints parentheses it does not have to
and it turns out that those parentheses
are optional.
So to see that let me show you the
general rule which I have down here at
the bottom of this slide.
When you see a type like T, with multiple
arrows like this, like T1 arrow, T2
arrow, T3 arrow, T4, the implicit
parenthesis are always on the right.
So this for example would be a function
that takes a T1 and returns another
function that takes a T2, that itself
returns another function that takes a T3
and then returns a T4.
So when you're first seeing functions
that return functions, you really wish
the REPL would put in those parentheses
for you.
It's not going to, so you have to put
them in yourself in your head.
And you get used to this fairly quickly
and then you end up liking, in fact, the
conciseness of leaving off the
unnecessary parentheses.
Alright, so that was functions returning
other functions.
Now let me remind you that high-order
functions are not just good for numbers
and lists.
They're a great way to process, for any
sort of recursive data structure, where
you might want to do the same sort of
recursive traversal with many different
possible, computations.
So for an example of that, let me go back
over here and scroll down.
I have our old friend, this data type
binding for arithmetic expressions, and
suppose I give you a homework problem
like, given an X, one of these things, is
every constant in it an even number?
You could write that recursive function,
but suppose I had another homework
question that said is every constant in
it less than ten.
And you could write that as well but it
would be very, very similar and if you
had a bunch of these traversals that were
all of the form is something true of
every constant.
It would be a great idea to abstract that
kind of traversal, that kind of
processing of the data, into a higher
order function.
So let me, show you how may, might, we
might do that.
I might write a function true of all
constants.
It's going to take in a function and an
E, and it's going to say, does F return
true.
For every constant.
So it's a lot like a filter, in the sense
that we're going to call F on every
constant in here.
But it's not a filter, it's going to, the
whole thing is going to return true or
false.
So if our entire expression is a
constant, then I just want to call F.
On that constant and all the other cases
are just recursively calling true of all
constants on the sub-expressions, so that
we can find all the constants.
And this is the sort of thing that's fine
to write out once but it'd be a pain to
write it out over and over again for all
the different questions we might have
about the constants and expressions.
So it's great that we're abstracting it
into a higher order function that then
we'll be able to use multiple times.
Okay?
And I think that's right.
And then it's such a pain to write this
out. I'm even going to copy and paste
just a little bit and write multiply
there.
And now, if I wrote this once, and I
wanted to write the function that I
started with, all even.
Take an expression, are all the constants
in it even?
Then I would just say, true of all
constants, and pass in a little function
that asks if the argument is even, and
call that with E.
And let's see if I got all that right.
[SOUND].
And I at least got the types right.
all even is indeed a function that takes
in an X and returns a bool.
Yes or no, are all the, the constants
even?
True of all constants is one of those
high order functions that has nice type
that it really kind of explains a little
bit what's going on.
Although not completely, you still need
documentation for the function. It takes
in an X and an int arrow bool, because we
know that we take that function argument.
We apply it to constants, and then the
entire thing, the result type is bool.
Yes or no, the and also is combined to
return true or false based on whether all
the constants, are true according to this
int arrow bool argument.
So when you have these functions that
have return type bool like this, that
process some data,
I like to call them predicates.
It's a nice mathematical world.
The predicate is something that returns
true or false for something,
and this is an example of a higher order
predicate. It takes in, it abstracts over
that computation, says give me any
integer bool and I'll give you a
predicate that uses that int arrow bool.