[MUSIC] So it turns out that first class
functions are a lot more powerful than
we've seen so far.
But before we can understand that, we
need to take a step back and carefully
reason about this idea called Lexical
Scope.
So we're going to start that here.
So, this is a very important concept, but
it's not actually anything new.
It's something we just need to focus on
and reconsider now that we have higher
rare functions.
We know that a function body can use more
than just its arguments and any local
variables it defines.
It can use anything already in the
environment, anything in scope.
But the question is which scope, which
environment and the answer in almost all
programming languages these days is
Lexical Scope that we use the environment
where the function was defined not the
one where the function is being called.
Alright.
There are lot's of good reasons for the
symantecs, which we'll get to in the next
segment.
We'll even later in the course learn how
to implement the symantecs, which you
will do on one of your later homework
assignments.
But, at this point, we just want to make
sure we understand what the rule is and
the way Lexical Scope works.
This is one of the most important
concepts in the course, because we need
it to use first class functions as
properly and as powerfully as we can.
So let's look at an example, and I'll do
this with the code.
Alright.
this example doesn't actually have high
order functions in it, but we can still
see Lexical Scope being used.
So, here after line one, I have an
environment where clearly X maps to one.
So, in the next line when I add F to my
environment, I'm not going to repeat X,
I'll just add F here.
F maps to a function that adds one to its
argument.
And that is because whenever we call this
function we're going to valuate this
body, X plus Y, in an environment that we
have when the function was defined.
And when we defined this function, we had
an environment where X maps to 1.
So this function that f maps to always
adds one to its argument, no matter where
it is called.
That is the rule.
So, now lets see what happens, here on
line three, I shadow X so in this
environment X maps the two that has no
effect on F, has no effect on the
environment where F was defined.
Clearly here, we now have an environment
where x still maps to two, and y maps to
three.
So now we get to the all important call
here.
We look up F in the environment, we get
the function that adds 1 to it's
argument.
We look up X we get 2, we look up Y we
get 3.
So we call the function defined on.
Line 2 with 5, because we looked up X and
Y here in the environment at the call
site.
But then when we make the call, we pass
5, we add 1 to the argument, and so in
the end, Z maps to 6.
That's the essential part.
If you thought Z was going to map to 7,
you're using a different rule, which is
not how ML works, and not how most
programming languages work.
Okay.
So that is the key idea and the key
example for this segment.
Now let's go back to the slides.
Here I've said the same thing we just
talked about.
The point is that on Line 5 we evaluate X
+ Y in the current environment at Line 5
which gives us a 5 but then when we call
the function, we evaluate that function
body, the X + Y on line 2 in the old
environment where X maps to 1, extended
with Y, of course, mapping to 5 because
that's how function arguments work.
So this is why we need function closures,
which we have not talked about before, in
our language.
Right?
Because you might be thinking, that seems
a little magic to me.
How can a function be evaluated in an old
environment that isn't around any more?
Once we've shadowed X, how can that body
of F use the old X?
And the fact of the matter is it's not
magical because the language
implementation, the ML interpreter and
compiler and whatever else that
implements ML has to keep around those
old environments so that we can implement
Lexical Scope properly.
So the way to think about the semantics
of functions in general, is that we know
functions are values.
We can pass them around however we want.
But a function value actually has two
parts.
So far we've only been talking about the
code part which is sort of obvious.
You can't have a function without a body
to that function.
But a function value, this closure has a
second part.
It has with it the environment that was
current when the function was defined.
So we really have a pair.
It's not an ML pair.
It's just something with two parts, and
they, and those parts are the code and
the environment.
This thing is called a closure, and when
you call a function, you're actually
calling one of these pairs, one of these
closures.
And what you do is you evaluate the code
using the environment.
So you use both parts of the pair and
that's how a function call actually
works.
So in our example we can now go back to
it and see what actually happened,
another way to reason about the
semantics, which is at line two we
created a closure, and that closure had a
code part that said give me an argument
why and I'll evaluate the code X + Y.
And it had an environment part that said
that I will evaluate that code in an
environment where X maps to 1.
So then when we did the call on Line 5 we
passed to that closure the argument five,
two plus three and then the result of the
call used the code in the closure and the
environment in the closure with the one
addition that Y maps the 5 for the
function argument.
And that is once again why we got 6 back,
alright.
So that is Lexical Scope and that's how
closures implement Lexical Scope and
that's how you can think about the
functions we're going to be passing
around in ml.
So to give you a bit of an outline of
where we're going from here that is the
rule of Lexical Scope.
Now what I want to do in the next segment
is continue with these sort of silly
examples, but examples that use
functions, taking functions, or
functions, returning functions because
that shows that its a pretty powerful
feature, its may be a little harder to
reason about, so I want some more
advanced silly examples.
Then we'll get to the why.
Why would you implement, why would you
want the semantics of your language to
have this Lexical Scope.
We'll contrast it with the other
possibility which is called dynamic
scope.
And then we're going to talk a lot about
programming idioms.
How once you know that a language has
Lexical Scope, there's a number of very
powerful things you can do with first
class functions that rely on the fact
that we have Lexical Scope.