[MUSIC] Okay, I want to continue our
discussion of lexical scope.
Now, I am going to pass into the
discussion, functions that take and
return there functions.
So, the rule is not going to change.
The rule is the way always evaluate the
function body in the environment where
the function was defined.
At the point we created that function, we
made a closure with the environment, we
had at that moment.
And that's the environment we used when
we later called the function.
So, nothing is going to change here
except what the environment is, is going
to be much more interesting because we're
going to have nested let expressions,
we're going to take functions, we're
going to return functions.
So, in this segment, I'm going to do two
examples that are a little bit
complicated and are silly, and they're
not going to motivate the semantics.
And then in later segments, we'll get to
why you want the semantics and how it
lets you do powerful things,
okay?
So, let's go to the code. here's our
first example.
Let's just walk through it line by line.
So, we start with an environment where x
is one, this is going to turn out to be
irrelevant, because we're going to end up
shadowing x anywhere before we could
possibly use it.
Then on this next line, we're defining a
function y and this, oh, sorry function
f.
And this function f returns this
anonymous function right here.
So, let's just look at this function.
And the great thing about lexical scope
is we can figure out what this function
does completely separate from the rest of
the file and how it's potentially called.
So, the function f takes an argument y,
creates a local variable x that holds y +
1.
So, that's going to shadow in here, this
outer x, that would have been in the
environment but, of course, it's shadowed
in the body of this let expression.
We then return this function,
alright?
So whenever you call f with some y, this
is going to take z and return in terms of
f's argument, 2y + 1,
right?
Because x is y + 1 and we're adding x and
y and z together.
That is what it will always do because
the environment where this function was
defined had whatever y maps to based on
the call to f and then x-mapping 2y + 1.
So let's see that in action with a use of
f and a use of the function that's
returned.
Down here, I'm going to have val x = 3.
This will again be irrelevant.
I'm just putting it here to show that
it's irrelevant.
[SOUND] And the reason why it's
irrelevant is right here I call f with
four,
okay?
So, this is going to return a function
[SOUND] that adds 9 to its argument.
[SOUND] The reason why it's 9 is because
2Y + 1, where y is four, is nine.
We call f with four, so we go up to the
body of f right here,
y is four, we create an environment where
y is four and x is five and we return a
function that when called will use that
environment, extended with whatever z
maps to.
So sure enough, right here where I call
g, the function returned up here,
when I call g with six, I will get 15
because that is 9 + 6.
The fact that this y is five here, also
irrelevant.
The same way that we're not going to use
the fact that X is three, when we
evaluate this x plus y plus z, we're not
going to use this y = 5.
When we evaluate this x plus y plus z, we
use the environment where the function
was created,
y is four, x is five.
If we had another call to f down here
with a different argument, that would
create a different closure with a
different environment, one where x was,
oh, sorry, y was eight, and x was nine,
so that would return a function that
always added 17 to its argument, okay?
So, that's our first example, let us now
go to our second example.
In the second example, we're going to
pass in a function to a function rather
then returning a function from a
function,
alright?
So, here is our function f that takes a
function g.
And all it does is call g with two.
the rest of this is more irrelevant
clutter.
And, in fact,
let's look at function F.
And again, the advantage of lexical scope
is we can understand a function just by
looking at its definition and what is in
its environment.
We never have to look at how it's called.
So, if I look at this function, I say,
oh, it takes a function g and it calls it
with two.
And, in fact, the rest of this is, I
mean, I'm just defining a variable that's
never used so I would very naturally just
come in here and delete all these.
I'm, and, it just, I'm commenting it out
here so you can still see it, but that
should be exactly the same function, a
function that takes its argument and
calls it with two, is the same as a
function that defines a local variable x
to be three and then calls g with two.
So, the great thing about lexical scope
is you can do this kind of code
maintenance and know that its never going
to change how the function behaves.
Let's see that by following through with
an actual call.
So here, I have val x = 4.
And now, I create a little function here,
h. So, this function is always going to
add four to its arguement.
Why?
because it's the same thing at top level.
When I create this binding h, I create a
closure that has it, the current
environment where the function was
defined.
And then at this point, we have an
evironment where x is four, so h is bound
to a function that will always add four
to its arguement.
So now, we got to the exciting last line
where we're going to call f with h.
So, I'm going to look up f and I'm going
to get this function that always calls
its argument with two.
And I'm going to pass in h, which is a
function that always adds four to its
argument.
So, I will get six,
I will not get seven.
Seven is what you would get if you passed
in this code, which has body xy.
+ y.
And then here said, oh, now, I want to
look up x in this environment.
But that's wrong.
We always look up x in the body where the
function we're calling was defined.
And here, we pass for g the function h,
that's this function.
We looked up h in the environment, we got
this function that adds four to its
argument and so we get six,
alright?
So, those are our two complicated
examples.
If you don't believe me, feel free to go
back through them more slowly.
Try them in the read–eval–print loop.
See what the different variables are
bound to at different points.
The remaining slides here have the exact
same examples and a little bit more text
to walk you through it.
So, this was the first example we did
when we ended up with 16, and this is the
second example where we ended up with six
bound to z.
So now, that we hopefully understand
lexical scope and believe me that we
didn't change the rule in this segment,
it's the same rule we had before,
we can move on to discussing why you want
the semantics for your programming
language.