[MUSIC] Okay, now in our study of lexical
scope, we can get to the motivation of
why this is the symantecs you want.
So remember lexical scope is using the
environment where a function is defined
to look up variables in the function
body.
The other natural thing you might think
of, go, does have a name, it's called
dynamic scope.
If you have dynamic scope use the
environment where the function is called.
So decades ago, these were considered
reasonable options and in a programming
language course, you would study both and
think about which one of language you
might have.
I think it's fair to say that, these
days, lexical scope is considered the one
that makes sense.
We'll talk a little bit at the end of
this segment about things that do work
with dynamic scope, it is occasionally
useful.
But lexical scope is really how
programming languages work these days.
So, there are reasons for this and these
are precise technical reasons.
Sometimes in programming languages,
things are just a matter of taste,
but I'm about to show you things that
lexical scope let's you do,
ways it let's you reason about code and
dynamic scope simply does not,
and that much is not a matter of opinion.
The only opinion you might have is
whether or not those reasons are good or
important.
So let's just get started.
I'll show you three main reasons.
The first two are actually related.
The first one I'll say that the meaning
of a function does not depend on what
variable names you use.
This is nice,
because you can go in and change the
names of your variables, say to make them
more informative or to port them to
different human language or something,
and you can know that it's not going to
affects any of your callers.
So for example, look at this first
function we see here we've seen a
function like this before, and suppose
that you come along and say, you know, x
is not very, a very good name for that. I
want to call it q of fu or pizza instead.
You could change it here and you could
change it here and you would know that no
caller can tell.
It's a local variable and the name of
local variables should really never
matter.
It's good abstraction.
It's good modularity.
It's good software engineering and it's
only lexical scope that gives us that.
Let me show you that with the code here.
So here, I have the function that we had
on the slide,
I've just called it f1 to distinguish it
from f2 here.
And f2, I've done the variable renaming I
suggested.
It's exactly like f1, except I've used q
for my local variable both in its
definition and its use instead of x.
And it turns out that no one will ever be
able to tell.
If I call (f1 7) and get a function back,
that function is going to add 15 to its
argument, 2y + 1.
If I call (f2 7), I will get back a
function that adds 15 to its argument.
All callers can tell is that I get back a
function that adds 15 to its argument, so
both a1 and a2 will be 19. It doesn't
matter that there is an x in scope here.
If we had dynamic scope, if we evaluated
these function bodies, x + y + z, q + y +
z, where we called these functions
instead of where they were defined, then
under dynamic scop, one of these
functions would end up using this 17 and
the other one would actually end up with
an unidentified variable.
because we would try to use q and there
would not be any q here, that's actually
one of the other reasons we're going to
get to, okay? So that's our first reason
is that function domain does not depend
on the variable name uses.
I actually already showed you another
example of this which is the second
example down here, that it lets you
remove unused variables.
In the previous segment, I showed you an
example where we had a function body that
was let val x = 3 or something like that,
in g called 2.
This val x is irrelevant, so it would be
fine to remove it.
On the other hand, if we had dynamic
scope, then if the caller to f passed in
some g that had in its function body x,
we might end up using that x, because
here is the call site and under dynamic
scope, which is not what ML has. We would
end up using the environment where the
function was called.
So you really need lexical scope, to
reason about these functions this way,
this way,
and this is essential, for modularity of
the software.
And modularity, in software is one of the
most important features you want from
your programming language.
Okay.
On to reason two,
somewhat similar.
Functions can be type checked and
reasoned about where they're defined not
where they're used.
So let's look at this example.
we can just look at it on this slide
here.
I look at this function f, which we, it's
the same one I've been showing you.
And we can reason about the fact that it
returns 2y + 1 and its function that when
called returned 2y + 1, excuse me.
And its type is take an int and return an
int arrow int.
So its type is int arrow, int arrow int.
Once we know that it type checks, we know
that if we call it with an int, that
shouldn't lead to any problems.
And indeed, when we call it was 7 here on
the second to last line, we get back the
function that will add 15 to its argument
and then when we call that with 4 we get
19.
What if we had dynamic scope? If we had
dynamic scope, then down here at the
bottom, when we end up calling this
function, we go to evaluate x + y + z.
What we're going to get back, hm,
we're going to look up x in our
environment,
we're going to get a string.
That's a really bad idea since you can't
add strings in ML.
We're going to look up y in the
environment.
We're going to get an undefined variable.
Well, no,
y we might get, or z because there is no
y and z here.
Those are undefined variables.
So our whole purpose of type checking
just got thrown out the window with
dynamic scope, because we end up using
the wrong variables in the wrong places.
Okay? Onto our third and probably most
exciting example, because it's going to
to let us do new things. Closures just
got much more powerful, because we can
use this lexical scope idea to have them
store whatever data they need.
And this is, works particularly well with
functions like map and filter that I've
showed you before that iterate over data
structures.
So, I have the same code over here. Let
me get to it here. Alright.
So, we have seen the function filter
before.
This is just a function that takes a
function f and a list xs and returns a
list that only contains the elements of
xs for which f returns true.
Okay?
So suppose that I wanted to filter on all
of the, I wanted all the numbers that
were greater than negative one or the
nonnegative numbers.
Here is the way I could implement that in
these two lines using filter.
What I'm going to do is I am going to
define a little high order function here
it takes in a number x and it returns the
function that takes a y and returns true
if y > x.
So greater than x has type int arrow int
arrow int.
So, down here where I call greater than x
with minus one, I'll get back an int
arrow int.
Okay?
So if I call filter with the result of
this call, that's essentially going to be
a function that takes in a y And asks is
y > -1?
Filter that over the list,
I get a function that takes a list and
returns all the nonnegative numbers in
the list, zero or positive.
So where are we using lexical, lexical
scope here? In the creation of this
function that would pass the filter,
greater than x, when called with minus
one, returns a closure that captures,
stores in its environment that x is minus
one.
So, when we pass this function into
filter, we will be asking for each
element of the list,
is that element greater than minus one?
It does not matter that up here in the
body of filter, there's a different x.
If we had dynamic scope, this would not
this, would ask is a number greater than
itself, we would get false, and we had
filter everything out of our list.
What's going on here in general is that
filter just says give me a function, any
function f, and it does not care about
the fact that the closure pass then, can
have whatever data it needs in its
environment.
In this example, it's using just minus
one that was stored when we created the
closure here.
I may show you a second example using an
unanimous function. We also call filter.
This is a function all greater than or
all greater, that takes in a list and a
number and filter out all the numbers
less than n, less than or equal to n.
So it only returns strings strictly
greater than n.
So, I call filter, I call it with this
little anonymous function n, xs, and
notice that when I pass in this function,
it's going to end up getting called in
the body of filter between if and then.
But we look up variables in the body of
that function, not where the function is
called but where the function is defined.
So when we look up this n, we will always
get the n that was passed into all
greater.
So this will work correctly if you call a
greater with a list and 17, we will
filter out anything that is 17 or less
and we need lexical scope to do that.
Alright?
Let's go back to the slides we will see
more examples of this after I show you
some other high-order functions, but this
is really where we get a lot of the power
of closures.
And now, let me ask the question, if
dynamic scope is such a bad idea, why do
we even have a name for it? Okay?
So, people now do realize that lexical
scope for variables is definitely the
right default.
It's very common behavior across
programming languages, it's important
when designing a language to get this
right.
Now, dynamic scope is occasionally
convenient in some situations.
And so some languages, for example Racket
which we'll use later in the course have
special ways to do it.
You can add to your language a special
kind of variable, separate from the
regular variables, that works with
dynamic scope.
Most languages don't bother but it can be
convenient.
an example is trying to change through
dynamic scoping where output is
redirected to certain files and things.
I'm not going to show an example here.
The other thing I would like to point out
is if you squint a little bit and think
about it, exceptions, which we saw
previously in the course, act a little
bit like dynamic scope.
If you think about a handle expression
and when you raise an exception, which
handler does it go to? It's not lexical.
You don't look at the structure of the
code.
It's not the closest handle expression
where the raise was defined.
It's the closest handle on the call stack
in the current dynamic nesting of calls
and that is much more like dynamic scope.
You look up the current handler,
is it, did your caller want to handle
this exception? Did its callers want to,
and it's not based on where things were
defined.
And lots of experience with exception
handling just suggests that for
exceptions, that's a better default,
people find that more convenient and
better stylistically when designing their
software.