.
Alright in this lecture I want to show
you something kind of neat about tuples,
and to use that to introduce this really
important concept in programming
languages called syntactic sugar.
So let me just show this to you in the
repple.
we have already seen how to build pairs.
Here's a pair.
Three plus one, four plus two creates the
pair (4,6), no problem.
And, similarly, we could create a record,
maybe with a field second of four2, plus
two and a field first of three1.
plus one.
Alright?
So nothing unusual there.
We see the tuples and records are
similar, but different.
But now, suppose I did something kind of
strange, and I made a record.
But I made the field names, say, one and
two,
in whatever order I want, because the
order never matters.
Something like this.
Watch this.
Oh isn't that weird.
I made a record with field names one and
two and the repple printed it out as a
pair, (6,5), and it printed the type as
int * int.
Its like it turned my record into a tuple
or something.
Of course this is no problem, right? If I
wanted to say, take a hash one of a pair,
and add to that hash two of another pair.
Oop.
underscore not plus,
there we go.
I get nine of type int and you know for
hash one and hash two it doesn't really
matter.
Hash two can mean get the second
component of a pair or it can say get
field two of a record.
Right?
So it doesn't seem to matter.
and just to show that you really can give
numeric field names to records if I had a
record like this with three and one,
alright,
well that prints as a normal record.
it has type one:bool three:string.
But if I had something with three equals
hi, one equals true, two equals, say,
three plus two.
Now I have a triple, (true, five, hi,)
bool * int * string.
And what I want to convince you is that
this is because there is no such thing as
tuples in ML, there are only records and
tuples are just a way, a different way of
writing records that you as a programmer
can use whenever you want.
And the repple always chooses to use of a
[INAUDIBLE] and this is because tuples
are just "syntactic sugar" for records.
So lets unpack that idea little bit here.
Okay.
Previously, I taught you tuples as though
they're in ML.
We gave syntax,
we gave type-checking rules, and we gave
evaluation rules.
But we could've done something else
instead.
I could've taught you records first, even
though they're a little more complicated,
and then told you that there's some
special syntax for writing certain kinds
of records.
That whenever you write the syntax for
building a tuple, e1 comma up to en, in
parentheses, that that's just another way
of writing the record with field names
one up to n, and with the corresponding
expressions.
And whenever you write the type for a
tuple type with those stars in between
the component pieces,
that's just another way of writing the
record type where, again, the field names
are one through N.
In other words, tuples are nothing more
and nothing less than records with
particular field names.
And that is how the ML Language
definition actually works.
That all there is about tuples are
special syntax that you can use when
writing programs, and that we print when
we write the results of things in the
rupple.
So you really can write things like the
record one equals four, two equals seven,
three equals nine.
It's terrible style.
I don't know why you would do this.
The tuple syntax is easier to read, it's
what people expect.
I just showed you this for the purpose of
teaching you this idea.
But it really is that in ML we have
records, tuples are just a particular way
of writing particular records.
So,
what we say in programming language
speak, is that tuples are just syntactic
sugar for records with fields named one,
two, up to N.
So, I'm going to use this phrase a lot in
the course, so let's understand exactly
what it means.
Syntactic because we can describe the
semantics,
the evaluation rules and typing rules for
tuples, completely in terms of something
else.
Right?
We do this.
Just you wrote this.
It's like you wrote that.
And then we can use all the semantic
rules we have for a different language
construct.
So that's why it's called syntactic when
we do this.
We call it sugar because it makes the
language sweeter.
It's a pleasant thing to use and see.
So we call it syntactic sugar.
We're going to see many more examples of
this. there,
syntacic sugar is great because it
simplifies our understanding of the
language.
Once you understand how tuples are really
a form of records, you understand
everything there is to know about tuples,
as long as you understand records.
They also simplify implementing the
language.
The ML implementation just has to convert
tuples into the corresponding records and
there isn't as much duplicative work to
do.
We only have to implement one kind of
each of type, instead of two.
Okay.
So this is far from the only example
we'll see.
there are other examples of syntactic
sugar and actu, we, we've already seen
one other.
You can think of e1 and also e2 as being
syntactic sugar for,
if e1, then e2, else false.
Right?
We can explain everything there is to
explain about and also, in terms of that
syntactic transformation in terms of an
if-then-else.
And also is better styled, but we can
define its semantics in terms of another
concept, we already understand.
So that's syntactic sugar.
And now we understand the truth about
tuples