In this segment we start our study of
data types.
This is the language concept we'll use in
ML to make our own one of types which is
a really important feature in
programming.
but ML does it in a very different way
than other languages you've probably
seen.
So it'll take us a while to build up the
ideas we need.
So what we're going to do is we're going
to introduce our third kind of binding.
So far we've seen variable bindings with
val, function bindings with fun, now data
type bindings which start with the
keyword data type.
These pack a lot more punch into one
binding, so I have to tell you the
different things that happen when you use
a data-type binding.
So, what you do here, as you see on the
slide, is you write some type name,
any name you want like MI type, is just a
silly example to show you the pieces.
Then an equals, then a bunch of
possibilities.
These are separated by the pipe
character, which you can think of as or.
So, this says, I want a new type Mytype.
And the way you make values of MyType is
either, they carry an int, star int, or
they carry a string, or they carry
nothing.
So they are one of types.
Every value of MyType is either going to
have a pair of int's or a string or
nothing.
And we could have any number of
possibilities that we want.
Now, what I haven't explained yet are
these things you see in the capital
letters:
TwoInts, and Str, and Pizza.
I chose pizza just to emphasize that
there's, you, these can be any names that
you want.
It's conventional to capitalize them.
Some people use all capitals.
but I'll just capitalize them like you
see here.
and these we call the constructors.
So what is happening when you introduce a
data type binding, is that we are adding
multiple things to our environment,
both our static environment, and our
dynamic environment.
We're introducing this new type name,
mytype.
And we're introducing the constructors,
TwoInts, STIR, and Pizza.
And these constructors have a couple
purposes.
But for now, they're just functions that
given values of the correct arguments,
return something of MyType.
So two ints, as a constructor is now in
our environment and is a function of type
int STR int arrow MyType.
If you give it a pair of ints you will
get back a MyType.
STR is a function from string to MyType.
And pizza is not a function because it
doesn't carry anything.
It already is a value of type MyType.
Alright.
So, lets try this out in the repple I
have the same example here.
Here's a data type binding.
And then I just have a bunch of variable
bindings that are using the constructors
in various ways.
So let's just load this up and use it,
and see if what we get back makes a
little bit of sense.
Alright?
So, what the repple prints out is first,
it evaluated the data type binding.
And it'll just print the whole thing
because it is relevant to what we see in
the rest of the file, in the rest of our
program that we now have a type MyType
and it has constructors, pizza, STR which
takes a string and two ints of in star
int.
The order of constructors in our binding
doesn't matter.
So as usual, the repple has chosen to
alphabetize them for us just like it does
with record field names.
Then when I said val A equals STR high,
that makes sense.
STR as a constructor, is a function from
type string error MyType So, if we call
it with a string, we get back a MyType
and that's why you see here in the repple
that val A does, indeed, have MyType But
what's the value?
Well it turns it is STR of high.
These constructor if you can also think
of as tags as things that are actually
there in the values to say what kind of
MyType we have.
Here we have the STR kind of MyType and
the underlying value, the underlying
string, is the string high.
So, that's why A is bound to the value,
STR of high.
So, constructor applied to value is the
value.
Alright.
If you had just said STR without an
argument well, that is just a function
from string to MyType that's why valve B
here is a function from string to MyType.
This is a common programming error.
You probably didn't mean that.
You probably meant STR applied to
something.
But it does type check, and it just does
something that you probably weren't
expecting.
On the other hand, with pizza, that makes
perfect sense.
Pizza is a value of type mytype.
So, if I have that as my expression for
C, then C is going to be pizza.
The same way A will be STR of high.
Alright, D similarly, if you want to use
the two ints constructor, we'll pass it
in int STR int.
So, in this case, we'd evaluate one plus
two to three, three plus four to seven,
pass that resulting pair to two ints.
And so, the result is this value, two
ints of three comma seven.
All right.
Once you have these values you can use
them however you want.
So if you say val E equals A, of course
we look up A in the dynamic environment.
We get STR of high and that is now the
result of E as well.
Just like it has been with everything
else, that we've seen in the course.
All right.
So there are a few examples.
Let's go back to the slides and consider
even some more.
Okay, so anytime you have a value of type
my type, its going to be made from one of
the constructors.
That's why it's a one of type.
And the value you get back really does
have two parts.
It has what I'll call the tag part, that
remembers which constructor you used to
make this value.
And then it has the corresponding data.
So for example, if you this expression,
two ints three plus four, five plus four,
that evaluates to something with tag part
two ints And corresponding data part,
seven comma nine.
Similarly STR if true then hi, else, bye.
would evaluate to STR of hi.
Okay.
So we now know how to build data type
values.
But whenever we introduce a new type in
our language we need a way to build the
pieces and we need a way to access them.
For one of types and data types, like
mytype really are one of those types.
There are two aspects to accessing the
value.
We need some way to check which kind of
thing we have,
which variant of mytype we have, ie,
what's the tag?
Which constructor made it?
And then we also need a way to get the
underlying data, if there is any.
For pizza there isn't, but for two ints
and STR there is.
So this is a moment where it is worth
looking at the other one of types we've
seen, lists and options and seeing that
they have these two aspects for accessing
the values also.
Null which tells you whether a list is
empty or not and esum which tells you
whether an option issome or none are the
variant checking functions.
All right.
That's all they do.
They tell you which tag is it the empty
list or is it not the empty list.
Is it none or is it some?
Where as the head, tail, and val of
functions we've seen, those extract the
data.
Head returns part of a list.
Tail returns part of a list.
Valid returns the thing under the sun.
Now we have an issue here.
What if you apply head to the empty list,
or val of to none, well those raise
exceptions for the wrong variant.
So now that we have data type bindings.
One thing ML could have done is said that
when you introduce a data type binding,
like data type, mytype, equals, all that
stuff,
in addition to getting the constructors,
those functions two ints and STR in the
constant pizza,
you would also get functions for checking
variants and extracting data.
Maybe it would add to the environment
functions like is STR of type MyType
arrow bool, take it to MyType and return
true if that value was made from the STR
constructor.
And get STR data, of type mytype arrow
string,
that would get you the underlying value,
if it is a STR and raise an exception
otherwise.
These would be direct analogies of how
head and null work.
Null is like isStr, head is like
getStrData Alright?
That would make sense.
It would be a perfectly reasonable
language.
It would probably be easier to teach you
right now, but instead ML did something
much better, and we'll start studying it
in the next segment.