.
Alright.
In this segment, we're going to start
studying case expressions,
which is the ML language concept we're
going to use to access values made up
from the types we introduced with data
type bindings.
So, what we're going to do is we're going
to take these two ideas we learned in the
last segment.
Then we need a way to figure out which
variant of a one of type we have.
And we need a way to get the pieces out.
We're going to see that ML combines these
into a single language construct.
In future segments we'll see its actually
much more powerful than we're showing
here.
But we'll introduce the basics to see how
you can use it.
So you see the example here on the slide.
I also have it here in ML.
So in the,
in a, file here.
So you see the same datatype binding we
studied before.
So this is a new type, MI type, its built
from one of these three constructors,
either two ints, str, or pizza.
Okay And now what I have is a function
that's actually going to take in
something of type MI type.
We could have written this here, but as
we'll see this is not op, this is
optional.
It's fine, to let ML figure this out for
us.
And this is going to take in a MI type,
and in this case, return an int.
Alright?
So the way we're going to do this is
we're going to have this case expression.
What we're going to do is between the
case and the of, which are both keywords,
we're going to have a value that was
built out of the data type.
In this case, MI type, if we had a
different data type binding with use case
expressions on that too.
We use case expressions to access the
pieces of a data type.
Then what we have, as indicated by the
english word case, is several cases.
And each of these cases is separated by
this pipe character, and what this
basically says is if it's a pizza, then
take this branch, so like an
if-then-else, it's something with
branches, and evaluate this thing on the
right.
So you'll get three.
If it's a string, then I take this branch
and get an eight.
Well, what is this s for?
This s is a variable that we will bind to
the data under the string constructor.
Now, we're not using that here because we
didn't want to use the string, but we
could have.
And this variable s would be in scope in
this branch.
And finally in this last branch, we
actually are going to use this idea.
We're going to say, take this branch if x
was made from the two ints constructor.
And when evaluating this corresponding
expression, let i1 be the first int made
from the two ints and i2 be the second
int that was provided when we made the
two ints.
And so in this case we'll add the two
branches together.
Alright? So let's try that out.
Let's go over and use this file.
And sure enough f is just a function from
type MI Type to int and now we can try
calling f with pizza,
and we'll get three.
Or we can call f with str of hi, and
we'll get eight.
Notice by the way we can't call f with
just hi.
Right.
Hi is type string, right, not type MI
Type.
So if we do this we'll get a type error
message that this is not the type that f
expects.
F's argument x has to be a MI Type and
you can tell that because of these
patterns that we use to match against the
value.
And now probably the most interesting
case if we call f with two ints of some
pair of ints like maybe (7,9),
we will get sixteen.
Alright?
So, that's how you use it.
Of course, if we had, had some val x that
equals a str of hi, then we could have
called f with x and this would all work
as usual.
Okay so now let's go back and look at
that case expression a little more
carefully, to make sure we understand its
syntax and evaluation rules and typing
rules.
And I think the slides will help us do
that.
Okay so here's the same code, so we're
really focusing in on this case
expression and in one sense its a
multi-branch conditional.
Its like an if-then-else, if-then-else
that's nested.
What we do is we evaluate this expression
between case and of.
That's going to give us some value And
then we're going to see which branch
matches.
So this is called pattern matching,
because to the left of this arrow, the
equal angle bracket, are different
patterns.
Alright? And we take the first branch
that matches.
And the definition of matching is built
from the same constructor.
Alright? Once we build the same, match
the constructor we then use these
variables that are part of the pattern to
introduce local bindings.
So in this case, its like a little let
expression.
Alright? So this is letting i1 being the
first int and i2 being the second int in
the pair that was made with the two ints.
And in this branch we're letting s be the
underlying string.
And we can choose whatever variable names
we want and the scope of the variables is
just that branch alright.
Okay.
So the pattern match [INAUDIBLE], is
first, find what branch matches and bind
the variables appropriately,
then in that extended environment,
evaluate the expression on the right and
that's the answer for the whole thing.
So this example is slightly different
than what I showed you in the code, but
in each case, we have some expression
over here.
They all have to have the same type, just
like a then branch, and an else branch
have to have the same type, because the
result of the entire case expression is
going to be the result of whatever
branch's expression we evaluate. And so
the type of the entire case expression
has to be the type of those branches.
Okay?
So that is a case expression.
In general, let's now generalize it past
our example, we're going to have some
expression between the case and the of.
And then we're going to have a bunch of
branches.
Each branch is a pattern, which I'm
writing with p here, and then this equal
angle bracket and then an expression.
And we separate them with these pipe
characters.
So a pattern is a new kind of thing.
I know that they look like expressions.
If I go back here two ints i1 comma i2,
kind of looks like an expression.
It is not an expression.
Okay, it is something we're going to use
to intro, to do the matching and then to
introduce variable bindings.
Okay for the corresponding branch.
So for today,
in this segment, each pattern is just a
constructor name, and then the correct
number of variables.
So for pizza, it was just the constructor
name.
For str, it was the constructor name and
one variable.
For two ints, it was the constructor name
and then two variables in parenthesis
separated by commas.
If you had three arguments, it would be
similar and so on.
So syntactically, they look like
expressions, but we don't evaluate them.
They're not expressions.
We use them for pattern matching.
And then what we do is, we match the
result of evaluating the zero against
those patterns,
get the variables bound to the
corresponding pieces, and evaluate the
same branch on the right-hand side.
So, why is this better than a different
model where we just provided functions
like istr and getstr data like I said ML
could have done?
Well first of all, if you really wanted
such functions you could define them
yourself.
You could use pattern matching to write a
function of type MI type arrow bool that
for str return true and for any two ints
or pizza would return false. Do not do
that.
It's poor style.
You're giving up most the benefits of
pattern matching.
But certainly, case expressions are just
as powerful as that approach because we
can use case expressions to do that
approach.
Okay.
But these next two reasons, one and two,
are probably the most important ones.
Which is that thanks to writing all your
different possibilities together in a
case expression.
The compiler can check that you don't
forget any cases and you don't have any
redundant cases.
So let me show that by flipping back
here.
You might of seen, I had some commented
out things here.
Suppose I un-comment this last case.
So now I have two branches for pizza.
Alright? Could be an error that you make.
If you come over here to SML, always
restart by the way, otherwise you end up
shadowing the constructors, it's very
confusing.
case expressions.SML.
oh look at that.
It no longer compiles, and in fact, it
actually says that we have a redundant
notch.
It's a compiled time error because it
knows that the fourth branch in my code
could never be taken.
Oops, that's a different file.
There we go.
That this fourth branch could never be
taken, and so it's a compile time error
since you know, there'd be no reason to
write such code.
And so that's very helpful.
suppose conversely that we forgot our two
ints case, or rather than showing you
that how about I leave that in and I show
you this other function that forgets a
couple cases.
It forgets both the str'd case and the
two ints case.
Well in this case I believe we will just
get a warning if I recall correctly, but
a warning that we would be very wise to
heed.
and it says, warning match non
exhaustive.
And indeed, if you take that function G,
and you call it with a str of hi,
you now get a run time exception saying,
I tried to find a matching pattern, and I
didn't.
And, if we don't have any of those
warnings when we compile, then we know
that will never happen.
So, this is a nice guarantee we're
getting, from the type checker, which is
looking at all our patterns and making
sure we've covered all the possibilities.
Okay, so that's the first two reasons.
The third reason is that we'll never, if
we use case expressions the way they're
intended,
do things that lead to errors, like head
of the empty list.
That instead, we always have one case and
in that case, the patterns already
extracted the values.
So when we had, in our program over here,
str of s, we already know, in this case,
that s is going to be down to the
underlying string. And we'll never make
the mistake that over here in this branch
of trying to get, one of the int values
under a two ints, right?
Because, we just use the pattern to get
the values out.
Okay.
And finally we're not done showing you
case expressions, alright?
This is the simple use of them but we're
going to generalize them.
It turns out patterns can be much richer
and more powerful than we've shown so
far.
And we'll be able to use those patterns
to write very elegant and very concise
code.
Much more elegant and concise than if we
had to use functions for checking
variants and extracting pieces of data.