Alright, in this section I just want to
show some more examples of data type
bindings in particular, because the only
example I've show you so far was just a
silly example that didn't actually do
anything useful.
So I want to explore the idea of one of
types and some of the common idioms that
we see them used for.
Alright.
So these example will be small.
But they'll nonetheless be indicative of
the sort of things to use data types for.
So the simplest example is probably just
for what's e-nums or enumerations are
used for in other languages.
If you haven't heard of those, no
problem.
So supposed I just want to represent what
suit a playing card is.
So in English, every playing card is
either a club, a diamond, a heart, or a
spade.
So it would be a great example to just
have a datatype binding.
I have a new type suite, and then if I
want to do something for each possible
suite I can just have a case expression
that has one branch for each pattern.
If you don't do this with an enumeration
you end up just encoding something like
oh, one is for club, two is for diamond,
three is for heart.
And that sort of thing is hard to keep
track of,
you don't get as much error checking,
it's harder to read.
Data types are perfect for this.
Now what's interesting is this is a very
simple use of data types because none of
the constructors, club, diamond, heart,
spade, carried any data, there were no
underlying values, and that's fine data
types just can do more than that.
So another example is if I wanted the
rank of a playing card.
So this is the thing that in America is
called a Jack, a Queen, a King or an Ace
or is a number between two and ten.
So the second data type I have here can
represent that fairly well, you could
argue that by doing num of int I'm not
restricting that int to be between two
and ten, it could be negative seven, it
could be a 142.
But this is still a pretty good concise
way, a very readable way to read the rank
part of a playing card.
You would then, and we'll see how to do
this in a future segment, create an each
of type that had a suit and a rank.
And that would represent a card.
Alright, so another common pattern,
another common idiom that we use data
types for is when we just have alternate
ways of identifying some object, some
thing that we're representing in our
program.
So suppose I had a bunch of students in
my class.
And mostly I wanted to represent them by
some sort of student number.
But some of the students were say, just
taking a pass/fail or just sitting in,
they were turning in the homework but
they didn't have a student number.
So then what I might want, is some type,
like called ID, for student ID, that was
either an int, which I'll mark with a
constructor student num.
Or a name, which could have a first name,
a last name, and maybe an optional middle
name.
And since for each student I only want
one of these possibilities.
I don't want any confusion, I don't want
all of this stuff.
this is a perfectly reasonable way to
represent them.
So compare it if you will to trying to do
that same idea with each of types and
unfortunately students often do this and
we often even see code and programming
languages that encourage using each of
types when you have conceptually one of
type.
So here's something that's really bad
style Let's do the same idea where we
have a record, with a STUDENTNUM field, a
FIRST field, a MIDDLE field, and a LAST
field, but we'll say, even though
students' IDs have all these, you should
never use them all.
And what we'll do is we'll say the
STUDENTNUM is what you should use, but if
it's minus one, or some other special
value, then ignore it and use the first
middle and last field.
Alright?
So what don't I like about this approach?
You're basically giving up all the
benefits of using a language concert that
enforces that you have a 1-0 type.
You're getting no help that people should
only use a number or a name, not both.
You have to read this comment to
understand that you have to expect a
minus one value and react accordingly.
It just makes it a lot less clear, what
it is that you're actually doing.
And that's why in any programming
language, it's worth learning how 1-0
types should be represented, and then
using that pattern when it's the right
thing to do.
Alright, now that said, this is a bit of
a strange example because there are
situations where it makes sense to use an
each of type to represent students.
Suppose we just had a slightly different
thing we were modeling, where every
person does have a name and optionally
has a student number.
And I want to have both of those.
Well if you want both things then each of
is exactly the right thing, and you
should use a record time like you see
here.
This student num should just be an int
option.
Don't use minus one, it's too hard to
remember to check for it.
Use and options, which is the sum of a
number, or none.
That's the one of.
And then the first, middle and last names
should always be present.
Since the middle name may not always be
present, we'll make that an option as
well.
So this is a big thing you have to do
when you're designing your software, is
understand what kind of data you want,
how you're going to model those things in
your program, and then use the right kind
of compound types, to directly capture
the idea of what you're doing.
Alright.
So that's all good.
Now, in the rest of the segment, let me
focus on an example of another kind of
data type binding that's going to be
recursive, and is going to be near and
dear to our hearts.
Because it's how you represent things
like programming languages themselves.
So here's the last data type binding I'm
going to show you in this segment.
It's called X for expression.
And it defines a little language if you
will of arithmetic expressions.
So it says, an expression is one of the
following things.
It's either a constant, which holds an
ent.
Or a negation of a smaller expression;
not just an INT, but any smaller
expression.
An add, an addition of two smaller
expressions, or a multiply of two smaller
expressions.
So notice how we're using self-reference
here.
Many of the constructors themselves hold
other Xs the same way a list in its tail
holds another list.
And what we're actually doing is defining
a set of trees.
The set of trees that this data type
binding represents are trees where at the
leaves are constants, with a number
attached.
And at the internal nodes, are either
negate, which has one child, one smaller
expression.
Or, add and multiply, that have two
smaller expressions.
So NML, once we have this data type
binding, we could write an expression
like you see here in the middle.
We could just call the add constructor
with two arguments that each themselves
have type X.
The first one could be constant, which we
just need to call with any thing of type
int.
Like the result of the expression ten
plus nine.
And then negate, which has to be called
with one expression.
And another expression could be the
constant four.
So that's how we would write these MML.
But what I want you to have in your head
is this tree version of it.
To think of this expression as evaluating
to this value.
It's a tree that has add here at the
root, two children constant, which holds
a nineteen, and negate, which itself has
a child which is a constant that holds
four.
And so every value of type X is going to
look like some sort of tree that has this
kind of shape.
So now we very concisely, in just a
4-line data binding, described a set of
trees that represent an interesting
collection of arithmetic expressions.
And now what we could do is we could
write functions that operate over things
of type x.
And probably the most obvious type of
functions, to write is something that
takes an X and returns the integer you
get if you evaluate it.
Right.
So we have a little language here.
Let's write a function, e-val of type X
arrow int.
So we're going to take any X and we're
going to return the int that arithmetic
expression should evaluate to if you
actually ran it.
So here's what we would do, we would have
a case expression.
We would say, well, any X is built with
constant, negate or multiply.
What should we do in each case?
Well, if it's built with constant.
Let's get the underlying int out.
That's the result.
That's the number.
But what if we have a negate.
Well then we have some smaller expression
here.
We'll bind it to E2.
So now over here in this right branch, we
have an expression that is in the
variable E2.
And what we could do is recursively call
e-val on it.
And that will tell us the result of
evaluating E2 in this little language.
And then we could use ML's negation
operator to negate the result.
For add, lets bind a two local variables.
The two sub trees, E1 and E2 recursively
call eval on both of them.
Take those two numbers we get back and
use ML's plus, ML's addition to come up
with the result.
And if you like that, multiply is very
similar.
Create two variables.
E1 and E2 for the two parts,
recursively called Eval,
and then multiply them together.
So, it's perhaps not very surprising that
functions over recursive data types, data
type bindings that have self reference
like this, end up being recursive.
You want to do something useful within
the X you have.
Usually you need to consider the smaller
expressions that are in the subtrees of
that tree.
And they way that your going to
recursively· find those and figure out
how they're made is with a recursive
function call that then has it's own case
expression.
All right.
So that's most of the code I wanted to
show you.
Everything I've shown you on the slides
is over here in the file.
You'll also notice a second function
here, number of ads, and then I have some
example codes.
So for example here's what I had on the
slide.
So example X is just a little variable,
mining of type X.
And then example ints what I call eval on
example E, will just be something of type
int.
I have one other, this function number of
ads, also, happens to have the same type
as eval, X arrow int.
But what it does, is it doesn't run the
expression doesn't, compute it's answer.
Instead, it just counts how many
additions are anywhere in the expression.
And it's the same kind of recursive
processing.
I'll just do a case on E.
If it's a constant, there are no ads in
it.
If it's in a gate, it has the same number
of ads that are in E two.
So just recursively call number of ads
with E two, and that's our answer.
If it is an ad,
well then, there's one ad.
But we need to also include any ads that
are in the sub expressions.
So let's recursively call number of ads,
E1, number of ads, E2,
add those together, add one to that, that
will be our answer.
And multiply is similar, except we don't
have the one plus.
Because the multiply itself is not an ad.
And there's an example here of trying
that out as well.
And so what I want to leave you with, is
data types are useful for representing
lots of different kinds of data.
Particularly, these interesting tree like
structures, that we can then write
recursive functions over, to produce
answers, in terms of the answers for the
sub trees.