Okay.
What I want to do in this segment, is
give a general way to think about how to
build new types.
In fact this is going to be more general
than even in ML.
But we're going to be able to use this
idea, these concepts, to better
understand what it is we've been doing in
ML.
And what we're going to, going to
continue to be doing in the upcoming
segments.
So the way I want you to think about all
the types out there is that there are
base types and compound types.
So base types are things like int, bool,
unit, char, real that describes sort of
the basic values in your language.
And then compound types, are ways that
you build new types with other types
inside of them.
So tuples, are compound types because we
can take any t1 and t2 and make a pair of
a t1 and a t2.
Lists and options are also compound types
because we have a t list for some type t
or an option type for some type t.
And in the upcoming segments we're
going to learn new ways to make our own
compound types.
We're going to learn records, and we're
going to learn data types, which are even
more interesting.
But before we get there I want to take
this step back and basically tell you
that in any programming language there
are really three fundamental ways to
build compound types out of other types
that are part of the pieces and all
though these aren't the standard names
I'm going to call them each of, one of,
and self reference.
So when you build an each of type, the
entire idea is to build a new type T
where values of type T have each of some
other collections of type.
So if it were a triple with a T1, a T2,
and a T3,
that would be an each of type because
values of that compound have a T1 and
they have a T2 and they have a T3.
Conversely, a one of type, is a type
where a value of the new type has either
a tau one or a tau of two, a T two, or a
T three for some collection of types.
I'll sometimes say tau, the Greek letter
that's closest to T for types, it's all
the same.
Okay?
And the third way you can build a new
type is with some notion of recursion.
So, if you just add each of and one of,
you can't describe things like list or
trees.
Because values of a list type include
other lists that are smaller.
And so you need some way to say an int
list is either the empty list or it's an
int and another int list.
So you need that self reference.
And what's remarkable is, once your
programming language supports some way to
do each of.
Some way to do one of,
and one way to do self reference,
you have an amazing way to describe a lot
of interesting data in terms of types.
And that's why pretty much every
programming language has some way to
build these kinds of compound types.
All right.
So in terms of examples we've seen, as I
mentioned tuples pretty directly capture
the idea of each of.
If you have int str boule that contains
an int and a boule.
Options really are a one of type, but
their a bit of a strange example, because
you either have something, or you don't.
So, there's always this or involved.
So, int option, either contains an int,
or it does not contain and int.
That's an or, there's no each over and
involved.
And then when we create a list it turns
out it uses all three building blocks.
So an int list, if you just say it out
loud has all three concepts.
An int list either contains an int and
another int list.
So that's each off in self reference.
Or it contains no data.
And that's the one of idea.
Alright and of course these things can
nest arbitrarily to let us describe
interesting shapes of data.
So there's an example here on the bottom
of the slide where either we have some
data or we don't and that data is
described by two things.
Either a pair of ints or nothing and a
list of a list of ints which itself can
be described in terms of each of, one of
and self reference.
So where we're going with this is I'm
about to show you how to another way to
build each of types in ML.
And that's going to be records.
Records are a lot like tuples,
except they have named fields instead of
a first position, a second position and a
third position.
And we're going to see, they're so much
like tuples, that we can describe tuples
in terms of records using this important
idea called syntactic sugar.
After that we're going to see a way to
build our own one-of types, so if you
look at that previous slide, we can build
our own each-of types with int str bool,
but for one-of types so far, we only have
options and lists.
ML has a great way to define our own
types that maybe say either you have an
end or you have a string.
We don't have a way to do that yet.
And once we have such types we need a way
to access the pieces.
And we're going to use what will probably
seem very unusual to you if you've only
programmed in Java or C or Python before.
And that's a thing called pattern
matching.
It's incredibly powerful.
And we'll get comfortable using it even
though it's not like anything you've seen
before.
And then much later in the course we'll
get around to object oriented
programming.
Because you might be thinking, wait a
minute,
I know how to program in Java, or C plus,
plus.
I've never seen one of types.
It turns out you have seen one of the
types,
but OOP, Object Oriented Programming,
does them in a very different way, using
sub-classes and sub-types.
It's a very elegant way.
In fact it's the exact opposite way that
languages like ML do it.
And once we've seen both we'll be able to
make that contrast.
And it's one of the most fun in general
takeaway lessons from the course.