Okay.
In this section, I want to talk about how
you can define your own data types that
are polymorphic.
So the reason why I'm doing this is I've
previously claimed that the options and
lists in ML aren't particularly special.
That they are themselves just data type
bindings.
And the only thing that's different that,
is that lists have slightly special
syntax where we have the colon, colon as
s constructor in the middle, and bracket,
bracket for the empty list.
But that's not exactly true, compared to
the data type bindings I've shown you so
far.
Because lists and options are things that
take type parameters.
So, list is not a type.
It's int list that is a type or string
list, or even int list, list which is
list's who's elements are lists who's
elements are ints.
So, list and option are not types,
they're type constructors, they're
something that take type parameters to
produce types.
And we've also seen functions that may or
may not be polymorphic.
So, a function like sum list has to take
a list of integers and add them all up to
produce an int.
But a function, like my favorite, append
is something that works for any type
alpha, and it takes a type alpha list,
and another type alpha list, and returns
an alpha list.
And I just say alpha instead of quote A
because that's the traditional way to
pronounce that.
So, it would be good language to design
to not have built-in things like lists
and options that can be polymorphic in
this way, and then have data-type
bindings that you can define that don't
have this facility.
So, it turns out that ML did the right
thing, it lets you define your own. And
this segment is going to show you how to
do that.
Now, this is optional in the sense of I
wanted to show this to you for
completeness, but the homework is not
going to require you to do this, and I'm
just doing this to finish the story of
how lists and options are not
particularly special.
Okay.
So, here's the syntax I haven't shown you
yet.
And that is that you can have one or more
type parameters between the word datatype
and the new type level binding your
introducing.
So this first line here on the slide is
exactly how options are defined in ML
before your program starts running.
And it just says that option is not a
type, it's something that given one type,
alpha or quote A, produces a type.
So int option is a type, string option is
a type, and so on.
And then, once we have that quote A, then
we can use it in the types of data that
our constructors carry. So, in
particular, we can have some of alpha,
some carries what ever type this
particular kind of option carries as its
parameter.
Similarly, larly, if we wanted to define
our own linked list, ignoring the special
syntax in ML, we have one type parameter,
alpha, and the cons case carries two
pieces of data, an alpha and then another
list.
But you can't just write My List here,
that's never a type.
We say that the rest has to be another
alpha My List,
alright?
So, you can even do things with multiple
type parameters, so this last example
here shows that.
It defines a particular kind of tree
where I have two constructors, internal
nodes and leaves.
And the leaves always carry something of
type quote B or beta, the second Greek
letter.
And the internal nodes always carry
something of type alpha and then two
other alpha beta trees. So, this is going
to be a binary tree where all of the
internal nodes can carry data of one type
and all the leaves can carry data of a
possibly different type.
Those two type parameters, alpha and
beta, can be the same or they can be
different.
Alright, so that's how you do it.
I have a bunch of code associated here
that you can mostly look at on your own.
So, I started by showing you some list in
append over ML's built in lists.
So some list here is going to have type
int list arrow int.
And the type checker will be able to
figure that out because it sees that
right here, you're taking an element of
the list x, and you're adding it to
something else.
And so the elements must have type int.
The result type must have type int both
because we have an addition here and
because we have a zero here in this other
branch, and zero has type int.
Append, on the other hand,
the type checker can see that we don't
need are list arguments, x's and y's, to
have any particular type.
They have to have the same type because
if you take an element of one and cons it
on to something that has to have the same
type, because we return something that is
wise,
these two lists better have the same type
because you can't mix and match elements
of different types.
And so, the type ends up being alpha
list, arrow alpha list, arrow alpha list,
which says that callers can use append
with lists of any type.
But the two types, the two arguments, x's
and y's, have to be lists with the same
element type.
Alright.
Then, I have the data type bindings I
just showed you here on this slide.
And then, down here using our own
polymorphic data type, this alpha beta
tree I showed you where the leaves have
one type and the internal nodes have data
of possibly a different type, I wrote
three different functions.
This first one, sum tree runs over the
entire tree adding up everything at every
position.
So, if you have a leaf, we pattern match
on that here and we just return the data
there, this i.
If we have an internal node we add i to
the result of recursively summing the
left child and recursively summing the
right child, these left and right fields
of the data.
And so, everything has to have type int.
And so, the type checker will indeed
figure out, if you run this code, that
the argument has to be an int comma int
tree.
That only trees where both alpha and beta
are int can be legal to pass through the
sum tree function and get a reasonable
answer.
This is a much more interesting function
from the type perspective, although it's
probably less useful.
What it does is it also takes a tree, but
it only adds up all of the integers at
the leaves.
So, if you look in the node case here,
what the right hand side does is it just
calls some leaves on left and some leaves
of right.
It doesn't actually use the data at that
node.
And so indeed, the type checker will
notice that the legal types of trees you
can pass the sum leaves are anything
where the beta is int and the alpha can
be anything.
So, some leaves can be polymorphic.
It works for any kind of tree where beta
is int,
and then it returns an int.
And finally, if you did it something even
more general like just count how many
leaves a tree has.
So now, we're not using any of the
internal data.
We're not using this i I and we're not
using this i.
We just count by in the base case
returning one, and in the internal node
case summing the number of leaves on the
left and the number of leaves on the
right. Now, any kind of tree is a legal
argument, and indeed the type of num
leaves will be alpha beta tree arrow int.
Okay.
So that's fairly fancy type system.
As I mentioned, we're not going to get
into our own polymorphic data types in
homework two. But, it's interesting to
notice that the way we used constructors
and case expressions was exactly as
usual.
Nothing about the code we wrote was any
different, nothing about the evaluation
rules were any different.
The only differences in the type checking
were now the type checker has a much more
interesting job of making sure that types
are used consistently. So, even though a
list or a tree may be polymorphic,
you still have to, you can't mix element
types in a particular data structure.
And then, how polymorphic your functions
are, how many of those quote A's as and
quote B's appear in the type depend on
how the data is used. And that's why we
see things like summing the elements of a
list requiring a list of ints, but
something like append working for lists
of any type.