[MUSIC]
Okay, welcome to one of my favorite
segments in the entire course,
whereby extending our definition of
pattern-matching just a little bit,
we're gonna learn the truth about
a lot of what we've been doing.
So what we're about to find out is that
we've been using a lot more syntactic
sugar in our ML programs
than we even realized.
That in fact, every value binding and
every function binding can
use pattern-matching, and
that in ML, as a result,
every function takes exactly one argument.
Not zero, not two, not three.
And this is a very flexible,
elegant way to design your language.
But before we get to
that great punch line,
I need to extend our definition
of pattern-matching a little bit.
So so far, we used pattern-matching only
on our one of types, on our data type
bindings, and that's because we
needed some way to access the values.
The only way we could take something
that had one of our data type types,
see which constructor it was built from,
and
get the underlying pieces out,
was with pattern-matching.
And that's still the case, but
it turns out that pattern-matching
also works for each-of types.
It works for records, and since tuples
are always just syntactic sugar for
records, it works for tuples as well.
So let me tell you how that works, and
then I'll show you a number of examples
which we'll use in increasingly
good style as we go along.
So here's a new kind of pattern.
What you can do,
is in a place where you put a pattern,
you can put a tuple pattern, which looks
a little bit like a tuple expression,
except between the commas
we have variables.
And what that's going to do, is if you
pattern match one of those expressions
against a tuple value, it will bind.
It will introduce a local variable where
x1 is the first component of the tuple,
x2 is the second component
of the tuple and so on,
up to xn being matched against
the last component of the tuple.
And the type checker will insist that the
number of pieces of your tuple correspond
to the number of variables
in your pattern.
You're not allowed to mess that up.
Similarly for records, we have a new kind
of pattern where you write field name
equal variable name,
separated by commas inside of braces, and
that matches a record value that
has those same field names.
As usual the order of the field
names doesn't matter.
And what happens when you do this match,
is the variable x1 will be bound to
the value in the f1 field,
x2 in the f2 field, and so on, all right?
So that was a little abstract,
let's see some examples.
This is poor style, but it helps explain
how the pattern-matching works, and
we'll get to the better
style in just a second.
So first, suppose I had a triple,
a threetuple, where each component
was an integer, and I just want a little
function to add those three numbers up.
So what I could do,
is I could have a function sum_triple,
that took in some argument,
call it triple.
Then I could have a case
expression where my pattern
matches against tuples
that have three parts.
And in fact, since I use x, y, and z to
bind to the corresponding three pieces
of data inside that triple, I can use
those variables on the right-hand side,
and since I add them together,
those pieces must all have type int.
And so the type of sum_triple is int
star int star int, the type of three,
in tuples holding three integer things,
and the return type is int, all right?
And similarly here's a function full_name.
It takes a record where you have
fields first, middle, and last.
Here I'm concatenating them all.
This caret character is ML's operator for
concatenating strings, so
in fact, the three fields are going
to have to hold data of type string.
And this pattern here is extracting,
it's binding to x whatever is in the first
field, binding to y whatever
is in the middle field,
and binding to z whatever
is in the last field.
So we're using pattern-matching
to get the pieces out,
we're just doing it on each-of types,
instead of one of types.
Okay, so
now let me tell you another feature that
gives us a better way to write this down.
So it turns out, ever since
the very beginning of section one,
I told you that val-bindings were written
by val variable name equals expression.
And it turns out that's true,
but it's not the whole truth.
That what you can actually write
is val pattern equals expression,
and variables are just a special kind
of pattern, where the variable matches
against the entire result of
evaluating the expression e.
But if you put a different pattern there,
then it will match against the expression
e as well, and extract the various pieces.
This is great for
extracting the pieces of an each-of type,
you can even only get some of
the pieces out that you need.
It's bad style to do this where that e
is one of the constructors
of a data type binding.
And the reason is, this is gonna
be like a one-arm case expression,
a case expression with only one branch.
That's great for each-of types,
cuz you only want one branch, but for
data types you really want
all the different branches.
If you just put one here, you will get
an error at run time if you're wrong,
and you're giving up the advantage of
using case expressions where the type
checker makes sure you cover
all the possibilities.
Okay, so
here's how our examples would look now.
Instead of using a one-arm
case expression,
which is bad style,
let's use a let expression instead.
So now my function sum_triple is
gonna take in this triple, and
what I'm gonna do is pattern match
it with this val binding here.
So that will indeed evaluate triple.
It will look up triple in a dynamic
environment, it's gonna get some value,
and it's gonna make sure that x is bound
to the first piece, y to the second piece,
z to the third piece.
Then x, y and z will all be local
variables that are in scope in this let
expression, and I can add them together.
So the type checker will make sure that
indeed triple is a tuple with three parts,
all of type int,
because otherwise the rest of this
expression wouldn't type check.
And my full_name function works similarly,
except now I have a record pattern, and
since I'm concatenating x, y, and
z, r has to be a record that has
exactly the fields first, middle,
and last, all holding strings.
So this is actually quite nice style, but
I'm gonna show you something even better.
So here's the final version of how
I wanna write these things, and
I have to tell you one
more truth about ML.
It turns out that a function argument can
be a pattern and not just a variable.
So the same way I used to tell you
that function bindings looked like
name of function variable equals body,
it turns out what goes right
there is actually a pattern.
Again if it's just a variable,
it's gonna be matched against the entire
argument to the function, but
if it's a pattern, we'll go ahead and
extract pieces of the argument.
So now what I have are these
beautiful functions.
Sum_triple takes an argument that
will then be pattern-matched
against this tuple pattern, binding x to
the first piece, y to the second piece, z
to the third piece, and then the body can
do whatever it wants, add them together.
Full names similarly,
will have to be passed something
that can match against this pattern.
Only record expressions with first, middle
and last fields will match appropriately,
and since x, y and
z are used as strings in the body,
the type checker will require full_name
to take a record where first, middle,
and last all hold values of type string,
okay?
So now that we can do this, and
now that we have pattern-matching for
extracting pieces of tuples and
records, we can write this much
more concise, elegant, simple code.
And to make sure you get practice with
this, we're gonna have a rule on Homework
2, which says that you're not allowed
to use anything with the # character,
this pound character on your keyboard,
Shift+3 for me.
That's how we used to get pieces of
tuples out, with hash one and hash two,
how we used to get pieces of records
out with hash fieldname, but
on Homework 2 we want you to instead
always use pattern-matching,
cuz that's what we're working on.
And one of the nice benefits, is because
you're writing down these patterns,
the type checker will always be able
to figure out the type of thing you're
matching against, so you will no longer
need to write down any explicit types for
the arguments to your functions or any
other variables that you're using, okay?
So now that we know how to do this,
let me switch over to the code and
show you something really interesting.
So here in the file I have the three
versions of both full_name and
sum_triple we've been working on.
So this first version is bad style cuz it
uses one-armed branches which don't make
a lot of sense.
The second version is okay because
it uses a val binding instead,
and then this third version is
the simple one where in fact,
we put the pattern directly
in the function argument.
Now these are just three ways of
implementing the same thing, so
one is really syntactic sugar if you like,
for another.
So if I go over here and run this, or
at least load all these things in,
you'll see that
all three versions of sum_triple have type
give me a tuple that takes three ints and
returns an int, and that's the type of all
three versions of sum_triple you see here.
And similarly for full_name, they
always take in a record of first, last,
middle, string and return a string.
And indeed, these are three ways
of writing the same thing, so
you get a 12 if you do it that way,
and I'll try one other here.
You get a 12 if you do it this way.
So in all cases take a triple,
return an int.
But, I hope some of you are almost
ready to jump out of your chair saying,
wait a minute, wait a minute,
wait a minute,
let's look at this third possibility here,
this sum_triple.
That looks to me like a function
that takes three arguments.
That's how we used to write things
that take three arguments, and
now you're telling me that it's a function
that takes one triple as an argument, so
how can ML tell which
of it I'm trying to do?
When I define the function there and
also, oh sorry,
when I call it as I meant to here with
the third version, not the first one,
how does it know to pass in one triple and
pattern match against it,
instead of passing in three arguments,
a 3, a 4, and a 5, okay?
So let me put this another way.
Here on the top of the slide is a function
that takes one triple of type int*int*int,
and returns an int, and
it does it via pattern-matching,
as I've just taught you in this segment.
Here on the bottom, is a function
that like we learned a long time ago,
takes three arguments, x, y, and z,
and adds them together and returns it.
So if you see some difference
between the top half and
the bottom half, you're seeing something I
don't, because they're exactly the same.
And in fact, Every function in ML
takes one argument, not three, and
we've actually been using pattern-matching
all along, I just didn't tell you.
So here is the big truth.
In ML, every function takes
exactly one argument, and
what we have been calling
multi-argument functions are really
just functions that take one
argument that is a tuple.
And those functions are implemented by
using pattern-matching on that tuple so
that you get the different
pieces of that tuple out.
This is extremely elegant and
flexible, and I'm not gonna kid you.
Everyone when they talk about ML code,
talks about a multi-argument function,
a three argument function,
a four argument function, and so on.
But we know that what's really
going on in terms of the language,
is that that's just syntactic sugar.
We're passing one argument that
is a tuple, and then we're using
pattern matching to get the pieces out,
and this is actually a useful thing to do.
So I have a short example here on
the slide that I'll use to finish up
this segment.
Here is a very simple program
to rotate the pieces of a tuple.
So how about I just implement that
real fast over here, rotate_left
(x,y,z) = (y,z,x), all right?
So now if I call rotate_left (3,4,5),
and I actually spell it correctly,
I get (4,5,3), all right?
So I took in some tuple, and I returned
a tuple, and that's all great, but
what I could do is I could take that
thing that was returned, and pass it into
another function, like rotate_left,
in which case I would get (5,3,4),
or directly into say sum_triple3,
in which case I should still get
12 because the order doesn't matter
when you're summing things up.
This is something you can't do in
a lot of programming languages.
It's usually very awkward to return
multiple things from one function, and
immediately pass them to another,
but in ML every function takes and
returns one argument.
Rotate_left takes one
triple as an argument, so
if I have some expression that returns
a triple, like rotate_left does,
I can immediately take that thing and
pass it to another function.
So I have another example
here on the slide which is,
I could write a rotate_right function
that takes in some triple t,
and just implements it by
rotate_left(rotate_left t),
cuz it turns out if you have a triple,
two left rotations is one right rotation.
So it's a silly example, but
it's nonetheless an elegant example of how
having this policy of every function takes
and returns one argument, it becomes much
easier to take the results of one function
and pass them directly to another.
So now we know the truth
about ML functions.
Everything takes one argument.
This is one of those great segments where
we made our language bigger by adding new
kinds of patterns,
pattern-matching over each-of types, but
as a result we made our language smaller,
because we now know that there's no need
to have a special concept of
multi-argument functions.