[MUSIC]
In this segment, I want to talk a little
bit about type inference and then, we'll
continue this discussion the next segment
about one type being more general than
another.
We're going to study type inference a
little later in the course and understand
how ML actually does it, but I need to
tell you a little bit about it now so
that you're not concerned on your next
homework if you're getting some types
back from ML that might surprise you in
certain ways.
So, as I mentioned, once we learned how
to pattern match on each of types,
in the second homework, we don't want you
to use the hash character.
We don't want you to say hash two or hash
foo to get the foo field out of a record.
And conversely, now in ML, once we stop
using the hash character, we don't have
to write down types on any of our
function arguments anymore or on any of
our variable bindings or anything else.
And it turns out these things are
related.
That once you use pattern matching for
getting the pieces of a tuple or a
record,
the type checker can always figure out
what the type of a function argument
should be.
So, let me show you how that works mostly
by showing you code.
Here are two functions we've seen before.
Our old friends for summing a triple.
Take in a single triple x, y, z to
pattern-matching against the three parts
and sum them up.
Or take in a record here, with first,
middle, and last fields, bind those
fields x, y, and z and then concatenate
them together with some blank spaces in
between.
So, if I just run this and, load this up
we will see, as we've seen before, that
the type checker can figure out that
sum_triple1 needs to have type int * int
* int arrow int.
You can tell it's a triple, because it's
x, y, z.
You can tell they have to be ints because
x, y, and z are added together.
Similarly, full name has to be a record
with first, last, and middle fields.
And those contents have to be strings
because in the body, we concatenate them.
And then, the result type of full name
one is of type string.
So, these patterns told the type checker
most of what it needed to know.
And then how the variables were used
showed the rest.
So, let me show you that if you use
instead hash characters, the type checker
does not have as much information.
Now, these versions, sum_triple2 and
full_name2, which use hash characters the
old fashioned way, will work, and they
will work just fine.
So, let me quickly go over here, and just
show you that, that if I reuse them, they
work just fine and we get the correct
types for sum_triple2 and full_name2 but
if I took out these types, and let me
just do this for the first one here and
try that again,
I now get a compilation error message,
unresolved flex record, need to know the
names of all the fields, blah, blah,
blah.
And the reason why the ML type checker is
complaining is it looks at this
sum_triple, and it can tell the triple
here needs to be a tupple with at least
three fields where the contents are type
int.
But how does it know that there isn't a
fourth position, or a fifth position, or
a sixth position?
It doesn't.
And every type system has certain
limitations.
And in ML, one of those limitations, is
you can't write a function that takes on
both three tupples and four tupples.
And so, since the type checker can't
figure out how wide the tupple supposed
be, you get an error message.
And that's why this simply doesn't type
check and why, in homework 1, we made you
write those types down.
Alright.
So, that's fine.
That's an advantage of not using hash.
But now, let me show you something that
you may trip across in homework 2 and so
its important that we tell you about it,
okay?
So, here are a couple of functions that
don't use all the pieces that were
pattern-matching against.
So this function partial sum adds
together x and z and doesn't use y.
And, similarly, this name function
concatenates the first and last name but
doesn't use the middle name,
alright?
So, if told you on your homework, say, to
write a function of type int * int * int
arrow int, that indeed had the behavior
of adding the first position in the third
position, you would probably write
exactly this code.
And then, you would save it.
And then, you would come over here and
you would run this.
And you would see that the type of
partial sum is int * alpha * int arrow
int.
And you would say, oh no, I wanted an int
* int * int arrow int, and what I got was
an int * alpha * int arrow int.
And what I want to tell you is, that's
okay.
That sometimes, the type checker is
perhaps a little bit smarter than you
are, and in looking at your functions,
decides they are more general, more
reusable than you expected.
And indeed, if you look at this, it
worked just fine to call partial sum with
three integers.
It's a polymorphic function that works
for a tuple where the middle position has
any type, and indeed, we can call partial
sum with 3, 4, 5 and get eight, but we
could also call it with a string in
there, and that will also type check.
It would not work to put that string in
the last position,
alright?
That doesn't type check, and that's
because if you look at the code, the last
part does have to be an int, because we
add it.
So, whenever this happens, and it often
happens when you're not using part of
your argument, you'll end up with a more
general type than you might expect.
And that is okay,
alright?
I sometimes call this unexpected
polymorphism,
alright?
If your function is correct, and you
still need to test it, you still need to
make sure that it does work for the types
that it is required to work for.
Then, if it also works for values of
other types,
well, that's just a useful thing.
And we don't need to worry about the type
that ML gave us as long as it's more
general than what we needed.
Now, hopefully this idea of more general
is intriguing to you, and you'd like to
learn, hey, given two types, how can I
tell if one is more general than another?
And I can give you precise rules for
doing that and I'll do it in the next
segment.