[MUSIC]
In this segment, I want to continue our
discussion of how ML's polymorphism allows
some types to be more
general than other types.
And then also point out this strange
feature of ML, equality types,
that you might accidentally run across on
homework two, and it's okay if you do.
So, to take a simple example, suppose that
you were required on a homework
assignment, or just as part of your job,
to write an ML function that took two list
of strings and appended them together.
And you went off and you wrote a wonderful
function for append like you see here.
And you expected it to have type string
list * string list -> string list, but
as we've seen code like this in
fact gets a polymorphic type
of alpha list * alpha list -> alpha list.
This is okay, your job is done and
we want to talk about why.
Now we already know the informal story
that if you do write this code and
it has this type, you'll be able to
call a pen with two lists of strings and
get back a list of strings
that has four elements in it.
Or, even though this wasn't part of your
job, you could call with two list of ints.
But what you couldn't do is call
the list of ints and a list of strings.
And in fact you can tell
that just from the type,
because what I want to convince you of is
that even though this quote a this alpha,
can be any type, it has to be the same
type throughout the overall types.
So these three uses of alpha have to be
replaced consistently with some type,
whether it's an int or string or
pair of ints or whatever you'd like.
So let me explain how that works,
in general.
We can say that the type alpha list
* alpha list -> alpha list is more
general than the type string list
* string list -> string list, and
in fact this polymorphic type can
be used at any less general type.
So it could also be used at int list
* int list -> int list, but it is not
more general than something where
the first alpha is replaced by int and
the second alpha is replaced by string and
the third alpha is replaced by int.
Because we did not replace
alpha consistently.
So the general rule is,
a type t1 is more general than a type t2.
If you can take t1,
replace it's type variable consistently so
every alpha replace with one type, every
beta with another type either the same or
different with what you replaced
alpha with and so on to get t2.
So you can replace alpha with int * int,
you can replace alpha with bool and
beta with bool.
You can replace alpha with bool and
beta beta with int.
You could even replace each beta with
alpha and each alpha with alpha.
And I don't have an example of that here
but you could take a really polymorphic
function and come up with a different
type that was a bit less general but
still had some polymorphism in it, okay.
So that is what we have been doing.
Let me now combine this with a couple
other rules I have told you about before.
Remember our whole idea that
if you see type synonyms,
it doesn't matter whether you see the type
name or what it's a synonym for, and
remember that with record types
the order of the field doesn't matter.
So, here's an example on the slides,
supposed I have some types synonyms
where type foo = int * int.
And supposed that you write some homework
function and the type you get for
some part of it, is some record type,
where I have a quux field of type beta,
a bar field of type int * alpha,
and a baz field of type beta.
Now, the question is,
is that more general than this type here,
the second record type
you see on this slide?
Because if I asked for
this second one, and
you wrote something of the type first one
and it's more general, then that's okay.
And it turns out that it is, because for
this record type to be more general than
in the next one, it has to have
all the same fields, and it does.
It has quux, bar, and baz, quux, bar,
and baz, and each field of the less
general line has to be created by this
sort of consistent instantiation.
And every beta has been
replaced by string and
then there's bar field is even more
interesting, if you replace the alpha with
int and it's the only alpha, so
we are replacing the alphas consistently.
You would get int * int and
since foo is the same thing as int * int,
indeed this second type is less
general than the first type.
Another thing that is less general than
the first type is this written here.
It turns out this last type is absolutely
equivalent to the middle type.
It has all the same fields, and
all those fields have the same type.
The only difference is, I've re-ordered
the fields, which never matters,
and I've replaced the foo for
the type of bar with int * int.
So, this is the sort of thing you
might have to do on homework two,
that ML type checker tells you one thing
and you'll have to check using your own
brain that it's more general than
the type that you needed to produce.
So, that's one thing that
you might trip across,
here's an even somewhat stranger thing.
You might see some types that have
two quotes before a type variable.
So ' ' a instead of just ' a.
So for example, here's a type that says
I take an alpha list and an alpha and
return a bool, but these alphas have
this extra apostrophe at the beginning.
What that means is that
these are equality types.
So indeed a function of this
type is polymorphic, but
you can't replace the quote quote
alpha with any type you want.
You can only replace it with types that
you can use the equals operator on.
Now we have mostly only used the equal
operator for int, to compare to ints, or
for string to see if they are the same
strings, but it turns out it works for
a lots of types.
It works for
tuples as long as all the pieces of
the tuples are themselves equality types.
But not everything is an equality type,
it turns out that ML in order to enforce
good style doesn't let you compare values
of type real floating point numbers with
equals, because that's pretty
much always a bad idea, and
doesn't let you compare
function types with equals.
Something that will get
into in subsequent segments
when we're passing functions
to other functions and stuff.
So, the rules are exactly the same.
If you see a type like this, it works for
any type as long as you instantiate
the alpha consistently.
But certain instantiations
won't be allowed.
So this is a rather strange feature of ML.
It basically treats this equal operator
specially, has special support in the type
system for things that can be
compared with the equals operator.
And it's not something that I plan to
study in depth, but in case you see it,
I wanted to prepare you for it.
Here's a very short example
of how it may come up.
Suppose you wrote this function,
which is takes an x and a y, and
if they're the same turns the string yes,
or else is string no, and
maybe you thought you were intending x and
y to type int, but instead,
you will get a type like
' ' a * ' ' a -> string.
You would also get a warning from the ML
type checker about calling polyEqual.
You can ignore that warning.
But you might not ever
see this sort of warning.
So here's the second function that uses
the equals operator on this argument x.
But since it compares x to 3,
the type checker knows that you can only
ever compare two things of the same type.
That's the typing rule for equals.
So in fact x has to have type int.
You would see that over all this
function has type int error string,
because it must take an int and
it must return a string, and
there is nowhere we had equality
types anywhere to be seen.
So those are the strange
things to look for.
There's a very nice precise rule of one
type being more general than another, and
you'll now get a lot less confused
if you see unexpected polymorphosis
on your next homework