In this segment, I want to start talking
about nested patterns.
This is going to generalize everything
we've been learning about pattern
matching, by doing a very simple thing
which is letting us put patterns inside
of other patterns, and then extending our
definition of pattern matching to account
for that.
So it turns out that we can nest patterns
as deep as we want.
Everywhere we have been putting variables
in patterns we can actually put other
patterns.
This corresponds to the idea that when
we're making expressions, we can always
put nested expressions anywhere we want.
We don't have to write x plus y.
We can write expressions in those
positions.
We're going to be able to do the same
thing with patterns, and what this will
let us do is avoid hard to read case
expressions that have other case
expressions inside of them, and instead,
let us write something very elegant and
easy to read programs.
So it turns out the full meaning of
pattern matching, is going to be a
recursive definition, that's going to
take the idea of a pattern that can
contain other patterns, and a value that
can contain other values, and see if the
value has the same shape described by the
pattern, and if so, bind variables to the
right parts.
But I think it will be easier to see
several examples over the next couple
segments, before we get to that precise
elegant recursive definition.
So what I want to do in this segment is
show one nice example which relates to
zipping and unzipping.
So to explain what zipping and unzipping
is I have written a function zip3 and its
reverse, its inverse, unzip3 that work
like the following.
If I call zip three with a triple of
lists, so three arguments, each of which
was a list, say an a list of integers,
although this function it turns out this
function is polymorphic, what I get back
is one list containing triples.
So it went from three lists to one list
of triples and what it did is it put
corresponding pieces together.
So in the arguments the first elements
here are one, four, and seven, and in the
result the first element is a triple of
one, four, and seven.
Similarly we then see two, five, and
eight, and then three, six, and nine.
And unzip does the reverse,
it takes a list of triples and returns
three lists.
Where each list contains first all the
first positions from the tuples, then all
the second positions from the tuples, and
then all the third positions from the
tuples.
So by the way the reason why this is
called zip and unzip is that it acts a
little bit like a zipper, like on your
shirt or you know, on a bag or something,
because zip, takes these separate things
and puts them next to each other and
unzip, takes something that was all
together and separates it out.
I wouldn't look at your zipper too
closely though.
Because when you actually zip, the teeth
do not end up next to each other.
They end up adjacent, but the intuition
is right.
Okay,
so that's what I want these functions to
do.
Let's see how we might implement them.
And to give you some contrast here let me
start by showing you how we would do it
if we didn't have pattern matching.
So here is one way to zip together three
lists, so it's a function using our old
features, old zip three.
It takes in three arguments, L1, L2, and
L3, and if they are all empty.
L1 is null, L2 is null, L3 is null.
Then let's return the empty list.
L's if any of them are empty our lists
don't have the same length and I'm going
to call that an error and I'll raise a
run time exception I will show you in a
few segments how to raise exceptions but
this is how you do it I've declared an
exception up here and I'll raise it.
Otherwise I have three non-empty lists.
If I have three non-empty lists, let's
create a couple out of the head of L1,
head of L2 and head of L3 and cons that
onto the result of zipping tail of L1,
tail of L2 and tail of L3.
Okay, so that's zipping.
I prefer pattern matching.
this is pretty easy to get wrong.
you could easily miss some cases, you're
getting no help from the type checker.
But if you go to use pattern matching the
way you've been using it so far, it's
frankly a bit of a mess.
So, here is a version that uses pattern
matching.
And let's see, so let's first deal with
the case that all three lists are empty.
Well I'd have to prod a match on L1 and
then if its empty see if L2 is empty and
then if its empty see if L3 is empty.
And aha if I get here then all three
lists are empty and so I should return
the empty list.
In, in otherwise L3 is not empty but L1
and L2 are, so I should raise an
exception.
Otherwise, L1 is empty but L2 is not, and
I need to raise an exception.
Otherwise, L1 is not empty, so it
patterns match head1 and tail1 and then
if L2 is empty then raise an exception.
And you see where this is going, I, I'm
exploring all possibilities of empty and
non-empty rather than the convenience up
above of and, also and or, else.
So it turns out the fix for this is not
to abandon pattern matching but to use
the fact that patterns can appear inside
of other patterns.
So now let's look at how I like to write
zip three.
Here is a nice concise function zip
three.
It takes one argument, just like every
function in ml.
Let's call it list triple, you can call
it anything you like.
And let's pattern match on this triple of
lists.
And let's consider three patterns.
The first pattern is this one.
This is a pattern where I have a pattern
for a tupple with three patterns for
lists inside of it.
And what this is going to match is any
value that is a triple of three empty
lists.
So if list triple, is all empty, then
this pattern will match, and I'll return
the empty list.
Now let's look at the next pattern.
This pattern also matches triples.
Here's before the first comma.
Here's, after the, before the second
comma.
Here's after the second comma.
Each thing in it has to be a non-empty
list.
Why?
Because this is a nested pattern that
matches against non-empty lists.
Just like this one is, and this one is.
So the overall pattern will only match
list triple if list triple,
is something that is a triple containing
three non empty lists.
And if it matches I will bind six
variables head one tail one head two tail
two head three and tail three.
Head one, head two, and head three will
be bound to the beginning elements of the
three lists.
And tail one, tail two, and tail three to
the tails of the three lists.
And what I want to do over here, is the
very elegant call cons with the triple
made from head one, head two, and head
three, recursively call zip three with
tail one, tail two, and tail three.
So here is my pattern.
If it matches, here is my expression.
And it actually looks like I'm zipping it
up.
Create a tuple out of head one, head two,
and head three, recursively zip three
with tail one, tail two, and tail three.
Now that does not cover all the cases.
I've covered the cases where everything
is empty and where the three elements are
non-empty.
Here's a new kind of pattern: underscore.
Underscore matches everything and doesn't
bind any variables.
And it turns out for zipping and all the
other cases, I just want to raise an
exception.
So if the first pattern doesn't match and
the second pattern doesn't match, then I
want this third case.
The typechecker warned me that I want
this case because my first two patterns
don't cover all the possibilities.
So I really like writing programs like
this.
zipping is one great example, there are
other examples that work as well.
And for this segment let's finish up with
unzipping and then I'll show you some
other examples in the next one.
So in unzipping I want to take an
argument which is already a list of
triples.
And I want to return three lists.
So now my pattern matching is going to be
a little bit simpler.
If this argument list is empty, then I
want to return three empty lists.
That is how you unzip the empty list.
You return three lists all of which are
empty.
Otherwise, I want to pattern match
against a non empty list now we use to
just do this as something like head colon
tail or x colon exes, alright.?
But what you can do is you can nest these
patterns as well.
You can say, sure, I want to pattern
match
the rest of the list against this tl
variable, it has nothing to do with this
tail function.
I'm just shadowing it with a tl variable.
But I want to match the head of the list
against this eachof pattern, against this
tuple pattern.
So, if this pattern matches, then a will
be the first component of the head of the
list, b will be the second component of
the head of the list, and c will be the
third component of the head of the list,
and tail will be bound to the rest of the
list,
okay?
These are the only two possibilities I
have to account for.
Because any list of triples will either
match this pattern, or will match this
pattern.
And the type of unzip three is going to
require list to be a list of triples.
Okay,
so once I've bound these four variables.
Let's look at this expression.
Let us recursively call upzip three on
the tail that's going to give me back
three lists.
Let's use ordinary each of pattern
matching to bind those three lists to L1,
L2, and L3.
And now I'm basically done, because I
have the three lists for unzipping the
tail.
I have A, B, and C for the three
components of the head of the list and
now I just want to return the triple
expression that A cons on to L1, B cons
on to L2, C cons on the L3 and now.
Using the idea of nested pattern
matching, I've in what, less than ten
lines of code, written elegant and
concise, easy to read, zipping and
unzipping for three lists.
This is a bit of an advanced example for
nested pattern matching, but it uses all
the features that I want to show you.
Then in the next segment I'll show you a
couple other situations, common idioms,
where nested patterns are extremely
useful.