I want to wrap up our discussion of
pattern matching by giving a precise
definition of when a pattern matches a
value.
And this is a bit more complicated now
that we have nested patterns but it leads
to a very natural and elegant recursive
definition.
So just to be clear, what I'm doing here
is describing the semantics, the
evaluation rules for the part of pattern
matching where you have a pattern and you
have a value and you want to know whether
they match or not.
So for example the value would be the
result of the expression between the word
case and the word of.
And then the patterns would be each
branch of the case expression in order.
Now these rules also applied when you had
patterns in function bindings or in
variable bindings, but the key issue is
here's a pattern, here's a value, do they
match, and if they do match, what
variables are introduced and what are
those variables bound to?
Okay?
So in the presence of nested patterns
this is a recursive definition and we
would have one case of this definition
for every way of writing down patterns.
So I haven't written an exhaustive list
here on the slide but I think by going
through these examples you'll get the
sense of it and you'll get a sense of how
pattern matching is itself in the
language definition a recursive
procedure.
So let's start with the base cases of
that recursion and that's when the
pattern is either a variable or that
wildcard, that underscore character.
So, we have a pattern, we have a value.
One case of our definition is the pattern
is a variable.
If that's the case, the match always
succeeds, no matter what the value is,
and we bind the variable to the entire
value v.
That makes sense.
The and, the underscore case, the
wildcard case, is exactly the same, the
match also always succeeds, and we don't
bind anything.
Okay, good the other cases are recursive,
they build out of the smaller nesting
patterns.
Those nested patterns might be base cases
like variables, that is how our we
started using pattern matching or they
could be nested patterns in which case
this recursive definition will apply.
So for example, suppose we have a tuple
pattern.
So we'll have some pattern of the form
P1, P2, up to PN.
Then that will only match values that are
also tuples with N values inside of them.
And it will only match if P1 matches V1.
P2 matches V2.
And so on, up to PN matching VN.
That recursive matching is appealing to
the same recursive definition.
So we would use a recursive call, if you
will, to the pattern match procedure.
Okay?
Now if all of those sub-patterns, those
nested patterns, match then they will all
introduce various bindings of variables
to values and the overall pattern will be
the union of all those bindings.
So all the variables introduced by P1,
all the variables introduced by P2 up to
all the variables introduced by PN.
The one extra rule in pattern matching is
you're never allowed to use a variable
more than once.
If you try to use the same variable more
than once in a pattern the compiler will
reject that and, and tell you directly
that you're not allowed to do that.
Let's do one more interesting case.
This is the case for when we're using a
constructor.
So on the slide there where you see that
capital c, assume that, that is one of
the constructors for some data type
that's been previously defined.
So one kind of pattern we can write down
is that constructor C, followed by a
nested pattern P1.
The nested pattern is often a tuple.
but it doesn't have to be.
It can be any kind of pattern.
Now, if we have a constructor with a
pattern underneath it.
The only thing that will match is a value
that was built out of the same
constructor.
And a value that matches the pattern.
So we need the same C an we also need p1
to match z one and then whatever variable
bindings are produced by the recursive
match of p1 matching v1 are the variable
bindings that we have for the larger
pattern c of p1 with the value c of v1.
So hopefully that gives you a sense of
how.
Pattern matching is a recursive
procedure.
an we can use this to understand much
better.
What it means when these nested patterns
are matching against, values of certain
shapes.
So here are three examples.
In the first example here, you see A.
the pattern.
A Cons onto B, cons onto C, cons onto D.
And if you follow the recursive
procedure.
Using colon, colon as a constructor.
What we have are the nest in pattern A
and then the nest in pattern B cons onto
c cons on to cons onto D and so on
recursively.
And what this will end up matching is any
list that has greater than or three
elements.
Because we will recursively match A
against the first element, B against the
second C against the third.
And then D against the rest of the list.
If the list is too short.
We'll end up trying to match the empty
list constructor value against the cons
constructor pattern, that simply fails to
match.
That's okay,
we would move to the next case.
The next branch in our case expression.
Then second pattern, A cons onto B, cons
onto C, cons onto empty list, would match
all lists with exactly three elements.
Matching A to the first ONP to the second
and C to the third.
If the list is too short, then just like
in the previous example, we'll have some
empty list value that fails to match.
If the list is too long, we'll end up in
the recursive position where we have the
empty list pattern trying to match
against a non empty list value, and that
will fail to match.
And then in this third example, we have
some more nested patterns, where we have
a cons constructor pattern with a
variable on the right, that's that
variable e, and then on the left we have
the sort of pattern that requires a pair
of two nested pairs.
So this will only match against a
non-empty list whose elements are pairs
of pairs.
And then we'll introduce five variable
binates.
So, that is our more precise definition.
Hopefully it gives you the sense that
pattern matching is not a fuzzy concept,
it's a very precise concept.
And that better explains, that more
completely explains examples we saw in
previous segments.