This is an optional segment, where I'm
going to show you one more way that you
can write down patterns, particularly
with functions.
This is a style that I've never
particularly liked.
But there's nothing wrong with it and
other people do like it.
So, if you want to use this, you can.
And if not, like I said, it's optional.
So, let me just shoe a couple examples by
showing you some code.
Remember this data type binding we had
for arithmetic expressions.
So, these are trees where the leaves are
constants and the internal nodes are
negations, additions or multiplications.
And the most natural function you would
want to write over such a data type is
something that evaluates it.
So, something of type x aero int where we
produce the result of evaluating the
arithmetic expression and we had this
great recursive function that uses
pattern matching with a case expression
to do that.
So it turns out there's another way you
can write functions where the function
body is just a case expression.
So if the entire function body is a case
expression, you can get rid of the case
expression by moving the patterns up into
the function binding.
So we already know that in fact, when you
write a function named F, you can follow
that with a P, any pattern you want
equals E.
But so far, we've only done that for each
O patterns, because you want that pattern
to match any value that might be passed
to the function.
But as you can see here with this other
version of eval you can in fact have
multiple.
Fun f p equal e.
But you don't for the subsequent ones
repeat the fun keyword instead you re you
write a pipe.
And then repeat the function name,
and then put a second pattern and a
second body.
So when you put all that together you end
up with fun eval first pattern, this.
Second pattern this.
Third pattern this.
It's shorter.
People also like that it's a little more
mathematical.
We're defining the function eval and it
has several cases.
Eval applied to a constant is this.
Eval applied to a negation is that.
And so on.
But it's just syntactic sugar for a case
expression.
So just to show you one more example, you
see down here at the bottom my favorite
example,
append.
And append is itself something whose body
was just a case expression, and now we
can use nested patterns to be able to do
this all at once.
We can say, append, if the two arguments
match this pattern, so the first list is
empty and the second list is any list
because anything matches the variable
pattern wise, then the result is wise.
Otherwise, if the two lists match these,
this pattern, then return X cons on to
append of X's prime, wise.
So that's another example.
This is another way to write append.
So just to generalize this and show you
what's going on over here in the slides.
In general, if you had a function
binding, where you had fun fx equals case
x of.
Patterns.
You can rewrite that as I've shown you by
writing multiple patterns repeating the
function name and putting pipes, so the
pipe character, between the different
versions if you prefer.
one little detail here.
This is, of course, assuming that you
don't need that variable X in any of your
branches.
You usually don't.
You usually pattern match it off in your
case expression and then just use the
variables that you bind in the variable
branches, various branches.
So that's your optional syntax if you
choose to use it.