In this segment we're going to talk about
exceptions, which are what you use when
you have a run time condition that should
be an error.
We'll talk about how to create
exceptions, how to raise them, which is
called throwing in many languages, and
how to handle them, which is called
catching in many languages.
And this is a reasonable place in the
course to put this, because the way ML
does exceptions is very similar to how it
does data type bindings although
exceptions are a separate concept.
So let's explain most of this with the
code and then we'll summarize what we see
with a couple of slides.
So first, let me show you how the
function head, is actually implemented.
So remember what head does, it takes a
list.
The list is not empty, it returns the
first element.
If it is empty, it ends up raising an
exception that happens to already be
defined and called list.empty.
So here is exactly how I expect the code
in out ML standard library to be
implemented.
Just as a case expression.
In the case of a non empty list, it
returns x.
But for the empty list, it uses this
raise key word, followed by the
exception.
And indeed, if we had a call of head with
the empty list, head would never return.
Because what raise does is cause an
exception to occur instead,
alright?
So list.empty was just defined by whoever
wrote ML standard library.
Not surprisingly, we can define our own
kinds of exceptions.
And what you do is you use the exception
keyword.
And then any name you want,
it's traditional to capitalize them.
So here, I've created an exception called
my undesirable condition.
You can see here a little bit lower that
having introduced that new exception
binding.
I'll be able to raise my undesirable
condition.
You can also create exceptions.
It carry values, the syntax is exactly
like with constructors.
So here's another exception, where my
another exception is not an exception.
It carrying a pair of ends would be.
So you would be able to ride something
like rays, might other exceptions of
three, four.
And that's a way to pass data out to
whoever might be handling your exception,
alright?
So at this point we've seen our first
piece of raise up here in head, we've
defined our own exceptions.
Now here's a function called my div, that
takes two integers and if the denominator
is zero, instead of raising whatever
normal exception ML raises in this
situation, we raise my undesirable
condition instead.
So that's really all there is to it.
Now there is one other distinction I'd
like to make.
There's a difference between making an
exception value, which is just something
of type exn, and raising it.
So here is a function max list which
takes in a list and an exception.
And, if the list is empty, it raises
whatever exception was passed in.
Otherwise, if the list has one element,
it just returns it.
Otherwise, it returns the max of the
first element, and the max of the rest of
the list.
So it's another nested pattern matching
example.
But the interesting thing here is that
the caller to max list passes in the
exception.
So max list, in fact, has type int list.
Star E X N, which is the type of all
exceptions, arrow int. because if it
doesn't return, it will return in int.
if it raises an exception who cares what
the return type is.
So, here I have a call to max list, where
I pass in the list three comma four comma
five and pass in this exception.
Now this is not going to cause an
exception to be raised, it's just an
exception value.
And since in this case max list won't
call use arrays with the exception no
exception occurs.
So if I run this code w will simply end
up being bound to five, the maximum
element in the list.
Alright?
So the last thing I want to show you with
exceptions, is how to handle them.
This is what a lot of languages call
catching an exception.
So anywhere you have, and there's a new
form of expression I just haven't shown
you before.
Anywhere you have an expression e1, you
can then write handle, some exception
name.
It's actually a pattern.
Some, exception thing.
And then some e2.
And what this is going to do is if E1
evaluates normally, then the rest is
irrelevant.
But if E1 raises the exception, listed
here.
Then we'll evaluate, we'll catch that
exception.
We'll evaluate E2 instead.
If this is not the same exception that E1
throws then we are not handling it.
And it continues, the result of the
entire thing is that the same exception
is raised.
So here is a perfectly reasonable example
of a handle expression.
But since the thing before the handle
does not raise an exception, this just
evaluates the five.
The result of this entire thing is just
going to be five.
Alright.
On the other hand.
If we had this code here, where we pass
max list, the empty list, then indeed max
list is going to end up evaluating,
raising, my undesirable condition, so we
will handle that exception, and the
result z, will end up being bound to 42.
This final example which is commented out
here, this, if we evaluate it, will in
fact raise the exception, so why we'll
never end up being pound to anything and
since we don't have a handle expression
here, the evaluation of our program would
stop and so that is why I have it
commented out, and so we can see all
these quickly, if we come over here and
just use this file .
We will see that I am right.
That w and x are both bound to five, and
z is bound to 42.
And no exceptions were raised.
Because the only one that happened, which
was up when we evaluated the expression
for x, we handled and decided to evaluate
the expression to 42 instead.
Okay so, let's switch back to the slides
and see whats going on in general.
We have a new kind of binding I had not
shown you before.
This is an exception binding, this is how
you introduce a new kind of an exception.
We have a new keyword I hadn't shown you
before, raise, this is how you raise or
throw an exception.
And we have another new expression form
for handling or catching exceptions.
Where we evaluate the expression to the
left of the keyword handle, if that does
not raise an exception then that's our
answer.
If it does raise an exception and that
exception matches the one we have there,
then we evaluate E2, otherwise we
continue to raise the exception.
So, it turns out that exceptions are a
lot like data type constructors, that
there is this built in type EXN.
Over here in the code you'll notice that
max list does have type int list star
EXN, error int,
alright?
So when you add a new kind of exception,
you're really just adding a new
constructor of type EXN.
So EXN is just a normal type, which is
why we can pass values of type EXN, like
we did, into Maxlist.
It's not too common to do this.
But it's useful.
It does let your caller choose what
exception you raise.
Which seems like a potentially useful
thing to do.
And it turns out that handle expressions
are more general than I've been showing
you here.
You, in fact, can use pattern matching as
deep as you want on those things of type
EXN.
And you can even have multiple branches
separated, by the pipe character.
Okay, but nonetheless I've shown you
enough basics.
You'll use exceptions just a little bit
on your homework to make sure you
understand how they work and how they can
be used.
And now you know how they work.