In this segment, I want to continue our
discussion of tail-recursion and show you
the common pattern of how we create
tail-recursive functions and the role
that accumulators play in that process.
So, what I'm trying to emphasize is that
when we have tail recursion, we do have
significantly more efficient functions.
So, if it's reasonably eloquent, if it's
simple, and if performance is important,
it can be worth rewriting your function
to be tail-recursive.
So a tail-recursive function is just one
where all the recursive calls are
themselves tail calls.
So we have this situation where when we
do the recursion, there is no more work
for the caller to do after the recursive
call is done.
And it turns out there is a methodology
that can often guide this transformation,
a way for you to take your code and make
it tail-recursive.
And that is to create a helper function
that takes an accumulator, something that
combines answers as you go along to hold
the answers so far.
And what typically happens, is the old
base case from your recursion is your
initial accumulator.
And,
in the recursive accumulator style
function, your final result is just your
accumulator and it turns out that this
works anytime that you can combine your
results in essentially any order, in
order to get the same result.
So, in our previous example where we had
factorial, that's indeed the case.
It doesn't matter to us what order we
multiply all these numbers, three times
two times one or one times two times
three,
and therefore, this transformation worked
just fine.
So indeed, if you think of factorial in
your head as multiply n by the recursive
factorial of n minus one, that's the
traditional version.
But the tail-recursive version, which we
have here,
uses our methodology.
We have a local helper function aux that
takes an extra argument, the accumulator.
The initial accumulator in this call here
between the in and the n passes in one
which used to be our base case.
And then, in the tail-recursive helper
function, our base case when n equals
zero is to just return the accumulator.
And so, we are still recursively aux ox
each time with n minus one, but we're
multiplying numbers as we go so when we
get to zero, the accumulator is our
answer and that's why this worked out.
So let me show you two more examples,
the second one will actually be more
interesting.
The first example is just summing all the
elements in the list.
It turns out that at the top, we've
written functions like this many times,
this not a tail-recursive function.
In the recursive call here, where we call
sum with xs' prime,
the caller still has work to do after
this call finishes.
We need to add x, to that result.
But our methodology will work here,
because we don't care what order we sum
numbers up,
and so, we can create a helper function
aux.
It can take an additional argument and
accumulator.
Its base case can just return that
When we have our recursive call now, we
make sure it's tail-recursive.
There will be no more work to do by the
caller after we complete this call.
And we pass in, for our new accumulator,
xiii, + acc, so that we're adding thing
as we go.
And then, our initial accumulator, 0, is
what our base case was above when we had
our traditional version of sum.
So that was also a fairly easy example,
factorial and sum are fairly similar.
let's do a more interesting example.
This is something I haven't shown you
before.
Let's take a list and reverse it.
Okay? So if we get, had the list one,
two, three, we want to come up with a
list three, two, one. And it turns out,
in this case, the traditional version is
not very good and we're going to look at
why.
So I'd taken a list, xs'.
The way you reverse the empty list is you
return the empty list. No problem there.
Otherwise a-ha, we do want to recursively
reverse xs' prime.
Sorry,
that should be xs' prime right there.
and that's fine, but then what we need to
do is put x at the end.
Alright?
And it won't work to write cons X because
cons can't have a list in the first
position and an element in the second
position.
Now what we need to do is we need to make
a list holding x and then append to those
two lists together.
And it turns out that's remarkably
inefficient as what we'll talk about on
the next slide, but if we just do our
tail-recursive version, everything will
work out normally.
So here's the tail-recursive version.
Create a local helper function that takes
in the accumulator.
Let's start that accumulator with the
empty list. Let's pass in xs' for the
argument. nd here, if xs' is empty, then
just return the accumulator.
But now what we should do in the
recursive case, is yes, pass in xs' prime
for X is, and then this accumulator which
is the reversal of the list so far, we
just want to put x on the front of that.
Okay?
So if we were to reverse one, two, three,
the initial accumulator would be empty,
then the next accumulator would be one
cons on empty, then two cons on the one
on the empty.
And indeed, our natural accumulator
pattern is reversing the list quite
simply with a simple tail recursive
function and as we, as efficient as a
loop, it takes a list and produces a new
list that is the reverse of the list you
started with.
Okay.
So as promised dig a little deeper here
on what's so bad, so inefficient about
the traditional version.
Okay?
So it turns out that it's not just that
we're going to build up a call stack
every time here.
It's actually that this append operator
always copies the first list.
It has to that's how append works.
The same thing happens in the version of
append we would write whether append is
tail recursive or not.
So it turns out that this code, if you
were reversing a list of length
proportional to some number, let's call
it k.
The amount of work this is doing is
proportional to k squared.
It's growing quadratically with the
length of the list.
That was not true for factorial.
It is not true for sum.
It's because, when we have these k
recursive calls, one of them is going to
copy a list of length one, one a length
of list two, one a length of list three,
all the way up to one of list of length k
minus one, or maybe even k.
And the sum of the numbers from one to k?
Is approximately k squared over two.
It is only about, it is about half as big
as K squared.
And that is a lot more work then our
tail-recursive function.
Our tail recursive function did not use
this append, right?
It only used cons.
The total amount of work this bottom
version is doing is proportional to the
length of the list,
whereas the top version is doing a total
amount of work proportional to the length
of the list squared.
So this is an interesting point.
The moral here is don't just obsess about
whether you're tail-recursive or not.
You should also beware of appending
things,
that if you are recursively appending at
every step, your algorithm is sometimes
is significantly less efficient than you
might expect it to be.