I'd like to finish up our discussion of
tail recursion by giving a little bit of
perspective on how important it is, and
then talk about a more precise definition
of what it actually means to be a tail
call.
So, first of all, a lot of times when
people learn about tail recursion,
they're in a big hurry to make everything
tail-recursive and it's worth pointing
out that there are cases where you really
cannot do that.
Now technically speaking, you could make
every function call a tail-recursive
call, a tail call.
But you can't do it without building
other lists and data structures and
things that are going to take up just as
much space as your call stack would.
The most obvious examples are functions
that process trees.
When you're doing a recursive traversal
over the tree, you need to keep track of
what part of the tree you have visited
and you haven't so far and the call stack
is a great way to do that.
And you were generally not going to end
up with tail-recursive functions that
process trees.
You can usually use an auxiliary helper
function to make one of your recursive
calls, maybe the one over the left child
tail-recursive.
But then you somehow need to keep track
of what you need to do for the right
child.
So, you're welcome to try it and I think
you'll end up seeing that one of your
recursive calls will not be a tail call.
I would also make the more general point
that programmers are often in far too big
of a hurry to optimize their code.
a lot of programs we write, it's more
important that they be straightforward,
and readable, and easy to verify that
they do the right thing.
And oftentimes, a shorter, more natural
recursive function is perfectly good and
you can always go back and make a
tailrecursive function if it becomes
important.
The other thing I want to talk about is,
what exactly is a tail call?
So, so far, we have a perfectly good
informal definition. Alright?
This intuition that it's a call, where
after you make it, the caller has no more
work to do.
In other words, you have some call.
like F is going to call X,
and that result is the result for the
enclosing function.
Alright? But, that works, that's how I
think about it,
but how do you know if that's the
immediate result?
It turns out, like many things in
programming languages, there is an
elegant recursive definition of what it
means for a position in a function body
to be a tail position.
And then, a tail call is just any
function call that is in a tail position.
So a tail position is, there won't be
anything more to do afterwards.
Okay?
So I thought I would show you some of the
cases of this definition.
It's kind of a top-down recursive
definition about what it means to be in
tail position.
Alright?
So first of all, if an expression is not
in tail position, then neither will any
of its subexpressions be in tail
position.
Once something is not in tail position,
there's more work to do afterwards,
so none of the subexpressions are going
to be the last thing either, because
there will be even more work to do.
On a more positive note, if you have a
function definition, like fun f p = e,
the body itself is in tail position.
Okay?
So we start with the entire function body
and that is a tail position.
Now here's a recursive case.
If you have a conditional, like if e then
e2 else e3 or similarly for case
expressions, case e of a bunch of
branches.
The test that e1 between the if and the
then is not in tail position, because we
have more work to do afterwards.
But if the conditional is in tail
position, then, so are e2 and e3.
If there's nothing more to do after the
conditional, then there will be nothing
more to do after e2 and there'll be
nothing more to do after e3.
We'll do one of them and that will be the
last thing we do.
Let's do a local let expression.
If you have a let expression that is
itself in tail position, then the body e
is in tail position, because that also
will be something after which there is no
more work to do. So a call, if, if this e
were a function call, that would be a
tail call, but none of the expressions in
the bindings would be in tail position,
because we still have to do all the other
bindings and the body e.
Alright? And just as a final case, if you
have the parts of a function call, those
are not end tail position.
We have to evaluate e1, and afterwards,
we still have to evaluate e2.
We have to evaluate e2 and afterwards, we
still have to do the call.
So even if this call overall is in tail
position and is a tail call, any
subexpressions, any extra work we do in
e1 and e2, those are not in tail
position.
What this means is, if you ever have a
nested function call, like f of g of x,
f might be a tail call but g of x never
will be because the caller still has to
do the call to f afterwards.
So, as is often the case, we have our
intuition of no more work to do and then
we can make that definition more precise
in terms of the recursive structure of
our programming language.
And that is really enough to precisely
understand this idea of tail position,
tail calls, and tail-recursion.