[MUSIC] In this segment, I want to
introduce type synonyms which are a
seperate thing from what we've seen
before.
And a bit of a digression, of a
digression from data type bindings and
case expressions but nonetheless helpful
for the next homework and a nice contrast
with data type bindings.
So, data type bindings introduce a new
type name.
And that new type is different from every
other type.
The only way to make things of that type
is with the constructors that are part of
the data type binding.
A type synonym is a new construct I'm
showing you now for the first time.
And all you do is you write type, so
that's a new keyword, not datatype, just
type.
The name for the type, then equals, and
then another type.
And what I want to emphasize is that the
English word synonym is perfect here.
It just creates another name for the same
type that was already there.
And so now, we can use that name wherever
we were using t.
And we can use t wherever we might use
that name.
They're interchangeable in every way.
And I even want you to not worry about
which one the repel prints.
The two things, the type t and the name,
a name really can be used
interchangeably.
So, let's go over to some ml codes so I
can show you how this works.
So first, I have two datatype bindings
that we've seen before for suit and rank
and those behave just like they did
before.
But now, I also have a type synonym,
where I kind of remind myself and allow
myself to use in the program that
wherever I have a suit paired with a
rank, I can think of that as a type named
card.
So, the type card is a new type name that
will now be in my environment and it
means the pair of suit and rank.
So, I could write suit star rank or card
and that'll be fine.
Another common idiom by the way, that I'm
not going to use in the rest of the file
but I wanted to show is Is to give a name
to your record types.
It's a huge pain to write down this
record type anywhere or to remember, or
to even give a name for it.
So, instead of just having a comment that
says, this record is for describing the
names of people in my class along with
their student numbers,
I can go ahead in my program.
give a name to that type,
and then, use that type name wherever I
want,
okay?
So now, let me really emphasize this
interchangeability aspect.
So, here is a short function I wrote
called is_Queen_of_Spades.
It takes in a C of type card.
So notice, I can use that type name that
I introduced up here.
And it does the appropriate computation
of seeing if indeed, the suit is spades
and the rank is queen,
okay?
So now, here are three variable bindings,
c1, c2, and c3.
c3 is how we've been writing most of our
variable bindings where I just create a
pair of a Spade and an Ace.
And when you see that you might be asking
well what's the type of that?
Is it suit star rank or is it card?
And the answer is it's both because those
types are the same.
So, in fact c1 and c2
are both perfectly reasonable variable
declarations,
variable bindings.
It turns out you can write the type of a
variable if you want with a colon and
then, then, the type.
And the type checker will make sure
that's correct,
that the expression over here really does
have that type.
And what we'll see here when we go over
the REPL is all three of these,
c1, c2, and c3,
will type check just fine.
So,.
let's just, make sure that's right.
And they are.
We see all the bindings here.
You'll see the REPL printed our datatype
bindings,
our type synonyms.
Then this function is_Queen_of_Spades of
type card arrow bool and then it happened
to say that c1 is type card,
c2 is type suit star rank and c3 is type
suit star rank.
But I promise you that this works fine,
that type checks and runs, this type
checks and runs, and this type checks and
runs.
because anywhere you have card, it is the
same thing, it suits star rank.
So, I emphasize this because on your next
homework, we'll tell you to write
functions of certain types, like for
example card arrow bool.
And if you write a function and it seems
to work correctly but it prints out a
different type, like maybe suit star rank
arrow bool, I want you to recognize that
that's the same type and it's okay.
And the reason why that's going to come
up if I switch back to the code file here
is a little thing I haven't shown you
yet, which is soon we're going to write
functions like is_Queen_of_Spades
differently.
We're going to use case expressions for
that sort of code, too.
Even though suit star rank is actually a
pair, and not a datatype, it contains
datatypes.
And once we write is_Queen_of_Spades with
case expressions rather than in hash one
and hash two,
then we won't have to write types on our
arguments anymore.
We won't have to write c card.
We'll be able to just write c.
The only disadvantage of that is then the
REPL won't know whether we want to see
cards or suits star rank.
So, we'll just take whichever one it
happens to based on its own internal
procedures and internal algorithms.
But nonetheless, I find this style of
coding much more pleasant.
Just not writing down the types and
letting the type checker figure them out
for me for function parameters, the same
way we've been doing it for variable
bindings.
So, that's why this notion of type
synonyms and this interchangeability will
be so important.
it does raise an interesting question
though which is, why have this is your
language?
I mean, if it's really just a
convenience.
well, let's be honest, sometimes
convenient things for programmers are
worth putting in the language.
If you want to write CARD rather than
suit star rank, it's nice to have a
facility for doing that.
And the only confusion is that if you
wanted a function of type card arrow bool
and the REPL says, suit star rank arrow
bool, you have to realize that that's an
equivalent type and it's okay and it's
the same thing.
So, it doesn't really let us do anything
new, yet.
But in a couple weeks, later in the
course, we will build on top of these
type synonyms when we study ml's module
system.
And there we'll be able to do something
pretty special and we'll need these type
synonyms in order to do it.